Okay. So let's implement this function are
all even so let’s write first the prototype,
Bool are all even, and it should get an array
and it's logical size N. and let's start since
we are looking for a recursive implementation,
let's start with the base case. Base case
we're basically trying to solve the problem
for the smallest possible input. In this case
the size of the problem would be the number
of elements in the array.
So the more the elements are in the array
the bigger the problem is, the less elements
in the array the smaller the problem is the
smallest. The problem can be is when there
is a single element in the rate. So let's
check for this case: if we have, and N basically
tells us the number of elements in the array
so if N equals one that identifies the smallest
possible input. Now, let's have the solution
for this case; let's return the right value
in case that it is a single element array.
So in this case we just need to check whether
this single element is even or not, we can
use an IF statement modding it by two and
checking whether it's zero and returning true
or false. We can do the same in return statement
in the return line, so we can return the value
of A R R zero mod two equals zero. So if when
we're dividing the single element by two and
the remainder is zero, then this expression
here would be true and we would pass; this
true is a return value. But if the remainder
when we're dividing A R R zero by two would
not be zero, therefore it would be one, this
expression would be false and then we would
return the value false. So, that these two
lines of code here basically solve correctly
the base case, the scenario when we have the
smallest possible input. the recursive step
we are supposed to give the right value, the
right output for all other inputs for basically
arrays that are not single element arrays.
and we should use our induction assumption
that make it explicit, our assumption would
be if we call this function, if we call are
all even, this function, with a smaller instance
basically within an array of less elements
in it, then it would decide correctly it will
return correctly whether all of the elements
in this smaller array are all even or not.
In order to create a smaller instance, we
can just pass logically the first and minus
one elements.
So let's create a temp variable here: result.
And let's set result to be the result of calling
this function with the same starting address
but logically only N minus one elements. That
is obviously a smaller instance for this problem;
it is an N minus one array. And given this
assumption here calling the function on a
smaller instance would return the appropriate
value so res would be true if all of the first
and N minus one elements are all even, and
it would be false otherwise. So res almost
has all of the values we need here; all of
the result we need here. We just need to check
the last element; we need to check the last
element actually only in case that res is
true.
So, let's check if res is true then we're
not sure yet whether our result should be
true or false; we need to figure that out.
But if resists is not true, basically if res
is false, if not all of the elements in this
first N minus one elements of array are all
even that means that obviously not all of
the elements in the entire array are all even.
Therefore, we should return false. So if res
itself is false, if this smaller instance
is already false, obviously our value should
be false. Only the case where the first N
minus one elements are true is the case where
we need to figure out whether or were entire
array is also filled up with even elements.
So in this case we should just check the last
element and see whether it's even or not.
We should do something very similar to what
we've done for the single element array, but
instead of going for the first element we’ll
check the last element. So, we'll check whether
the last element A R R in the minus one index
mod two equals zero; if the remainder is zero
it means the last element is even, and since
all the rest of the elements are also evens
we would return that true. But if the last
element is not even, even though all the rest
of the elements are, we would still would
return the false.
So, it seems like this implementation here
is okay. Let's write a main program to test
it. First, let's declare this function and
our main, Let's keep it simple; let's create
an array in A R R, int A R R size 4, let's
put it in a few elements, two, twenty, forty
six, fourteen. And then let's just call this
function. So if are all even for this array
and four equals true then let’s print are
all even. Otherwise, let’s print not all
are even. We're expecting, obviously, that
all of them would be even in this case. Let’s
try to execute it; yeah, all are even.
Let's change it out; you know twenty three
see that it still works. Not all are even;
okay, good. Seems like our implementation
is fine. Let's take a final look here at this
implementation, as you can see we have the
base case where we solve the problem for the
smallest possible input, for a single sized
array. and then we have our inductive, or
recursive step, where we used our assumption
that calling this function on the smaller
instance would do the job would return true,
if the smaller instance contains only even
numbers. And we combine that for our original
input just by you checking for the last element
whether it's even or not. And that basically
is our recursive implementation for this function.