Let’s implement the factorial function.
So the prototype would be in factorial that
the parameter here is n. and we should start
with the base case; we should solve the problem
for the smallest possible input.
In the case of factorial the smallest possible
input, we're assuming that N is a positive
integer, so the smallest possible input is
when N equals 1.
Let’s identify this case when N equals 1,
that the case we are trying to solve here.
In this case the factorial of 1 is 1.
So let's just return 1 as our output.
Otherwise here we need to implement the recursive
step.
So our assumption would be that calling factorial
on smaller value than N would return the factorial.
in this case ,we already observe that pictorial
of N is basically N times the factorial of
N minus 1, so maybe we should just call factorial
for N minus 1 and multiply that by N. so converting
a single line of code but let me split it
into a few, let's create res local variable.
Let’s store in res, the result of calling
factorial with N minus 1.
that basically says that res now has factorial
of N minus 1 and we should then just multiply
res by N, that is the factorial of N. now
res would hold factorial of N we could just
return res for that matter.
That is totally all the implementation for
factorial.
Let's write a simple program that uses it.
So I'll just declare factorial up here, and
in my name let's cout factorial of four, basically
prints 24.
Let’s execute it; yep, prints 24 which is
exactly what we expected it to do. and when
we're looking back at this implementation,
we see that we used our assumption, we called
our function on a smaller input, and it did
what we asked it to do basically, to return
the factorial of N minus 1 and then we update
it we fixed this value in order to have the
value of the factorial of N basically by each
multiply by N. that was the whole idea here.