Recursion is basically a term used in several
disciplines.
In computer science, recursion is a problem
solving technique where we solve computational
of problems.
It is a very closely related to the mathematical
induction that we just spoke about.
The two are similar in some aspects; one of
the main aspects is the fact that both kind
of combine smaller instances for a larger
one.
So if we look at how we proved by induction.
We used an assumption of P on smaller values
in order to show that P is true on a larger
value.
Same thing kind of we're going to do here
with recursions.
So when we want to design a recursive algorithm,
we're going to give you a very high level
description of how we're going to design recursive
algorithms; later on we'll see if you will
demonstrate it using a few examples and you
get the hang of it.
But high level speaking, when we develop a
recursive algorithm, just as induction, it
has two steps: there is the base case/base
step and inductive or recursive step.
Now when we make recursive algorithm when
we use recursion, we use it as we said to
solve problems.
Not like induction where we use it to prove
statements, in recursion we solve problems,
because in computer science we solve computational
problems where in mathematics we prove statements.
So it would be very similar but then if in
induction in the base case we proved the statement
for the smallest possible value, in recursion
we're going to solve the problem for the smallest
possible input.
So that's what we're going to do in the base
we're going to solve our problem for the smallest
possible input.
In the recursive step, we're going to assume
that when we call the function on smaller
inputs it does what it has to do it does its
job.
And using that assumption we'll try to figure
out a way how to combine calls for smaller
instances, to solve the problem on a given
input.
Let's see how we do that.