Okay.
So we are now convinced that our implementation
really works.
As we said we use the smaller instance of
this problem, print ascending start and N minus
one.
That would print in entire elements in the
range from start to N minus one and followed
by the end would basically print the entire
range from start to end.
We can think of some other ways to use this
assumption of calling print ascending on a
smaller range and combining it in order to
print from start to end.
So given the range start and end taking the
range start to end minus one is obviously
a smaller range and calling this print ascending
really worked as we did.
But we can also, for example, call print ascending
not from start to end minus one but from start
plus one to end.
This call is also a call for a function on
an interval with a smaller range than the
original start and end.
By our assumption, this call should also do
its job or in fact it should print the numbers
from start plus one to end.
that is great because all we have left to
do here is just print start before we print
from start plus one to end; so that's another
version here.
Another implementation, another recursive
implementation, for the print ascending function.
We are first printing the value of start and
then calling the recursive function to do
the rest of the job: to print from start plus
one to end.
So if we have the range from start to end,
we can reduce it by calling start and end
minus one or by calling start plus one to
end.
Actually, we can think of another way or a
lot of other ways, but in another very interesting
way would say, instead of just reducing it
by one maybe we can take half the size of
the range.
So let's print the first half of the numbers
and after that we'll print the second half
of the numbers, for that let's first, I don't
know, calculate the middle point, which is
basically the average of starts and ends.
So, mid would be start plus end div to and
then we'll make two recursive calls: one to
print ascending from start up to the middle,
and the second to print from the middle plus
one, one after the middle, to end.
The first call by our assumption since it's
a smaller sized range; it would do the job
it would print from start to the middle all
of the numbers in ascending order.
and the second call since it is also a call
with a smaller size range, would bring the
numbers from mid plus one up to end.
Combining these two lines one after the other
would print the entire set of elements from
start to end in ascending order.
That's kind of cool; you must say?