Logically I believe or I hope I convinced
you that print ascending one and four works.
Let's see it in a more formal way.
Let's use our run time stack model, that basically
follows the actual way that programs are executed
inside our computer and let's see that using
this model print ascending one and four, also
prints one, two, three, four.
So, at the beginning we have a single frame
in our stack with a start equals one and end
equals four and we are at the beginning of
the function starting to execute it.
So we are checking if start equals to end,
in this case it does not, so we go to the
else clause and we call print ascending with
the start and end minus one.
that would create a new frame in our stack
with start equals one and end equals three,
and after we create this frame we jump to
the beginning of the function to store the
new functions execution.
So once again we check if starts equals end,
it does not so, we go to the else clause and
once again we have another function call here.
So we create a new frame in our stack, in
this case start is one and end is two, after
creating this frame we jump back to the beginning
of the function to start the execution of
this new call.
So we ask whether the start equals end, it
does not so we go to the else clause and unfortunately,
there is another function call.
That creates a new frame in our stack, in
this case start and end are both equal to
one; once again, we jump to the beginning
of this function to execute this call.
This time start is equal to end, so we see
out start, we print one that's our output
so far one.
And this call basically ends, so this this
frame is popped out and the one two frame
turns active.
We go back to where we came from we called,
this call the just ended right here in the
else clause.
So we go one statement after that to see out
end when we see out end in this active frame
and is two, so two is printed.
This call is also ended.
So we pop out this frame go back to where
we came from with one and three as the active
frame; we see out three this call also ends,
this frame pops out and we go back to where
we came from with one and four as the active
frame.
We see end and in this case would print four
and finally this last frame also pops out
and this initial call of print ascending,
one in four, basically ends.
As you can see this call here just printed
one, two, three, and four.
I know that this probably convinced you that
this implementation works for this function,
but then when we designed this algorithm we
didn't think of the runtime stack evaluation
that is going to occur.
We thought of it kind of an inductive manner;
how to combine a smaller instance of the problem
to be a solution for original input.