We’ve seen that there are two steps when we want
to solve a computational problem using recursion.
We've talked about the base case, the fact
that we solve the problem for the smallest
possible input and the recursive step where
we combine solutions to smaller instances
in order to solve the original of the given
problem.
Actually, we first define logically, it's
not any line of code that we find our assumption;
that calling the function on a smaller input
does whatever it has to do.
But given that in mind, we are trying to solve
our problem for the given input.
So we kind of make ourselves call the function
on a smaller input and try to see what fixes
we have to do in order to make it work for
the given input.
just the way we kind of proved by induction
where we in the induction step when we want
to prove that P of N is true we kind of make
ourselves use the assumption that P of N minus
one is true or all the values smaller than
N are true.
We kind of make yourself use this assumption
in the proof that P of N is true, same thing
in recursion we kind of makers of use or call
the function smaller inputs and try to fix
it, try to find a way to combine these calls
for creating a solution for the given input.
Let's try to see some more examples.
for example let's try to write a recursive
implementation of the function print ascending
and descending.
once again this function could get two parameters,
start and end; again we'll assume that start
is less or equal to N. but this time the function
given started and would print the numbers
from start to end in ascending order, followed
by the numbers in a descending order back
to start.
for example if we call print start and end
with three and five, it would print three,
four, five, four, three; it would printed
in an ascending and descending order.
Let's try to create a recursive implementation
of this problem here.
Starting with the base case, starting to solve
this problem on the smallest possible input.
Once again, this input for this problem is
measured by the number of elements in the
range from start to end.
Therefore, the smallest input possible is
the range of size one; we can identify it
by asking if start equals end, if it is equal
to end, the solution for this very small instance,
if we want to print ascending and descending
a single element range, it is basically just
printing that number; so cout start.
Quite easy, as we said the base case are typically
very straightforward.
But then let's see how we can solve all the
other cases.
First let's define the induction assumption.
If we call in this case our function print
ascending and descending on a smaller range,
it would do the job.
Basically it would print the numbers in the
range in ascending and descending order so
our assumption is if we call print ascending
and descending on a smaller range, it would
print the numbers as requested in an ascending
and descending order.
Let's try to use it in order to solve our
problem for the range of start to end.
So let's try to take a smaller range than
start to end.
For example, let's take start plus one to
end; let's think, what the call print ascending
and descending start plus one to end would
do? by our assumption, we said that if we
call this function on a smaller range, which
obviously is a smaller range start plus one
to end, it would print all the numbers in
that range in ascending and descending order.
So it would print from start plus one up to
end then back to start plus one, that's basically
most of what we need to do in order to print
the entire range from start to end in an ascending
and descending order.
We just need to print start before this and
print start after that so if we'll add two
cout statements before this call and after
this call, we would get a print of start and
then a print descending the range start plus
one to end then back to start plus one.
Followed by a last print of start, which would
all combine together, would print from start
to end and back to start.