Let’s write another function using recursion.
This time let’s write a recursive implementation
for the function: factorial.
This function, we already had an iterative
version of it, this time we’ll write a recursive
implementation.
Factorial, as you probably remember, should
get a positive integer as a parameter and
then it should return the factorial of that
value.
For example, if we’ll call factorial of
four, we’re expected to twenty four back.
That’s because one times two times three
times four is twenty four; four factorial
is twenty four.
Let’s take a look at factorial of N; so
factorial of N is N times N minus one, times
N minus two, and so on up to one.
We can definitely have an iterative implementation
for the factorial, as we already have, but
when we’re thinking or trying to implement
some sort of recursive implementation.
We should try to see how we can combine or
how we can define the factorial of N, with
smaller instances of the factorial problem.
In this case, we will probably see that one
times two times up to N minus one, is basically
N minus one factorial.
So, factorial of N is basically N times the
factorial of N minus one.
So given that observation in mind, we can
create a very easy recursive implementation.
Let’s go ahead to the computer and do that.