Okay.
So we're going to prove that for any natural
number N, two N square plus five N minus six
is greater or equal to zero.
Before we start just know that this statement
here is of the form for any natural number
and P of N is true, where this here are P
of N: two N square plus five N minus six greater
equal to zero, that's a P of N. Okay.
Let's start to disprove here; know there are
a lot of ways to show this statement here.
But we’ll use induction, you know, in order
to prove it.
So, it's first state that we will prove using
induction on N. And as we said there are two
steps: there is the base and there is the
inductive step.
So, let's start with the base.
The base: we are supposed to show that P of
one is true; basically, that this thing here
is true for any cause one.
And that's quite easy because for any cause
one, we get that two times one square plus
five times one minus six basically equals
to one which is greater or equal to zero just
as required.
Now, let's try to show; let's try to do the
inductive step.
So for the inductive step, we said that we're
going to assume that P of N minus one is true,
and under that assumption we'll show that
P of N is also true.
So we assume that P of N minus one is true,
that means we should just take N minus one
instead of N in our statement; two N minus
one square plus five N minus one minus six
is greater or equal to zero.
So, that's our assumption.
And we’ll show that under that assumption
two N square plus five N minus six is also
greater or equal to zero.
So, this here is our assumption and this here
is what we need to show.
And we’ll use our assumption for, to show
that thing.
So, okay.
So let's see; two N square plus five N minus
six.
Let's see how we can make it using our assumption.
So hopefully it would just be equal to two
N minus one square plus five N minus one minus
six.
If these two expressions were equal, using
our assumption we can just say that the right
hand side is greater or equal to zero and
therefore two N square plus five N minus six
is greater or equal to zero.
Unfortunately, they're not equal because of
this thing here is, and I'll simplify it,
it goes, gets to two N square plus N minus
nine.
So, we can fix this expression for it to be
equal and for that we would need, okay, so
two N square, we have on both sides.
On the left hand we have five N, on the right
hand we have, and so we need to add four N.
On the left hand we have negative six on the
right hand we have a negative nine so let's
just add three more, and now these two things
are equal to one another.
So, now that's very easy because, it's very
useful actually, because we know that this
thing here is greater or equal to zero; that's
our inductive assumption.
We also know that four N plus three, also,
is greater or equal to zero because N is greater
or equal to two, is a positive integer.
So, if we multiplied by four and add three
we would definitely get a positive number.
Therefore, these two add-ins, basically, are
greater equal to zero plus zero, which is
their zero.
All together, we get that two N square five
N minus six is greater or equal to zero.
So, the inductive step showed that given our
assumption: that's two N minus one squared
plus five N minus one minus six is greater
or equal to zero.
Given that assumption, we can then say that
two N square plus five N minus six, itself,
is greater or equal to zero.