Okay.
Let's try to use this technique in order to
solve the following problem.
Let's try to write a recursive implementation
for the function of print ascending.
Print ascending is supposed to get two arguments,
a start and an end, both are integers and
as the name kind of says, it should print
the numbers from start to end in an ascending order
So we will assume that start is less or
equal to N, so there is like a range of numbers,
a valid range of numbers to print and print
ascending should then print the numbers from
start to end.
For example if we'll call print ascending
one and four, it should then print the values
one, two, three, four in an ascending order.
Once again, we would need to make a recursive
implementation for this function, obviously
an iterative one is very straightforward,
but let's try to practice the recursion technique
on this example here to see how we can then
define recursive functions.
So, as we said there are two steps in solving
or creating/developing a recursive algorithm;
first one is the base case where we are supposed
to solve the problem for the smallest possible
value/smallest possible input.
So first we need to define what's the smallest
possible input, or maybe before that we should
even try to figure out how do we measure the
size of the input.
So we know that the inputs are start and end.
These are the input themselves but the size
of the input is a big difference so what should
be the size of print ascending start and end.
For example, if we use print ascending three
and six; what's the size of this instance?
I would say that the size of print ascending
three and six would be three, four, five,
six, N equals four, the number of elements
in the range from three to six.
Print ascending seven nine, would be seven,
eight, nine, the size would be three.
Again, the number of elements in the range
from seven to nine.
Print ascending five and five, the size would
be one.
There is only one number in the range from
five to five.
So, let's define N as the input size to be
the number of integers in the range from start
to end.
Saying that, it would be easier for us now
to solve the problem for the smallest input;
we know how to measure the size of the inputs.
So, the smaller input would basically be the
smallest valid range of numbers, basically
a range with a single number in it.
So if we want to solve the problem, solve
print ascending, with the smallest values/the
smallest size for start and end, if we try
to identify this case it would be when start
equals N. When start equals N, basically,
we are in the case where there is a single
element in the range from start to end.
So our solution for the smallest possible
input would start, if this is the case of
the smallest possible input.
If start equals to N, then let's see what
we should do in this case.
So, when we call print ascending with a single
element or a single integer range, the print
ascending should just print the single element
in that range, basically cout sort that is,
right?
So, this few lines of code basically solves
the problem for the smallest input; quite
straightforward, quite easy.
By the way just the same as mathematical induction,
the base case is a very easy step in the proof.
It's very easy to show that P of one is true,
most of the times.
Same here, solving the problem for the smallest
input is typically very easy; we just have
to identify the smallest input and the solution
is quite straightforward then.
The recursive step that's a bit more tricky.
The recursive step, as we said, we first need
to define the inductive assumption and then
we would need to use it in order to solve
the original of the given problem.
So we said that, generally, the inductive
assumption is something of the form if we
call the function on a smaller input it would
do its job. for print ascending, if we try
to make this assumption more specific here,
I would say something like if we call printer
sending on a smaller range it would print
the numbers in that range in an ascending
order.
Instead of the word function, if we call the
function I would say if we call print ascending
instead of saying on a smaller input I would
say on a smaller range.
So if we call print ascending on a smaller
range and instead of just saying it would
do its job, I would say it would as print
ascending should do print the numbers in the
range in ascending order.
So, this is a very powerful thing to assume;
we're assuming basically that calling the
function on a smaller input would do something,
actually it would do what it has to do it
would print the numbers in ascending order.
Having this powerful assumption, let's see
how we can use it in order to solve our original
problem of printing the numbers the entire
set of numbers from start to end.
So let's try to use this assumption let's
try to call print ascending on the smaller
range.
So, our original range is, let’s say, from
start to end.
Let's try to call this function on a smaller
range, for example, not from start to end
but from start to end minus one, that's a
smaller range.
What would happen if we call print ascending
start, end minus one?
Actually I don't know, but our assumption
says that if we call print ascending on a
smaller range it would print the numbers in
an ascending order.
So, since and end minus one is a smaller range,
this call here should print the numbers from
start to end minus one in ascending order.
Surprisingly probably a lot this call would
print the numbers from start to end minus
one.
That’s most of the job we need to do here;
we need to print the numbers from start to
end in ascending order, and this single line
of code already printed the line from start
to end minus one in ascending order.
The only thing left for us to do is just after
that is print the value of end.
These two lines combined together then would
print the entire range from start to end.
I know it is surprising; I know it is very
not intuitive the next we are will try to
show why it works.
I think maybe before the second video just
try it on your computer and make sure it does
work and get surprised a bit.