Let's talk about a variation, a more general
form of induction, called strong induction.
Strong induction is also a mathematical technique
to prove universal statements of the same
form, P of N is true for any natural number
N, but then the technique is a bit different.
This technique also has two steps: the base
case and the inductive step.
Base case, same as the regular mathematical
induction, we prove that P of one is true.
But the inductive step would be a bit different:
in regular induction we just prove that a
P of N minus one implies P of N, in the strong
induction we prove that if P is true for all
values more than N, that implies that P of
N is true.
So, our assumption here is stronger instead
of just assuming P of N minus one and using
that a single assumption to prove that P of
N is true, here we assume that P is true for
all values smaller than N. Basically that
P of N minus one is true, and P of N minus
two is true, and P of N minus three is true
and all values of P are true up to N; all
of that together should imply that P of N
is true.
We have a much stronger assumption here to
show that P of N is true; that's why it's
named strong induction.
Let's see why this technique basically can
be used in order to show that P of N is true
for all natural numbers N.
So, once again we prove that P of one is true,
in our base case, that means that we can conclude
that P of one and is true.
And then we show that P of one implies P of
two all values smaller than two are true,
basically P of one, means P of two is true
by showing this statement using the fact that
P of one is already true, we can conclude
that P. of two is true.
Then we also show that if P of one and P of
two are true, then P three is true.
Our assumption, the stronger assumption for
P of three was that all values smaller than
three are true; P of one and two are true.
That implies P of three is true and, in this
point of time, we already know that P of one
is true and that P of two is also true.
And therefore, we can say that P of three
is true.
Moving on, we showed that P of one, P of two,
and P of three, all of them together are true
that implies P of four.
Again, we already know that P of one and P
of two and P of three are all true.
Therefore, we can say safely that P of four
is true.
I believe you see that these things can go
on, and that way we basically show that all
P of N’s are true for all natural number
N’s.