Let's now go over branch instructions in MIPS64.
The two most fundamental branch instruction
in MIPS64 are Branch if equal, or BEQ, and
Branch if not equal, BNE.
Both branch instructions use relative target
calculation and have the same Function, labeled
func2, to calculate the address of the target
instruction.
Both instructions compare the values of two
registers to check their condition.
Branch if equal checks if the values of the
two registers are the same.
If so, the CPU branches to the calculated
target address.
Otherwise, the CPU goes to the next instruction
in the sequential code which is PC+4.
Branch if not equal checks if the values are
different.
If that is the case, the CPU branches to the
calculated target address
Several other branch instructions derived
from branch if equal and branch if not equal.
Such instructions are Branch if equal to zero,
branch if not equal to zero, branch if less
than zero, branch if less than or equal to
zero, any many more.
We focus primarily on branch if equal, branch
if not equal, and branch if equal to zero.
There is one terminology that is commonly
used when talking about conditional branches.
It is the “branch is taken/not taken”
term.
When one says a branch is taken, it means
that the condition that the branch checks
is true and the CPU branches to the target
address calculated.
Branch not taken means the opposite.