Let us now see some use cases of branch and
jump instructions.
Consider this high-level C code.
This is a function that calculates the absolute
value of a number.
That is, if the number is negative, it turns
it to a positive; otherwise, it keeps it as
is.
The value us returned from the functional
call.
As we see from the high-level code, there
is an if condition to check if the number
is negative.
This if condition in high-level code will
be translated to a conditional branch instruction.
We also notice there is a return instruction
to end the execution of the absolute value
function.
This return instruction will be translated
to a jump register, as it is the jump register
instruction that is used to return from function
calls.
Here are several approaches to translate the
if X is less than 0 condition into machine
code.
Let us assume that X is in register R4.
The simplest approach is to use the branch
if less than zero instruction.
In that case, if X is negative, the CPU would
skip the sequential instructions and branch
to the part of the code that perform X = minus
X in order to get the positive value.
Another way to is to use the branch if greater
or equal to zero condition.
In that case, X is positive, we would skip
the sequential instructions and branch to
the part of the code that does return X.
Otherwise, we would subtract.
Another way is to combine SLT with branch
if equal instruction.
The SLT instruction checks if X is less than
zero.
If it is, it set R8 to 1.
Otherwise, R8 is set to zero.
The branch instruction then checks R8 to zero.
If R8 is equal to zero, then x is positive,
the branch is taken, and the CPU branches
to the return instruction.
We will use this approach to further develop
the code for the absolute function.