So, now we have the code that handles the
if condition.
How do we write the rest of the code to complete
the function?
First, what instruction should be right after
the branch instruction?
In the sequence of the code, the instruction
following the branch must handle the case
where the branch condition is false and the
branch is not taken.
So in our example, the branch instruction
condition checks if X is positive.
Therefore, the next instruction in the sequence
handles the case where X is negative.
For our absolute function, when X is negative,
we need to negate it.
For that, we can simply use a doubleword sub
or DSUB instruction to negate R4 and turn
it into a positive value.
To find out what the instruction after the
subtraction should be, we again look at the
high-level code of the absolute value function.
We observe that once the subtraction is performed,
the next operation is to return from the function
call.
And we already know that if the branch condition
is true and X is already positive, we would
simply return from the function call.
In this respect, there is nothing left to
do in this code but to return from the call.
For this return instruction, we use the jump
register.
This jump register instruction is also where
we would do the branching to in case our branch
if equal condition is true.