So far, we have covered basic instructions
such as Load and store instructions to get
data from and to memory, as well as some arithmetic
and logic instructions. The arithmetic and
logic instructions we have covered so far
require that all operands to be first put
in registers. However, there are cases when
we write code and we use hardcoded values,
instead of variables, to perform arithmetic
and logic operations.
As the high-level code example highlights,
the second variable is hardcoded as 17. MIPS64
provides Immediate Arithmetic and Logic Instructions
for such high-level code. The basic idea of
an immediate ALU instruction is to store the
value of the hardcoded operand as part of
the 32-bit instruction. Several immediate
ALU instructions are provided including doubleword
ADD I, for addition, doubleword OR I for OR
operation, and doubleword AND I for AND operation.
The I at the end of each of these instructions
stands for immediate
Each immediate ALU instruction has a 16-bit
immediate value to store the hardcoded operand.
This 16-bit immediate is labeled, do I M M,
for Do Immediate in the semantics. For an
immediate arithmetic instruction such as doubleword
ADD I, this do immediate value must first
be sign-extended before the arithmetic operation
is performed. However, for an immediate logic
instruction such as D OR I or D AND I, the
do immediate value does not need to be extended.
It simply needs to be padded with zeroes to
reach 64 bits before the logic operation is
performed.