We will now discuss Jump instructions.
So far, the instructions we have covered only
allow us to write sequential code.
But what happens if we have function calls,
conditional statements, and loops in our code.
As we know, code that we write generally involves
these situations.
This is where jump instructions come into
play.
These instructions allow the CPU to skip chunks
of sequential code in the binary and to jump
to locations specific… to jump to locations
of specific instructions in that binary.
We call these locations target instructions.
There are two types of jump instructions:
unconditional jumps, where we always jump
to the target instructions, and conditional
jumps, where we branch to the target instructions
based on a given condition.
From now on, we will refer to unconditional
jumps simply as jumps and conditional jump
as branches.
Jump instructions are generally used for calling
functions and returning from them, whereas
branch instructions are used for if/else statements
and conditional loops
Another important factor in jump and branch
instructions is how far can the instructions
jump and how to calculate the target address
of that instruction we are jumping or branching
to.
There are generally two methods: one is called
relative branch or jump.
In this method, the target address is a function
of the program counter of the branch or jump
instruction.
The other method is called indirect branch,
where the target address is independent of
the program counter.
Relative branch and jump instructions restrict
how far the target addresses can be, usually
it is bounded within a few kilobytes of the
program counter.
On the other hand, indirect branch and jump
instructions obtain their target addresses
from registers or a memory and can, in theory,
take any value.