Let us now detail the MIPS64 jump instructions.
There are three such instructions: Jump, Jump
and Link, and Jump register.
Jump is commonly used when performing unconditional
jumps within a function or procedure.
This can be used for example for goto statements.
Jump and Link is used for function calls and
has two jobs: it first saves the return address
in the R31 register, and then updates the
program counter to the address of first instruction
of the function.
Note that the return address in this case
is the address of the instruction we must
return to when the function call has completed.
Jump register is used to return from a function
call.
Jump and Jump and link both use relative jump,
whereas Jump register uses indirect jump and
holds the address of the target instruction
in a register.