Let us now discuss how to calculate the target
addresses of the different jump instructions.
As mentioned before, Jump register uses indirect
jump, where it gets the target address from
a register.
Therefore, there is no calculation done, as
the address of the target instruction is simply
copied from the register RS to the program
counter
On the other hand, both Jump and Jump and
Link use the same function to calculate the
target address.
We label this function func1 and it uses the
program counter of the jump instruction and
another 26-bit parameter that we call address.
Note that this address parameter is not the
target address we are looking for.
Let's take a close look at the formula for
func1.
The first step is to increment the program
counter by 4.
In this instance, the program counter is the
address of the jump or the jump and link instruction.
The next step is to take the most significant
4 bits of the result from step 1.
This assumes that the program counter is 32
bits.
If we encounter a case where the program counter
is less than 32 bits, then we have to pad
it with zeroes to make it 32.
The third step is to take the address parameter…
to shift the address parameter left by 2,
which has the same effect as multiplying it
by 4.
This turns the 26-bit parameter to a 28-bit
parameter.
The last step is to concatenate the most significant
4 bits from step 2 with the 28 bits from step
3.
The result is the 32-bit address of the target
instruction.
Let us take a look at an example of how calculate
a target address for jump and link instructions.
Here we have a jump, where the program counter
is 4DC and the address parameter is 13B.
Note that all numbers are in hexadecimal.
We expand the program counter to 32 bits because
the formula for func2 expects 32-bit program
counters.
The first and second steps are straightforward;
this is because even after we do PC+4, the
most significant 4 bits of the program counter
are still 0.
For step 3, we multiply the address parameter
13B by 4.
Remember that this is a hexadecimal multiplication,
so the correct answer should be 4EC.
Then we expand the multiplication result to
make it 28 bits.
This is done by padding the result with zeroes.
The last step concatenates the results from
steps two and 3 respectively, giving us the
target address highlighted.