So what happens when we actually open up the
file?
Well the first thing is that the program,
your program, will ask the operating system
to open the file.
And what the operating system does, for output
files, is it checks to see if the file exists.
If the file does exist, it's going to be erased
and a new file created in its place; so you'll
lose the contents of that file.
If the file doesn't exist then it's created
and either way your program is going to receive
back the connection to that file, so that
then you can start to output to it.
It's really important that when you're finished
working with a file, that you close the file.
And there's a function inside the ofstream
object called close.
So you would just simply say out file dot
close, for example, and that would close the
connection.
Because when you're writing to a file what
you have to realize is that, you’re actually
sending information into a buffer; it's into
a memory space.
And the operating system is then told a periodic
interval to take the memory out of that memory
space and physically put it on the on the
hard drive.
What happens if your program crashes or the
system shuts down when your program has already
written to that memory and hasn't yet flushed
that buffer out to the hard drive; you lose
all that information, it's all completely
lost.
So it's best to make sure that you close the
file.
The other problem of course is that if we
have an output file we're doing writing to
this and, we remember on the discussion on
locks just a minute ago, that if we're out
putting information to a file we've locked
that file for reading.
So if you still have a connection to the file
if you still have the file object open, nobody
can read in and that includes you if your
program continues and tries to read in the
data that it just wrote out.
It won't be able to because of that locking
mechanism.
So it's really important you close that file
connection when you're done with it.
If the of stream object is destroyed because
it falls out of scope or if your program ends,
of course the file connection is closed in
the buffers flush so everything's written
at that point.
So you don't have to worry about it if your
program ends.
But if you're going to read in later on it's
really important that you close that file
and reopen it.