I just wanted to start by talking a little
bit about what we can do with outputting a
file.
So we'll go through the quick procedures of
how to create an output file and where that
information is stored and then we'll talk
about putting some information in the file.
So of course as we discussed the first thing
that's important is that we pound include
fstream.
Okay.
And from that point we then have options of
creating an ofstream object and I'll just
call my object, out file here.
When I do that I get an object of type a left
stream which I can write to and it's not at
this point connected to anything.
So we haven't specified a file name or anything
like that at this point, so we don't really
have a file.
In order to create or rather connect this
object to a physical file, we can do an open
operation and we can just give it like file
name or let's call it out file dot TXT.
And when that happens the file actually gets
created.
Now if the file already exists it's going
to be overwritten, we know that, and if the
file doesn't exist it's going to be created.
So I'm just going to compile this and give
it a run, just that we see.
Now the question becomes where are these files
created because we haven't specified where
the file is supposed to be created.
So what it's going to do is create it in what's
called the current directory, and for visual
studio the current directory actually is where
the CPP file is.
So I'm going to go ahead and open that here;
you can see I hope the folder view here and
I've got this CPP file and in the CPP file
I've got out file dot TXT.
So I've got the output file TXT; of course,
it's zero bytes because we have to put any
information into it.
So it was created here and you can see the
creation times 12:37 pm, if I run it again
I get a different creation time.
So now if I go back I'm going to see is 12:38
because now a minute later.
So we are creating those files successfully.
We also have the option of doing it in one
shot of just simply creating the output file
and calling the open using the constructor.
So I could have done this; although I'll comment
it out.
I could have done that because you'll see
the combination.
That would make it not necessary to call the
open operation on that file; it'll be opened.
How do we output thankfully we can use the
outfile object very much like we've been using
Cout since the beginning of the semester,
and here I have just a “hello world” and
I'm going to run that program.
Now you're going to see that there is some
information here in this output file a file
dot txt and if we open it up you're see “hello
world.”