So how do we, now that we have the file connection
open, how do we now read in from that I asked
stream object.
We've been doing it the same way with as with
the keyboard.
The only difference here is that in the keyboard
instance, we had to wait for the user to input
the information so that we could read it in
into our program; now everything is open and
everything is available inside the file, so
we don't have to actually wait for anything
to happen.
All the read in operations can happen before
anything proceeds we can do the entire read
in of the file before we proceed.
Now one of the questions is how do we detect
when we've run out of stuff in the file or
even better question is how do we detect if
the file never contained anything to begin
with; maybe it's just simply empty.
And you'll see a lot of books and a lot of
it's information on the internet about using
dot E.O.F. but I want to caution you against
using that because a lot of a lot of these
instances don't understand what E.O.F. does:
E.O.F. tells us that the end of file has been
reached.
But unfortunately recognizing that the end
of file has been reached requires that we
read in that end of file marker.
So if we open for example a completely empty
file then E.O.F. will not have been reached
because we haven't read in the end of file
marker, and if we start to then read in and
process information will be processing information
that doesn't really exist; we will have garbage
information.
So I caution you against using E.O.F. and
the better solution to that is to do a while
infile arrow arrow O. temp, and what that
does is read in the file read in a piece of
information into that temporary variable,
whatever the data type is not really important.
The first piece of information in the file
will be read in into that temporary variable
and then because we've contain this inside
of a while loop the while loop will test in
a infile in very much the same way that we
just tested it to make sure that it was open
successfully.
So it's a two-step process, which does both
the read in operation and the test to see
that it was successful.
So we've got a nice compact way of both reading
in and testing that it was successful at the
same time through this simple while loop format;
which works out a lot better than ever then
E.O.F. ever actually did.
The input operator, we have to understand
how that really works, and we might have gone
over it in the past but it really bears repeating
here.
The input operator in C++ is going to skip
over all leading whitespace characters; whitespace
characters are r your space your tab your
return characters anything which does formatting
inside the file but we don't actually see.
So, if you were open this in Notepad it shows
up white but it's really there.
It skips over all the leading whitespace characters
and then reads in any valid characters and
we’ll talk about what valid characters are
in just a minute and then it stops when it
reaches any trailing whitespace or any invalid
characters.
So that's the three step process that the
input operator is going to doL its going can
skip leading whitespace read invalid characters
and stop when it reaches trailing whitespace.
And if we put this in a loop and constantly
read in, then what we're going to be doing
is skipping any leading whitespace characters
reading in the valid characters and then stopping
at the trailing whitespace character but then
the next read in operation will skip over
those whitespace characters.
And if we've done this correctly we can read
in the entire file and when we get to the
end, we will have completed everything and
everything will be working exactly as we expected.
So, that's what we're going to aim to do in
reading in data.