So we can always use the ignore function if
we want to skip over a set of characters.
Now what the ignore function does is it allows
us to tell it how many characters we want
to skip or what character we want to stop
at skipping.
so you'll commonly see something like in File
dot ignore, and then nine nine nine nine and
then backslash n in a character in a single
character scene and single quotes there.
which means we're going to skip over nine
thousand nine hundred ninety nine characters
or the first return character that we see.
so it basically skips to the end of the line
as long as the line is not more than one thousand
nine hundred ninety nine characters.
and what this is useful for is if we want
to read in part of the line, not the whole
line, and then we want to skip to the end
of the line.
we can use the read in operation like the
input operator and then we can once we've
got the information that we want we just ignore
the rest of the line and then go back to using
the input operator to read in the next lines
piece of information that we want.
So the ignore function is actually a very
useful function.
Sometimes we might be at the end of the line,
because we just did an input operator and
we stop the trailing whitespace, the return
characters trailing whitespace, and the next
line we want to read in the whole line.
if all we did was a get line we would get
nothing because we were really looking at
the return character, but we can first do
it an ignore and skip over that return character
and then read in using the Get line then the
whole next line.
So get line and ignore kind of go together
and ignore is the solution to having to do
get line after we've done an input operation
using the input operator.
we put in ignore in the middle to make sure
that we skip over that return character and
the next line we're going to get the whole
line As opposed to a blank which is nothing
at the end of the line.