So, what happens if you want to do both reading
and writing, and I mentioned this before but
it's bears repeating.
Surprisingly, it's actually strange to want
to do both reading and writing at the same
time. and I know the concept that you have
in mind is one of like well what if I open
up a document in word and I want to edit that
document.
Well, what word actually does is read in the
entire file; it’ll read in your Word document
into main memory and when you make any changes
you're not making them in the file, you're
making them in main memory.
And anybody who's forgotten to save the file
knows exactly what I'm talking about because
when you go back if you hadn't saved it, it
won't remember any of those changes that you
made.
So what's happening is we're reading in the
file making the changes in memory and we're
writing back over the same file.
Which is useful because if we want to save
the information out we can either save it
out to the same file or we can save it out
to a different file altogether.
Now usually we'll read in that entire file,
will make those changes in memory and then
we'll write the file out to the disk and that's
a normal process to do; that means we're not
going to be doing both reading and writing
at the same time.
So what you would see is the opening of an
input file, the complete reading in operation
of the input file, and then calling close
on that input file.
Then we would do whatever changes are as necessary,
open the output file with the same file name,
write everything out and then close the output
file.
So that's really the process for doing both
reading and writing; in other words, in place
modification of the files is not a normal
thing to do.