In this module we saw how to open files for
both reading in and writing out.
We saw how to write out information to a file;
how to read in information from a file.
We talked about some of the pitfalls of opening
files as well as reading in and writing out.
We saw how the input operator works, specifically
the three-step process of skipping leading
whitespace and then reading invalid characters
and then stopping when it reaches trailing
whitespace.
We saw the use of the getLine function, the
ignore function, we saw a seekG, and we saw
how we can append onto the end of the file.
So at this point you should have the abilities
to write into your code file processing routines
so that you can bring in information directly
from a file.
And we can now you use very large datasets,
which allow us to do quite a bit of information
processing, and we don't have to worry about
a user sitting there for hours typing in on
the keyboard.