The first thing we have to understand is that
there's so much data that has to be entered
into most programs that it's really unreasonable
to ask the user to type it in at the keyboard
each time the program starts.
And of course we understand this from our
past experiences with Word and Excel and PowerPoint
and all the other regular programs that we
use generally store that information in a
file.
And a file is a nice compact way of keeping
track of all the data that's needed for a
particular run of a program.
There needs to be a way to access data on
the file system and in fact, we need to talk
about both the input and the output.
Input means bringing data from the file system
into our programs and using it for processing
or whatever we want to do with it.
Output means taking the data from our program
from main memory or from wherever we have
it stored in variables or vectors or arrays
or wherever, and putting it out on the file
system.
And this is actually a two part process; there's
actually two steps here.
So that when we're working on a file we would
have read that file initially, we would work
on it in main memory, and then we would output
that file back to the file system.