So C++ has an internal representation object
for the files.
So there's an object inside C++ which represents
our connection to the file.
The data type of that is going to differ based
on what we're going to do with it; whether
it's an input file or an output file.
And if we want to have an input file, then
the object type that we have to create is
called an ifstream.
And if we want to have an output file, then
the object type we have to create is an ofstream.
So it's fairly easy to remember these as fstream
objects, and the i is an input file stream
and the o is an output file stream so ifstream
or ofstream.
You have to create the appropriate type and
you can't change what you're going to do with
that file once it's created.
But of course you could always close it and
open it is a different type.