Cin and Cout are also objects.
We've been working with them over the past
few weeks and we didn't realize that they
are actually also objects and their data type
is an ifstream and an ofstream.
Now since we understand inheritance, we know
that an ifstream object is actually an istream
object as it's base class.
Every ifstream can be treated as if it were
an istream, and every ofstream can be treated
as if it were an ostream object or said another
way, if we design a function to accept istream
and ostream by reference of course objects
then we can also accept ifstream and ofstream
objects.
Which is a really nice convenient way of saying
that we can create a function that can accept
either a file or it can accept the screen
or keyboard for input and output.
And that's very helpful for debugging purposes
if we create a function to do all the processing,
to do all the output or all the input, and
then allow for debugging to send either Cout
or Cin to that function.