Here I'd like to demonstrate that we can actually
do this two different ways.
In the previous slide, you saw the method
that we used was creating a value for the
day, month, and year, and what I'd like to
show you here is that we can use what's called
the member initialization list.
So the constructor, if we put a colon at the
end of it and then we have a list of the data
members, and we don't have to have all of
them we can have some inside the member initialization
list and some initial-ised inside the code.
This allows us to construct the member variables
using whatever values we'd like.
But I'd also like you to take a look at the
other method, which is creating the data inside
the code for the class, without the use of
a member initialization list.
At this point it's really up to you which
you like to do.
I just want you to see both.
Later on there will be a situation where we
can only use the member initialization list,
but for now it's entirely up to you which
you'd like to use.