Now that we've created an object, for example
the date object, we have to take a look into
the object itself a little bit more.
And C++ has a really interesting structure
that it creates inside every object and it's
called this: this is actually a pointer which
points to the object itself.
It's sort of like a pointer back into itself.
And this pointer points to what we call the
calling object, so when you make a function
call like a dot set year, the this pointer
will be pointing to a inside the set your
function.
So it's really useful in a lot of cases, for
example, if you created a person class and
you wanted to have a recognition that the
person could be married for example.
Then each person would have a spouse pointer,
a pointer to another person so speak, and
when you get married, of course one person
marries the other person but then that second
person also marries the first person at the
exact same time.
So we would have a function call like a dot
marrying B, in which case A's spouse pointer
should point to B, and B's spouse pointer
should point back to A. And the only way that
we can get a pointer to a is with this, so
the this pointer is needed in a lot of situations
where we need to recognize that we have some
pointer back to the object that we're working
in right now.