A little while ago I mentioned that you could
either have an operator overloading as a member
or nonmember.
So what are the benefits of having one versus
the other; why do we have the option of doing
both.
Well first off, the key thing to remember
of course is that members have access to private.
So if we're a member of the class, if we overload
this operators a member of the class, then
we can directly access the private information.
And in a lot of cases we have to overload
it as a member because of those restrictions,
because we're not going to create functions
to allow everybody to access the private information;
we might not have an accessor function so
we want to have a limited access to the private
data, yet we want to have these operators
overloaded.
In that case the only choice is to make it
a member.
We also have the option, and this is a little
bit strange, but we also have the option of
listing a non-member function, as a friend,
if inside the class we write the signature,
which is the prototype of the function, we
write the function signature and before we
write friend.
Then we're not saying that that function is
a member of the class in fact it's by definition
a nonmember but it has access to private information.
So friend functions have direct access to
the private information, even though they’re
non-members.
And this is a little way of sidestepping the
private restrictions inside C++.
It is used in some cases and, is in fact used
often in the input and output operator, but
apart from those operators it's not used very
often because we consider it side stepping
around the rules, so we don't want to use
it.
Otherwise there's really one fundamental difference
between choosing member versus nonmember,
apart from the fact that it has access to
private.
If we're doing for example A plus B; A plus
B is going to work in either case whether
we choose to overload the plus operator as
a member or nonmember function, A plus B will
still work.
But if we have a constructor which can construct
an object out of constant like an integer,
then A plus five or A plus an object plus
A constant is going to work if there's a constructor,
which we can take five and construct one of
these objects.
So that would working again in either case
if we have that constructor; it'll work if
it's a member or nonmember.
But here's where life really gets interesting.
If we turn that around and we say five plus
A, well of course assuming that we have that
constructor that can construct one of these
objects out of a constant, five plus A will
only work if the plus operator is overloaded
as a non-member.
C++ has this restriction that it says that
because we now are going to require that the
left hand side is an object, we have to know
that it's not a constant object.
And the plus operator overloaded, if it's
a member is going to have to have full access
to the objects of the object will have to
exist before hand It will not be able to be
constructed automatically out of a constant.
So here, the only difference between choosing
member a nonmember is that a plus five will
work in either case but five plus A will only
work if we have a nonmember.
Generally speaking this is a small price to
pay for over for having access directly to
the private information.
So personally I usually make things members,
but there are a lot of purists in C++ who
prefer that you create only those items that
are members that have to have access to private.
And then create nonmember functions that are
based on the use of the member functions.
So for example, the plus operator you might
be able to overload by using the plus equal
operator.
So you’d overload the plus equal operator
as a member but the plus operator as a nonmember,
and then use the plus equal to solve the problem.
What you choose is entirely up to you; you’re
the programmer and you decide.