So now that we can talk about object oriented
programming, let's get into what we can do
in this module.
We'll give a definition for an object and
a class, we’ll talk about the concept of
encapsulation, we're talk about how to create
a class, enforcing protections and access,
mechanisms for class accessors and mutators,
and we'll talk about the constant modifier.
We're also going to talk about how to guarantee
that an object is created properly.
We'll talk about using operators on classes
and we'll talk about classes that contain
dynamic memory.
We're also going to get into concepts of inheritance
and polymorphism.
And we'll talk about dynamic binding as well
as pure virtual functions.