We've got an interesting problem that we've
got to take into account here, and that is
that if the class contains any dynamic memory
then there is an issue that comes up with
what we call shallow copy.
So all classes have a leftover of C's struct
era, where they'll have an assignment operator
and what we call a copy constructor, a constructor
that can copy an existing object.
That's really a left over C++ because with
structs we were always able to say A equals
B and all the data members would be copied
over.
Unfortunately, because we're in C++ and we
are using pointers, where pointers are involved
those built in operators are going to copy
the pointers instead of copying where the
pointers of pointing to.
And that's really problematic and this is
known as what's called a shallow copy.
So I'm going to show you some code here.
What we've got is we've got a class called
thing, it's very boring, but it contains a
pointer to a value.
And the thing object constructor is going
to create a new integer on the heap which
is going to store that value.
So here in main I'm creating thing one and
thing two, and yes that is a Dr. Seuss reference
in case you get it.
And what I want you to see is that thing one
has a value that points to the value one,
and thing two has a value pointer that points
integer two on the heap.
So on the heap we've got these two integers,
one and two, and we've got on the stack we've
got two variables, variable one and variable
two, each have a value pointer.
And the value pointers pointing appropriately,
so on the surface this all works perfectly
fine and everything's okay.
But when we set one equal to two, when we
say one equals two, that has the effect of
copying the pointers.
And now that we've copied the pointers, we
have the value pointers both pointing at the
same object on the heap, instead of the same
object holding the same value.
So if we looked at the value in object one
we would see two and if we look at the value
in object two we would see two but the problem
is that those two pointers are actually pointing
to the same thing.
And what happened to the variable, the integer
that object one was pointing at, it's a memory
leak.
So here we've created a memory leak; just
by copying an object.
And we can’t allow that to happen; so we've
got to find a solution to this.