Now that we’ve seen the problem, let's take
a look at the solution.
Well we're going to need to overload; we're
going to need to change copy operations.
The copy operations need to copy the data
and not the pointers, and that's what is really
the solution to this problem.
Since we're creating memory in the constructor,
we're going to need to also destroy that memory
at some point.
Now we haven't talked about this yet but if
you look back at the code when main ends,
the data that was created on the heap isn't
ever released; we never call delete for that
data.
So really what we've got are a couple of problems
and the solution to that is what we call the
Big Three.
And the Big Three is a set of functions that
if we need any one of them were going to need
them all, and that's almost with one hundred
percent certainty.
There are very, very rare situations where
we might need one copy constructor, for example,
we wanted one copy constructor and not need
the other two but it's very, very rare.
So we call them the big three because if you're
going to, if you realize you need any one
of them you better create all three of them.
The destructor is just like a constructor
but the exact opposite; the destructor is
called automatically when the object falls
out of scope.
So at the end of a function call when the
object is no longer going to be used, the
destructor is called automatically.
In the same way that the constructor was called
when you created this thing, the destructor
is going to be called when it's no longer
in use.
We also have the copy constructor, which is
useful if we want to create an object based
on another object; so we might have a copy
constructor for the date class that takes
in an existing date.
And the assignment operators, the third one,
it copies one object to another copy and it
does that sort of deep copy.
So here we have to be very careful because
in a lot of situations that we're going to
run across, what we have to do first is clear
out the left hand side object.
So we might have to empty everything out the
left hand side object.
And there is one situation that the assignment
operator has to take into account and that
is self-assignment.
If the user is doing something very, very
silly and ends up writing something like X
equals X, then clearing out the left hand
side object will accidentally clear out the
right hand side that we're about to make a
copy of.
And so that we've lost that information that
we had intended to make a copy of.
To protect against that the code that we like
to use is just a simple if statement it’s:
if this equal equal the address of RHS.
And in doing that what we're doing is testing
to see if the this pointer is the same as
the thing that we're about to copy, the pointer
to the thing that we're about to copy, and
if those two are the same pointer then really
the pointing at the same object which means
we really don't need to do any work we can
just return star this.
So the big three is the solution to the problem
of dynamic memory, and I'll give you the code
here to take a look at it.
You can see the big three: the destructor,
the copy constructor and the assignment operator,
are really just a couple of pieces of simple
code to take care of what has to be done in
terms of a deep copy and in terms of destruction
of the object.