So we want to look at the set name function
because the set name function inside cat is
going to do something different then just
set the name.
We have a rule that says if we change the
name of our cats we have to cut off their
whiskers; I don't know this is a crazy rule,
but that's what it is.
And so we have to set that whisker length
back to zero any time somebody changes the
name of a pet.
Now how do we do that?
Whisker length is a member of the cat class;
only cat can change the whisker length.
But name is a member of the pet class and
only pet can change the name; so how do we
do it?
Well, we override the set name function so
that if anybody has a cat and sets its name
the first thing we're going to do is change
the whisker line but we also have to go back
and actually set the name because at this
point we've overridden the function.
This is the new version of the function sequence;
C++ will not automatically go and call pets
set name if what we're working on is a cat
object.
So what we do is use the scope resolution
operator and indicate the name of the base
class function, in this case pet, to indicate
that what we're calling is the set name function
inside the pet class.
If we didn't have this we'd have recursion.
If we just said set name; we would be the
function calling itself would be calling cats
set name function which would be a horrible
loop that we'd never get out of.
So what we do is we indicate that we're calling
the pets set name function and then we pass
in the name.
We effectively have the solution of solving
both problems, setting the whisker length
and changing the name, in one easy function.