From time to time, there's going to be situations,
of course, where we have to have allowance
for the derived class to access the base classes’
private member variables.
And we can't make them private in that case;
so there's no friend possibility here.
But what sequels post does create is something
called protected.
The protected modifier is added, now we now
have public, private, and protected.
Protected is specifically for this purpose:
it allows a derived member function to access
a base class’s protected information.
But it doesn't allow any access outside of
those two classes: outside of the base class
or the derived class.
So if we're inside main protected in private
or fact of the same thing but if we're inside
a derived class we would not have access to
the private information, whereas we would
have access to the protected information.
It doesn't change anything Internal to the
class; so it's only in the case of inheritance
that protected becomes useful because that's
when the derived class would exist.
And it would have access to those items marked
as protected inside the base class.