This is a topic I actually really like; it's
polymorphism.
And what we're saying is that since every
cat is a pet, we should be able to copy data
between cats and pets.
Now if we take a look at main memory, what
we're going to see is that inside every cat
there is a pet object.
Not in reality that there is a pet inside,
But what we're going to see is that all the
stuff that is in pet is also in cat.
So if we have a function which expects to
take a pet, it could take a cat because the
cat class will have all the items that exist
inside the pet class.
It's going to have more in this case is going
to have whisker length but it's going to have
everything that was inside the pet.
All the functions, all the data, everything
that we should be able to do with a pet we
should also be able to do with a cat.
So since every cat is a pet every cat is going
to contain all of the functions inside pet,
though not necessarily the same versions and
that's where one of the problems really comes
along.
Polymorphism in C++ allows us to copy the
data over from a cat into a pet object.
And that's what I want to want to show you
here with a little bit of code.
What I've done is create a pet object and
a pet pointer and as well as a cat object
and a cat pointer and we're going to look
at a couple of examples here.
If we take a cat and try and store it in a
pet, this always works, this is always allowed;
it's a solution known as slicing.
So taking a cat object and storing it into
a pet in this case, P equals C that will always
work.
But what happens is those objects, those items,
of the pet that are in class are copied over.
What happens to the whisker like this; it's
just completely lost.
So in our example we'll be copying over the
name of the cat will be copying over the pet
ID of the cat and we’ll store that in the
pet object but we can't fit the whisker length,
so we just don't copy it.
It's very much like when you took an integer
and you stored a double in that integer; it's
just chopped off the decimal point and threw
away all the stuff after the decimal point,
didn't do any rounding or anything like that.
We can also copy information from a pet and
sort of upgrade it to that of a cat, but C++
doesn't do this automatically.
C++ won’t allow this to be done automatically;
what we will have to do is overload the assignment
operator.
So inside the cat’s class inside the cat
class, if we overload the assignment operator
to take a pet object then we'll get this upgrade
possibility because the cat class will know
what to do, will know what value to set and
whisker length.
It will copy over or it should copy over those
items that are in the pet manually and then
you can have whatever value for whisker length
you deem appropriate, maybe at zero maybe
not, I don't know.
But the point is that if we overload the assignment
operator for a pet inside the cat class, we're
allowed to do cat equals pet.
The pet pointer being assigned to a cat will
always be allowed; and this is the real core
of polymorphism this where the magic really
happens.
Because we have a base class pointer, we can
make it point to a derived class object because
the derived class object will contain all
the functions and all the data that are in
the base class.
So the pointer can point to a derived class
object and we haven't lost anything.
It's really important to recognize the difference
here between slicing P equal C and polymorphous
P pointer equals the address of C. In one
case we're taking the cat information in the
slicing case we're taking the cat information
and storing it into an object that actually
is a pet; and the other case we're taking
a pet pointer and making it point to a cat.
So polymorphism is not working with pets,
it's working with pet pointers that are pointing
to cats.
And that's a huge difference because we have
to recognize that the pet pointer is not pointing
at a pet; it's pointing at a cat or maybe
it's pointing at a dog or a fish or a turtle
or whatever kind of pet you want.
But the point here is that the pointer can
point to any data type as long as it's derived
data type of the pet class.
All the pet functions, all the pet data is
still going to be in those derived class objects
so it's allowed.
Again we've got to keep in mind that the versions
of the functions might be different so that's
going to become an issue in the next slide.
But for right now we can recognize that everything
that's in the base class object will also
be in the derived class object.
If we do have that pointer, the only things
that we can use are those things that exist
in the base class.
So we can't change the whisker length via
the P pointer, we can't change the cat's whisker
length, even though it is a cat object; P
pointer is a base pointer and the only things
were allowed to access are those things that
exist in the base.
So we can set the name and we can set the
pet ID number but we can't set the whiskered
length using in the pet pointer, we need a
cat pointer to do that.
And one thing that's very important to recognize
is that we can never take a cat pointer and
make it point to a pet object.
We're never allowed to do assignment between
the data type pet pointer and the data type
cat pointer.
Even though they're both just pointers and
even if the pet pointer is actually pointing
at a cat, C++ will not allow us ever to copy
the pet pointer into a cat pointer.
So what we're doing here with CPTR equals
to the address of P. There's no way to make
that work in C++.