If we go back to our previous example of having
a base class pointer point to a derived class
object; C++ makes some interesting assumptions.
First off, by default C++ assumes that a base
class pointer points to a base class object.
And that is not at all true because polymorphism
tells us that we can make a base class pointer
point to a derived class object.
But C++, for good reason, tries to optimize
things and say that if we have a base class
pointer we can assume that it's pointing to
a base class object.
Unfortunately, that means that if we call
any functions via that base class pointer,
the function version that we're going to be
calling is that of the base class even if
the pointer actually points to the derived
class object.
So if we, for example in our previous example
if you want to take a look at the code going
back, if you take a look at the code for the
pet object there is a function called speak.
And if we call that function on a base pointer,
on a pet pointer, we will get no output even
if the pointer is pointing in a clear cat
object.
So by default, we've got this issue where
the base class pointer might be pointing to
a derived class object and we call the wrong
version of the function; that could be catastrophic.
Imagine if the destructor for the base class
was called but what we wanted to destroy was
the derived class.
That would be absolutely catastrophic; we'd
have a memory leak.
The solution to this is to mark the function
as virtual in the base class.
If we put virtual in the base class then C++
waits until run time to make the decision
on what your version of the function to call.
So if we have a base class pointer and were
accessing a function which is marked as virtual
C++ stops and says: I don't know which version
to call, I'll wait until I can actually see
what object I'm working on and then I'll call
the version appropriate for that object.
So rather than make the static binding decision,
rather than decide which version of the function
we're going to call at compile time, we do
what's called late or dynamic binding at run
time when we actually see the object that's
when C++ will make the decision of which version
of the function to call.
The version of the function call depends on
the type of object not the type of pointer.
And that's the way that we can get around
the problem of accessing derived classes functions
via the base class pointer.