There are some situations as you can see where
we might not know what the base class should
do, but we know that the function should exist.
What kind of noise does a pet make?
It's a question we really can't answer; until
we know what type of pet this is we can ask
the pet to speak although all pets can speak.
Alright fish make some sort of “blub blub”
noise; I don't know.
But the point is that the pet class should
have a speak member function we don't know
how to make a pet speak.
All the pets that we're going to create cats
and dogs and fish and turtles, and I don't
know what else, are going to have a function
called speak.
And we want to be able to use the base class
pointer to access that speak function.
So if the base class should contain a function
but it doesn't know what the function should
actually do, the function can be marked as
pure virtual with the equals zero.
So here's the code that we're going to look
at.
The idea here is that we have the best pet
class and we have the speak function.
And speak function is going to be virtual,
of course, but we don't know what the speak
function should do.
So we'll make it pure virtual; we'll set it
equal zero.
And in doing so, it allows us to use the pet
class pointer to call the speak function,
in fact inside the pet class itself we could
even call the speak function.
But we don't know how to actually perform
the code for the speak function until it's
defined later inside the cat class.
So if you see the cat will override the speak
function and print out meow in this case,
and what we've got is the ability to have
a pet pointer pointing to a cat object and
call the speak function of that cat object.
Now there are some restrictions though: because
the speak function is pure virtual it causes
the pet class to become what we call an abstract
class.
Abstract classes have a lot of restrictions
on them whereas we can create pointers to
an abstract class; we can never instantiate
an abstract class.
We can't create an object of type pet, because
if we were allowed to create an object of
type pet then we could possibly call the speak
function and then we don't know how to do
that.
So C++ says if you have even one pure virtual
function you can't create an object of this
class.
So what can we do?
We can create pointers and we can derive from
this class.
So that pet becomes useful as a base class
but we can never create an object of it; we
can create pointers to lots of pets and they
can point to objects which override the speaker
function and provide the code.
But if any of the derived classes contain
pure virtual functions, because the either
have it overridden or they've created new
pure virtual functions, then they too are
abstract classes.
In this case the cat class is perfectly fine;
we can create an object of the cat class and
have a pet pointer point to it.