The idea of object orientation came out in
the early 1980’s because we had an enormous
number of functions and we had data not associated
with the functions.
So programmers would have to pass a large
amount of data to a function to perform a
specific task on that data and if the data
got disconnected from each other, from the
different parts of the data, we would have
a loss of information.
So what the concept came about was to put
all of this data into one capsule, encapsulation,
and have functions that can work on that data
as a single atomic entity.
So we can create in code something that exists
in real life which contains enormous amount
of information, enormous number of pieces
of data, and we can combine them and have
functions that operate on that data at the
same time.
We use classes in C++ to protect the information
so that it can’t be changed from the outside
world.
So from anything outside the class it wouldn’t
have unrestricted access to the data inside
the class; we only have access from the functions
inside the class.
It allows us to do multiple atomic operations
inside a single function that has to change
lots of data.
So it’s not just asking a user or a programmer
to make one change then a second change, because
we know that the programmer invariably will
do the first change but forget to do the second
change.
Now we can create a function that solves the
program to make both changes.
It enforces the idea that the designer of
the class knows best about what to do, rather
than having a set of documentation which tells
a programmer outside what to do.
So the model that I like to employ, the model
that I like to use to visual this, is that
of a card shuffler inside a Vegas casino.
So if you’ve ever been to Las Vegas you’ve
seen these card shufflers and what they do
is they continuously shuffle these cards,
the deck of cards.
And when new cards come in, they get added
to the shuffle so that nobody can count the
cards and know what’s gonna come out next.
But the point is that they’re a single contained
item, and what happens inside is sor5t of
a black box.
We don’t know what happens inside.
But as the dealer puts more cards in and takes
more cards out, what is happening inside is
controlled by the designers of the card shufflers.