Here what I've done is create a dog class.
And the dog class is defined as being having
a class as the base class and it also creates
a speak function.
Dogs have ears but that's not important; we
don’t care about the ear size.
The speak function here will woof instead
of meow.
And now what I can do in main is create an
array of three pet pointers.
Now it may be a little bit strange to see
the pet star star there, but what I'm saying
is that the array is in array of three pet
pointers.
If I created the array as three pet objects;
I would not get any polymorphism.
Because polymorphism requires that we're using
a pointer to access the object and it requires
that the function we're calling is virtual.
So here I need three pointers to pets not
three pets: I set the first pointer equal
to a cat, I set the second pointer equal to
a dog, and I set the third pointer equal to
a cat.
And then I can use a for loop to go through
and make all those pets speak.
And what I think is great is that if you look
at that last line of code, we're making a
function call to the speak function via a
pet pointer.
And we have C++ deciding at run time, which
version of the function is going to be called.
So it doesn't know which version of the function
to call until we actually get to the point
in the code, the very nanosecond that C++
is running, that the computer is running that
code and it says: oh I'm looking at a cat
object so I will call them in the cat's function
for speak and I will meow, or I'm looking
at a dog object and I'm going to print out
woof.
So I think that really kind of almost magical,
the way that C++ can take the virtual function
and a pointer to the base class and decide
which object it's actually looking at and
call the appropriate function.