We went over a lot in this module; and I know
it's like drinking from a fire hose right
now.
But we did talk about the definition of the
object in class; we talked about the whole
concept of encapsulation.
We talked about creation of a class and the
enforcement of protections on the class.
We talked about accessors and mutators, and
the const modifier.
We talked about constructors and how to guarantee
that they were constructed properly.
We talked about using operators on classes
and we talked about classes that contain dynamic
memory, and then we went into inheritance
and polymorphism.
There's a lot having to do with object orientation
and the amount that you have to capture for
this module is really significant, but once
you kind of get your head around the whole
idea that we're working with data and the
functions to work on that data as a single
entity, it really starts to become a little
bit obvious.
So I hope you are able to follow along with
it and if not e-mail us with any questions.
Thanks.