So first it helps to define what the term’s
class and object are. and for our class we
consider that a framework which is used to
build multiple objects which are similar.
So for example you might think of a blueprint
for a house as a class.
The idea is it's the framework that we're
going to build the object around; it tells
us everything about what's going to be inside
the class but it doesn't tell us what the
values of the data are for example.
The object is just an instance of a class;
it's a class instantiated.
So when we create one of these variables,
we have an object and for that.
I'll use the example of a house or a cookie,
so going back to our previous examples of
the blueprint for the house with a cookie
cutter for baking.
We can talk about the object being the House
or the cookie and of course we don't try and
live in the blueprint, we want to live in
the house and if we don't want to eat the
cookie cutter, because it doesn't taste very
good, we'd rather eat the cookie.