The previous code we looked at was a really
simplistic view of a class.
And the problem with the simplistic view of
a class is that it's storing three integers,
and integers, the domain of an integer is
negative two point one billion to positive
two point one billion.
Now I don't know what it means if the day
is negative two point one billion or the day
is positive three hundred thousand, it really
doesn't make sense because in our model in
our world, the day can't be a number outside
the range of one to thirty one.
So rather than allowing uncontrolled or what
we call public access previously, we should
really protect that data and we should mark
the data as being private.
Now one thing to note is that if we leave
off the notation of private or public, then
by default C++ assumes that what we want is
private.
So we can modify the class now to change that
public keyword to be a private keyword.
And now nobody outside of the date class,
can access day, month, or year.
And that means change it print it do anything
with it; nobody has access to those three
variables.