Well now unfortunately since nobody has access
to day, month, and year; nobody can store
anything into day, month, and year.
Nobody can get out the day, month, and year.
So what we've done is create a fairly useless
class, because day, month, and year are completely
inaccessible by anybody.
What we really need here are something called
accessors and mutators, less formally known
as getters and setters.
So the accessors are used to get information
out of the class and the mutator are used
to put information into the class, and that
doesn't mean uncontrolled access, what it
means is that we can restrict the access so
that the values stored in day, month, and
year are going to be reasonable.
So we create three functions here that will
act as the mutators; so we've got the set
day, set month, and set year function, and
what I've done is I've created set year as
a function inside the class defined inside
the class, and set day and set months defined
outside of the class.
I'm only doing that for demonstration purposes.
There's really no difference in the code for
creating it inside the class versus creating
it outside the class; they both work exactly
the same.
But what I'm careful to do is not create a
lot of code, not to write a lot of code, inside
the class because it tends to make things
a little bit less easy to read.
So in this case, all three functions are members
of the class which means that they have access
to all of the private information.
So this is the idea of encapsulation that
members of the class will have access to the
private information inside the class.
And here what I can see from the set day function,
if you take a close look at it is, it restricts
the setting of the day variable to make sure
that the day does not go outside the range
of one to thirty one.
Now you'll notice that I have not passed in
any other variable besides the new value that
I'm trying to set and I have access directly
to the day variable inside the class.
As a member of the class, I have access to
all the data members inside the class and
all of functions inside the class and I can
do that directly without any extra definitions.
So the set day and the set month are just
definitions that I've put outside the class
and to do so, I need the scope resolution
operator.
But you can see that the code keeps track
of making sure that the day and the month
are reasonable values, so that we can't set
something that's completely outside what we
normally expect.