Now that we've got the mutators, we can change
the data but that doesn't give us any access
to actually view what's in there; so we can
store it but we can't change it.
If we are going to create a function that
is going to access information inside the
class but not make any changes to the to the
data inside the class, then we really need
to mark that function as being a const function.
what a const function means is that the object
from the start of the function to the end
of the function will not change.
and it's a protection mechanism to make sure
that we don't accidentally make any mistakes
by changing variables.
So the same as we would use const during our
previous programming samples, we now can use
const to protect our objects from accidental
damage by ourselves, the programmers.
Now there is one thing to take into account
when we have const functions.
If an object is const-ified, so if for example
we were to pass an object to a function and
we will pass that object by const reference
which is very common to do, then the only
functions we have access to inside that function
is a const function inside the object.
So here now if the object is const-ified,
the only functions that we can call are const-ified
functions inside the object.
It's a protection mechanism from C++ to make
sure that we can't do more than what the function
can do.