One of the problems a lot of students have
with linked lists is the idea of whether they
should stop at the last node and do some more,
or whether they need to go off into the null.
And this often comes down to a lack of understanding
with when to stop.
So I'd like to go over that at this point.
Both solutions are going to use a while loop,
but the conditions inside those while loops
are going to be slightly different.
Stopping at the end means that we want to
run the while loop as long as the next pointer
in the node that we're looking at is not equal
to the null pointer.
Now that requires that we keep a little bit
of track of the current pointer.
And it also requires that we're very careful
that we make sure that we have at least one
node, because if we start a temp pointer at
null and we say temp pointer is next, then
we've just de-ref null and the program crashed.
So we've got to make sure that the linked
list has at least one node and if we can do
that then we can advance that temporary pointer
until we reach the very end of the linked
list, the very last node in the linked list.
However, if what we want to do for example
is count the number of nodes on the list then
we want to include that last node and we want
to go until the temporary pointer equals the
null pointer.
Here's the biggest problem: we can't go backwards.
Once we've reached know all we can't take
a step back and move to the last node, so
we've got to decide from the beginning whether
we should go and stop at the last note or
whether we should go off the end of the last
node because we don't even need it.
Here's a here's a size function so here's
the function that size and what it does a
starts a simple counter at zero sets the temporary
pointer equal to head and runs that while
loop until the temporary pointer gets to null
pointer.
It really is just advancing that temporary
pointer; you see that line of code that says
temp equals temps next, temp arrow next that
line of code is going to advance that point
or node by node and we're going to update
the counter.
When we're done temp is going to be equal
to the null pointer and we're done, we've
counted all the nodes.
So if you take a look at a couple of views
of this, if the list is empty to begin with
then temp equals no all temp equals had causes
temp to be null, we don't do anything in the
while loop and we will return zero which makes
sense because list is empty.
So that's the simple idea of how to do a size
function but if we want to see how to do some
work at the end like an insertion at the end
assuming we don't have a tail pointer.
Then the first thing to check of course is
to see if the list is empty and if the list
is empty, then an insert at the end is the
same as the insert at the head.
So let's just go ahead and use that code again
so we can reuse that inserted head code.
But assuming that there are some nodes on
the list, we're going to have to go search
for the last note on the list and that's what
this…
That's what this function is going to do here.
The temporary pointer points at the new node
that we're going to create.
And now it's time to find out where to insert
this new node so we have the end pointer and
calling end pointer and we say while ends
next is not equal to null pointer then we
just advance that and pointer.
Of course this is a linear time problem, it's
big O of N to find the last node in the list
and then we can just update the next pointer
of the last note on the list to point to the
temp, to point to the new node.
So what we've done is we've created a loop
that finds us the last node and it's very
different from the loop before it which counts
the last node, or counts all the nodes including
the last node.
So we've got to keep in mind that those conditions
are quite different in those while loops and
to use the appropriate one at the appropriate
time.