Going back to discussion on recursion that
we had a few modules ago; you're going to
see a lot of recursion here in linked lists.
It's often used in linked lists because if
we look at a sub list, if you look at a list
that doesn't necessarily start at the original
head, you're going to see that it looks exactly
like the larger list and in fact, even the
empty list at the very end will look like
a regular old list.
So recursion is a real big popular topic here
in linked lists because everything can be
done using recursion or almost everything
can be done using recursion.
So here what I'd like to demonstrate is the
recursive copy function and what I did was
I just simply have a pointer.
So for example the assignment operator or
the copy constructor might call this to make
a copy of the right hand side list and it
would be passed the right hand side head node
pointer.
And if you look at the only thing it does
is check to see if the right hand side had
nodes pointer is null.
If it is then we return know it's an empty
list we're done.
And if not we can construct a new node based
on the right hand sides data, of course, so
that makes the actual copy of the data and
then call recursive copy for the right hand
sides next.
So we're using the constructor here, that
we created in the list node class to our benefit,
so we can construct a list node based on the
data and the copy of the right hand side next.
So in fact if we look at this, if you look
at the recursive algorithm, this copies the
null pointer first we get the null pointer
back and then it copies the last node and
returns the pointer to the last node.
So the recursive copy function which is copying
the next to last node and on and on and on
and on at the end.
When we finish copying we finish copying the
first node in the list and we return back
the pointer, which is then stored as head
and we've got the list copied.
So ultimately this makes what would be a very
complex or very time consuming algorithm,
because remember even if we didn't insert
an end that would be a linear time problem
just to find the end.
So we dealt them at least have a big O of
N squared algorithm to find and search all
the nodes which would be horrible but here
we can do a recursive copy in linear time
and be done with it.