You may ask yourself where we're going to
use linked lists and it's a reasonable question,
and anywhere that we need storage where we
have constant time insertion with no overhead
and we don't really need anything other than
linear access to the individual nodes.
That comes into play in a lot of situations
in computer science so you'll run across this
constantly.
In a later module, we're going to talk about
using linked lists to develop stacks and develop
cues.
We're also going to talk about other data
structures which are either similar to linked
lists or are based on linked lists.
So there's a lot of situations like that but
one real world situation that you might actually
have come across is the FAT thirty two file
system.
And this file system was in use in a lot of
places for a long time; ever since from the
basically the Windows ninety-five era on up
through to, well it was still being used a
little bit in Windows XP, but we stopped using
it pretty much in Windows seven.
You still use it today in a lot of situations
where you have to transfer a file from a Mac
machine to a PC and it needs to be editable
on both of them.
The only file system, at least right now,
that's compatible for editing with both MacOS
and with Windows is the FAT thirty two file
system so we still use it.
This file system stores a file, when we're
storing a file what we do is we store a pointer
to the first block on the hard drive where
the file is stored and the first block on
the hard drive stores a pointer to the second
block on the hard drive.
It's got quite a bit of data, but it also
has a pointer to the second block.
And then the second block stores a large amount
of data, usually about four kilobytes, and
a pointer to the third block and so on and
so on and so on and so forth.
The reason that this works is because very
standardized format, we all understand it;
it's a very old format so everybody knows
how to work with it.
But there are some downsides to it and let
me explain one of the biggest downsides that
you might have actually experience.
If you had a large video files stored on a
FAT thirty two file system, this video file
would be stored as pointers and the video
file might be, let's say four gigabytes.
But that means that it's broken down into
four million blocks; each one of which stores
a small portion of the video file.
Now if you watch the video straight through
you won’t notice any problem, you’ll retrieve
the first block on your video player will
display that and then the second block in
your video player will display that and so
on and so forth and so on and so forth.
But if you're like me and you stop and start
movies a whole bunch of times; you might stop
the movie restart your machine come back to
it a week later.
And you drag the slider to the middle, well
unfortunately we can't jump to the middle
of that set of blocks.
So we can't jump to the five hundred thousandth
block out of the one million to get to the
middle.
What we actually have to do is access all
five hundred thousand blocks and then we can
get to the five hundred thousand and one block.
So this is a downside of the FAT thirty two
file system and you may have experience that
if you have a video file stored on a FAT thirty
two file system, drag the slider and wait
for it to load all those five hundred thousand
blocks and throw them away because all they're
doing is accessing the pointers sequentially.