So what you can see here is a visual representation
of the linked list.
We have a head pointer that points at the
first note and inside the node there is an
object called a data section and the next
pointer the next pointer points at the next
node.
So the pointers are all the same pointers;
they’re list node pointers.
That's really what we're going to see later
on in this and this module.
So the objects that are being stored are whatever
data type you'd like, we'll see how to do
that later with templates, whatever data type
you'd like.
And we have this head pointer that points
at the first node, the next pointer points
the second node, the next pointer the second
node points at the third node, and the next
pointer of the third node points at null.
So there's three nodes on this list.
There's three data items on this list you
can call them: one, two, and three, if they
were integers, and you can store in them whatever
integer you want.
Now this list might also have a tail pointer
to point at the last node and that's functionally
dependent on what we decide to do with this
linked list.
So, we may end up needing a tail pointer and
if we do then we can have that as well to
point to the last node in the list.
And that's just for easy access if, for example,
we want to expand on the list by adding a
node then we can do that easily through the
tail pointer or through the head pointer.