We've been working with the arrays up to this
point, and they array data structure works
great for how we'd like to store information.
Unfortunately there are some limitations on
arrays; if we were doing insertion into an
array even if the insertion that we're doing
is on to the end of the array, we have to
make sure that there's space in the array
available.
If there isn't space available, we have to
expand the array as we saw in the pointers
and dynamic memory discussion.
We have to expand the array and doing so takes
big O of N. Regardless of that, if we want
to do an insertion at the beginning of an
array or if we wanted to an insertion in the
middle of an array, we have to push back every
element that's beyond that insertion point.
So we have to go to the last element and move
it back by one, we have to go to the second
to last to move it to the last element and
so on and so forth.
That's a severe limitation on arrays in that
we can't insert into the middle of them without
a big O of N process.
But we don't have that problem with a linked
list with a linked list.
We can do an arbitrary insertion on to the
beginning the end or anywhere in the middle
in constant time we can do it in big O of
one.
And the reason for that is because these pointers
keep track of where everything is going.
And as long as we're suing that it's being
stored in main memory, which it usually is,
if we're using main memory that's ram we can
access any node at a constant time.
So we don't have a problem with being able
to insert into the middle of the linked list.
Now unfortunately, the downside of the linked
list is that in order to go through to find
any node in the list we're going to have to
use a linear searching algorithm so it's going
to be big O of N.
So we can't arbitrarily go to the third node
of a linked list like we could with an array.
With an array, if we want the third node of
an array we simply go to that memory location
and access the third element.
But with a linked list to get to the third
node you have to go through the second note,
and to go through the second node have to
go through the first node and so on and so
forth.
So we have these differences in access and
insertion times and each one serves its own
purpose.
If we don't need arbitrary access to the middle
of a linked list or the middle of the data
set then a linked list would be a perfect
way to store that.
But if we do need arbitrary access to the
middle of the dataset then a linked list is
not a great idea.
So it's really just playing the averages of
what we expect to be doing with these things
that we can make a decision on to whether
we should use a linked list or an array.
Array insertion is big O of N; linked list
insertion is constant time.
Array access is constant time, whereas linked
list access is linear so you make the decision.
Now linked lists can be reorganized; they
can be merged.
They can be broken apart into new lists.
These operations only take constant time because
we're just manipulating the pointers.
linked lists don't require any overhead for
storage.
When we were working with vectors, we had
to make sure to leave a little bit of extra
room in case of expansion.
With the linked list, we have no need for
that so all we have of those pointers and
they only take up four bytes for each node
so hopefully it's not too significant a factor.
But the idea here is that we can make a decision
consciously about whether we choose an array
or a linked list to get the job done.