Before we get too deep into linked lists,
I have to talk to you about something else
that we need to go over first.
C++ has this idea of templates and a lot of
languages have these now; they might call
them generics, they might call them templates.
But the idea is that we don't really know
what data type we're going to be working with.
So in C++ we can template; we can use a template
when we don't know what the data type is of
one or more elements.
Before each function or class that we're going
to be working with, we have to put this indicator
this is a template class T. And T is just
my individual use, you can really use any
name but I just used to see all the time so
that's what I normally consider.
And that's a data type that we don't know
which data type it's actually going to be
in the end.
What C++ plus does is basically a find and
replace through that function to replace T
with the appropriate data type, whatever the
data type is.
So I've got here a function called my swap,
which is going to be a templated function
and it takes in two items and I don't know
what data type the items are.
It could be two integers.
It could be two doubles.
It could be two floats.
It could be two strings.
It could be two elephants.
What it can't be is one int and one elephant,
so we can't mix and match data type.
T has to be T consistently whatever the data
type is.
So here we're going to swap two items, meaning
we're going to make the value that was in
A into B. And we're going to take the value
that was in B and store it in A, and the code
for that is overly simplistic; it's just three
copy operations.
But the real takeaway here is that you can
use any data type for this my swap function.
And in C++ you would just call my swap and
give it two integers or two elephants, it
would be fine with that and you don't need
to rewrite this function numerous times simply
to change the data type.
And that's a huge benefit when we get to working
with larger classes, particularly with storage
of items where we don't know what data type
is going to be stored in really we don't care
what data type is going to be store; our job
is to simply store the data type.
And I imagine this the way I tell my students
to envision this is, imagine if you're running
a storage company, like the big the big storage
companies here in New York where you can rent
out a room.
The company doesn't care what you put into
your room.
I guess they might care if it's going to be
dangerous but they don't care what you're
going to put into that room; they simply care
that you own the room.
And that's exactly what we're doing here.
We're saying we'd like to the ability to swap
two things and don't worry about what those
two things are.