There's a little bit of extra work to be done
when we template a class.
So when we template the class, the name of
the class actually changes to incorporate
the template.
So here I've got a simple description of a
class called “sum valve.”
Where we've templated it to store a simple
data item and this is leading up to what a
linked list node would look like and we'll
get to that in a later slide.
But basically the sum val class stores one
data item, and it's got a function for get
val and for set val, and we don't know what
the T data type is and really we don't care
what’s the T data type.
And now inside main what we do is we’d create
this as sum val int and that's where you've
seen before, that's where a vector comes from.
So you've done this before with vector and
now you understand why; it's because vector
is templated.
So we have to tell it what data type we're
working with inside the sum val object, so
when we create it we say sum val int var name
or sum val char var name or sum val whatever
var name and you're giving it a data type
to now store inside some val.
Now the one thing to take notice of here,
is that every function that we create has
to be templated.
So the set Val function, for example, has
to be a templated function because first off
it has a parameter of type T. But also because
the class name is now changed to some value
less than T greater than.
So we can see that the actual name of the,
of the class changes to incorporate the data
type.
And that's just an internal C++ representation
but we do have to take note of that for any
time we're going to work with a templated
function inside of a templated class.