First thing we have to do and we're really
designed to classes here.
But the first class we're going to design
is a link list node class and of course can
be templated because it's going to have to
store the data item and we don't know what
the data type of the data item is.
So immediately we recognize that we have a
templated class.
So the nodes are templated.
And what we're going to be storing here is
the T data item and that is really the data
that's going to be stored inside each node,
so this is the data storage that we've got.
The next thing that we've got is a pointer
to the next node and if you pay attention
to that, if you look carefully, you're going
to see that this is an eldest node T pointer.
So you're actually got a pointer to a node
when we're creating the node.
So yeah.
This works because we can create a pointer
to the class object that we don't have yet
created, so we've created the LS Node class
and in the process of creating the LS node
class we need an Ellis node pointer.
But that does work; C++ was allowed us to
do that.
The next thing that we have is just a simple
constructor and the constructor I just made
to make life easier.
It's really it's not necessary, but it's yet
very useful in certain circumstances that
you'll see.
For example in the recursive copy operation
that we do later on, we use the LS node constructor
so that we can pass in either a data item
or we can pass in a pointer to the next item
and then of course it constructs those appropriately.
So you have to look back to the object oriented
lesson, if you need assistance on figuring
that one out.
Then we also have a friend class, which is
the LS class.
The LS class should have access to everything
inside the Ellis node.
So we'll make the whole class a friend of
this class so that all the functions inside
the Ellis class do have access to all the
private data here inside the illest Node class.
So it basically makes this a lot more accessible
and makes it a little bit easier.
It's not necessary.
We could do getters and setters but there's
not really a great reason to do getters and
setters especially because the Ellis class
is going to need to manipulate those next
pointers; so it can get very complex.
So that's why I do the friend there.
There's not much to this class; it's a very
simple class.
And in fact, in years past it was actually
implemented as a struct with no functions
because the only function that we really have
is the constructor.
So here we've got a very simple class to take
care of the LS node and it does store data
item so we're going to have to template it.