Here's the basic format for the linked list;
there's not much to it.
It is a little bit busy here but we'll go
through it step by step.
The first thing that you are going to see
is that there's a head pointer and really
that's the only thing that this entire class
needs to store; a pointer to the first node
in the list.
And of course it’s an LList node pointer,
it looks exactly like the next pointer that
we saw in the class, just a moment ago.
But here we've got a pointer to the first
node in the list.
Now of course if that head pointer is null
then that means there's nothing on the list,
so that's going to be our indication for an
empty list.
And if you look down into the public section
first line in the public section, you'll see
that that's what the default constructor actually
does; it just sets had pointer equal to head
equal to null pointer.
We've got a copy constructor and assignment
operator and destructor; that takes care of
our big three operations.
So those are our handle on the next three
lines, because we are working with pointers,
we are working with data storage that's on
the heap, and we are going to have to make
sure that that they had a storage is consistent.
So again look back at your pointers and dynamic
memory discussion to look at how the big three
plays into a factor here.
The insertAtHead function is simply going
to update the head pointer to point at the
new node.
So to do an insert and head all we have to
do is set the head equal to a new node and
make that new node’s next pointer equal
to the original head.
So that means keeping track of what the original
head pointer was maybe it was null, maybe
it was a node.
But if we're doing inserted head all we have
to do is create a new node and insert it physically
into the list.
removeFromHead is sort of the same thing which
had to advance the head pointer to heads next.
isEmpty is a simple function that just checks
to see if the head pointer is null.
Clear means we're going to have to eliminate
these nodes and the easiest way to eliminate
all the nodes is just constantly call remove
from head in a loop until isEmpty.
So it actually turns out to be while not is
empty remove from head and that's it; that's
the entire clear function.
insertAtEnd we're going to see a little bit
later on takes a little bit more effort and
then insertAtPoint is almost the same sort
of thing.
And then we have a size function to tell us
how many nodes there are actually on the list,
which we're going to see in the next slide
also.
So here is the basic format for the linked
list if you boil it down, it's really just
a head pointer and that's the entire linked
list.
And before we had object orientation back
in C, linked lists were created with a struct
for the node and then you would just simply
keep a pointer to the beginning of the linked
list and passed that pointer around.
So we could do this all without a class, it’s
just having the class keeps it all encapsulated
which is the point of a class together and
makes it a little bit easier to work with.
But there's not a lot of effort here and we
get a lot of benefit.