Let us now discuss the replacement policy
of a cache.
The goal of replacement policy is to
try to keep the block in the cache for as
long as possible based on the probability
that it will be used again in the near future.
This is done to improve temporal locality.
If we have a direct-mapped, then there is
not much of an option.
Since blue D RAM blocks can only go to only
one cache block, if a new blue D RAM block
is being brought into the cache, then we have
to remove the current content cache block
0.
So direct mapping doesn’t provide very good
options for replacement.
This is another reason why it is not ideal
for temporal locality.
If we have a fully-associative cache, things
are a little bit different.
This is because in a fully-associative cache,
we have options.
Remember, in a fully-associative cache, a
D RAM block can move anywhere in the cache.
If a block is free in the cache, then we can
always move the new D RAM block to that free
location.
So there is nothing to evict in that current
case.
Let us consider the worst case that all the
blocks of the fully-associative cache are
occupied, and we must evict something.
The most common replacement policy is called
the least recently used policy, or LRU policy.
The idea behind the LRU policy is to evict
the cache block that is the oldest to have
been accessed.
The intuition here is that if the content
of a cache have not been accessed recently,
then they are unlikely to be accessed again
in the near future.
So we can evict it.
On the other hand, if the contents of a cache
block have been accessed recently, they will
likely be used again soon.
So it is best to keep it in the cache to maintain
temporal locality.
To determine the recency of use, each cache
block has what are called age bits.
The age bits of a cache block work as a time
clock that indicates the last time a cache
block was accessed.
Whenever a cache block is accessed, its age
bits are updated to represent the current
time of accessed.
So in our example, we have a fully associative
cache and all cache blocks are occupied.
So the way the LRU policy works is that it
first reads the age bits of all cache blocks
and find cache block with the lowest value
age bits.
Remember, the least recently used block will
have the smallest value in its age bits.
This oldest block is chosen for replacement.
This way, blocks that have been used recently
can stay in the cache because they are more
likely to be used again soon according to
temporal locality.
So in this example, the least recently used
cache block is the last one because its age
bits are the smallest when we convert all
the age bits to decimal values.
So that cache block would be selected for
eviction.
During the eviction, the content of the new
D RAM block is brought into the cache block
and the age bits of this block are updated
to indicate that it was recently used.
As we see, now this cache block is the most
recent one to have been accessed in the cache
because its age bits have the highest value.
The LRU policy also works for set associative
caches.
But remember, in a set-associative cache,
a D RAM block can only go to a specific set
within a cache.
So consider the example of a 2-way set associative
cache.
A new D RAM block needs to be brought up to
the cache.
Since this D RAM block is blue, it can only
go to set 0 of the cache.
Since both blocks in that set are occupied,
one of them must be evicted.
So using the LRU policy, the cache controller
reads the age bits of the two cache blocks
and notices that the first one is the oldest
used.
The content of that cache block is thus evicted,
the new D RAM block is brought in, and the
age bits of the block are updated to reflect
the current time.
Although we have only discussed LRU policy,
there are other common approaches including
least frequently used, which uses counters
to keep track how often caches are used, random
replacement, which randomly chooses a block
to evict, and several hybrid methods that
dynamically adjust between least recently
used and least frequently used based on the
performance of the cache.