Ok.
So we have covered the different parameters
for cache organization.
Now let us see how exactly the cache is accessed
when the CPU gives it an address during the
instruction fetch stage or during the memory
stage.
This figure here shows how the cache controller
breaks down a physical memory address into
different fields to find where in the cache
is the data or instruction associated to that
address is.
All of these field are in bits.
The rightmost field of the address is the
cache block offset.
We will explain the role of the cache block
offset later.
The middle field of the address is the cache
block number if the cache is direct mapped,
or the cache set number if the cache is set
associative.
Therefore, this field indicates which cache
block number or set block number that the
content of this physical address must be in
if it in the cache.
The last field is the cache, address, is the
cache tag.
We will explain the role of the cache tag
later.
The D RAM block number is the concatenation
of the cache tag and either the cache set
number or the cache block number, depending
on the associativity of the cache.
Here we see the different formulas to obtain
the size of the different fields.
Note that all results of the formulas are
in bits.
Let us consider an example.
Assume that we have a memory hierarchy with
16-byte blocks, a 16-megabyte D RAM and with
Level 1 caches.
Each Level 1 cache is 16 kilobyte and is 2-way
set associative.
Based on this configuration, we can calculate
use our formulas to calculate the size of
each field for the physical addresses.
Note that here when we say physical address
what we mean the location of the data or instruction
in D RAM.
Also note that it is simpler to calculate
the size of the fields by using the two to
the power notation.
For example, 16 megabyte is 2 to the power
of 24, therefore, the address is 24 bits.