Now let us now see the role of the block offset
and the cache tag fields in the physical address.
Remember that each D RAM or cache block is
at least 16 bytes.
In MIPS64, an instruction is four bytes and
an instruction in.
So each block can have four instructions.
The role of the cache block offset field is
to indicate which of the four instructions
in the block to access for a given address.
In case of a data access, each data can be
at most 8 bytes in MIPS64.
So a cache block of 16 bytes can up to two
double words.
So the goal of the offset is to indicate which
of the two double words the address is requesting
Let us see the role of the cache tag.
Assume we have a 16 megabyte D RAM and a 16
kilobyte cache with a 2-way set associative.
Now consider the following addresses: 001C
and 004018.
When we break the addresses into the different
fields, we see that they both have same cache
set 0.
This means, when accessing these addresses,
the cache controller will go to same cache
set 1 to find.
However, they have different D RAM blocks,
which makes sense because they are different
addresses.
So, the role of the cache tag is to determine
which D RAM block that the content of a cache
block belongs to.
So, if we concatenate the cache tag and the
cache set, we get the D RAM block.
So, when searching for a data in the cache,
the cache controller has to also compare the
cache tags to see if it is getting the correct
instruction or data.
We will see an illustration of this later.