So let us take a look at how the cache is
accessed during the instruction fetch and
the memory stages of the CPU pipeline.
Let us assume we have 16 megabyte DRAM, and
a 16 kilobye, 2-way set associative cache
with LRU replacement and WriteBack policy.
In addition to the cache age bits and the
dirty bits that we discussed before, each
cache block has a valid bit and cache tag
bits.
The valid bit indicates that there is a valid
content in the cache block.
So initially the valid bit is zero and when
something is brought into the cache the first
time, the valid bit for that cache block is
set to one.
The cache tag bits hold the value for the
cache tag field for the D RAM address of the
data or instruction in that cache block.
We will illustrate how the cache controller
goes about searching the cache and updating
it given an address.
By default, when the CPU starts, all the valid
bits are zero because there is nothing in
the cache.
This is known as a cold start.
For simplicity, we assume this is the L1 data
cache.
So it only handles requests for data accesses
at the memory stage of the pipeline
At some point in execution, there is a Load
double instruction where the memory address
is 001C.
So the CPU calculates the target address and
gives it to the cache controller.
The cache controller then breaks down the
address into the different fields to find
out if the requested data is in the cache.
Here we see that the cache controller gets
the fields and determines that if the data
for this load double instruction is already
in the cache, then it must be in set 1.
The cache controller searches for each block
in set 1.
But since all the valid bits of the blocks
in that set are all zero, then there is no
data in that cache set.
Hence the data is not in the cache and must
be brought from the D RAM.
This is known as a cache miss.
Though we are using the LRU policy, there
is nothing to replace because the set is initially
empty.
So the cache controller simply sends the address
to the memory controller to handle the cache
miss.
The memory controller uses the D RAM block
field of the address to find out which block
is being requested.
Here we see that D RAM block is requested.
So the memory controller gets D RAM block
1 and sends it back to the cache controller.
The cache controller then takes the
data, adds it to an empty blocks in the set,
updates the valid bit to indicate that there
is some valid content in that cache block,
updates the cache age bits to indicate the
recency of access for this block and sets
the cache tag bits of that block to the value
of the cache tag field of the address.
In our case, the cache tag field is zero.