Later in execution, consider the cache looks
like this.
In addition, we get a new load double instruction
where the address now is 0014.
The CPU sends the address to the cache controller
and the latter breaks it down into the different
fields.
The controller calculates the set of this
address and it realizes it’s one.
The cache controller then begins searching
for the cache blocks in set 1.
For each block in the set, the controller
first check the valid bit of that block.
If the bit is not one, then there is no valid
data, so there is no need to continue with
that block.
If the valid bit is one, the controller then
compares the cache tag field of the requested
address to the cache tag bits for that block.
If the comparison matches, then the cache
block has the data we are looking for.
This is because when we combine the cache
tag and the cache set, we get the D RAM block.
Therefore, if they both match, then the content
of the requested D RAM block is in that matching
cache block.
This is known as a cache hit.
When there is a cache hit, the data is brought
from the cache to CPU, without the need to
go to memory.
Hence we get much faster access of the data.
Cache hit and cache miss ratios are the main
metric of performance of a cache.
The goal is to maximize the percentage of
hits that we have for all memory accesses
that the CPU makes.