The primary approach to overcome the main
memory access delay is by adding caches.
A cache is another memory component that is
put between the main memory and the processor
core and its role is to hold instructions
and data that the CPU often uses.
So what makes a cache different from DRAM?
First off, a cache is implemented as SRAM
instead of DRAM.
The S in SRAM stands for static.
This means that there is no need to refresh
the main memory, which makes it faster to
read from and write to.
However, SRAM requires more space to hold
one bit of data than DRAM.
Usually, SRAM can require up to 8 times more
area to store one bit than a DRAM.
So, although it consumes less power, SRAM
takes more area.
As a result, we can’t have gigabytes worth
of SRAM.
Usually, an SRAM cache is in the range of
2KB to 2-MB.
Given that a cache can be in the kilobyte
size, it is small enough that it can be put
on the same chip as the CPU without it consuming
all of the power budget.
So with the benefits of using static RAM and
being able to put the cache on the same chip
as the CPU, the access delay of a cache can
be between 1 and 12 cycles depending on the
size and other factors that we will discuss.
Now someone may have the intuition to simply
use SRAM for main memory instead of DRAM.
But remember, SRAM can require up to 8 more
area than DRAM.
Therefore, you cannot have a large 8 GB main
memory as SRAM because it will take too much
space on your computer motherboard.