For that the cache uses two locality principles
known as temporal and spatial locality principles
of temporal and spatial locality.
Temporal locality basically states that if
a data or instructions is used once, it is
likely to be used again soon.
Therefore, once an instruction or data is
brought into the cache, temporal locality
suggests to keep it the cache as long as possible.
One of the best examples of temporal locality
is loop code.
When we go in a loop once, we are very likely
to go through it again.
Therefore, it is best to keep the loop code
in the cache, rather than overwrite it or
move it back in the main memory.