Spatial locality states that if a data or
instruction is used, then the instruction
or data next to it is also likely to be accessed
soon.
The clearest example to illustrate spatial
locality is with arrays; once you access the
elements in the one cell of an array, you
are likely to access the elements in the next
cells.
Using this spatial locality, when a data or
instruction is accessed, instead of bringing
only data or instruction from the memory to
the cache, the whole block that holds this
instruction or data is brought in.
Consider the example here.
We have a code that accumulates the numbers
of an array.
Let us assume that we have 32-byte cache and
DRAM blocks and the elements of the array
are 8 bytes.
Once we go to the main memory to get eight
bytes for the first elements of the array,
we bring the 8 bytes for that element as well
as the 24 bytes next to it.
In this case, if the second, third, and fourth
elements of the array are needed, they are
already in the cache and are faster to access
from there than if we had to go back to the
main memory to get them.