So spatial locality is a bit easier to implement.
This is because, the main thing to consider
with that is the size of the cache block.
The larger the cache block, the more data
or instructions that are next to each other
we can bring and the more spatial locality
we have.
And since the cache block size is the same
as the DRAM block size, there is not much
the cache designer can do to impact that.
On the other hand, temporal locality requires
a bit of work.
Ideally, what we would like to do is keep
all the D RAM blocks in the cache.
But we know that is not practical because
of the size differences.
So the CPU designer has to make several design
choices in the cache in order to maintain
temporal locality as much as possible.
For that, the designer uses the following
parameters: the associativity of the cache
to determine which locations in the cache
can a D RAM block be moved to, the replacement
policy to determine when to evict a block
from the cache, and the write policy which
determines how to synchronize the data between
the cache and the D RAM.
We will discuss how each parameter impacts
not only the temporal locality but also the
delay at which the cache is accessed