So, let’s cover a little bit of the background
on computer organization.
This is just for us to get a flavor of what’s
inside of a CPU so we can get a better feel
for how it executes the code that we write
in a language like C or C++.
So, at a high-level, there are three main
hardware components inside of a CPU: the functional
units, the registers, and the memory hierarchy.
The functional units are hardware components
that perform logic, arithmetic, and other
operations.
Examples of functional units we may find are:
the Arithmetic Logic Unit , or ALU, which
performs integer addition, subtraction and
logic operations such as AND, OR, XOR, etc;
the floating Point Unit, or FPU, which performs
the same operations as the ALU, but for floating
point data; the integer multiplication unit,
or IMUL, which performs integer multiplication
and division; then there is the floating point
multiplication unit, of FMUL, which performs
floating point multiplications and divisions.
The General purpose registers or GPRS, are
components inside the CPU that hold the data
for the functional units.
So every data that a functional unit operates
on must first be located in a general purpose
register.
Similarly, once a functional unit finishes
an operation, it puts the result back in a
general purpose register.
The other important component in the CPU is
the memory hierarchy.
This hierarchy includes the hard disk, your
main memory or RAM, and several other storage
components known as caches.
The memory hierarchy stores both the software
and the data of a given program and different
levels of the hierarchy are used for different
purposes.
For example, the hard disk is used for permanent
storage, the RAM and caches are used for temporary
storage.
We will cover specific aspects of the memory
hierarchy towards the end of the computer
architecture section
So, let us go through a simple example to
illustrate how these three main components
work in concert.
Let’s say we have a simple program, written
in C or C++, such as the one we have next
to the Memory block.
The crux of the code is to perform the addition
B+C and to put the result back in memory location
of A. Since B and C are integer values 3 and
4 respectively, the ALU functional unit will
be used.
Remember that each data used by a functional
unit must first be available in a general
purpose register.
So the first operations of the CPU are to
move the data for B and C to general purpose
registers.
So, for the first operation to implement A
= B+C is to copy the value of B into a general
purpose register.
The second operation copies the value of C
into another general purpose register.
At this point, both values are in registers
so the ALU can use them to do the addition.
As we see here, in the operation, the ALU
performs the addition of 3+4 and puts the
result back into a general purpose register.
The last operation for this code is to copy
the value of the result register back into
the memory location for A. So in total, we
have four operation to perform A = B+C. The
first two operations copied the values of
B and C into the registers, because the functional
units only operate on data that are in those
general purpose registers.
The next operation performs the addition and
puts the result into a general purpose register,
and the last operation copies the value of
the result from its register to memory.
Later in this section, we will cover this
example in more intricate details