Let us first discuss the RISC architecture.
The basic idea of RISC is to have simple instructions
that perform simple operations.
Let us recall the A = B+C function from before.
In a RISC processor, each of the four operations
needed to implement this function can be implemented
as a machine-level instruction.
So that is four RISC machine-level instructions
for one high-level C or C++ line of code.
So there would be an instruction to load B
to register, and instruction load C to register,
an instruction to add registers for B and
C and put the result back in a register, and
an instruction to store the result back to
memory allocated for A.
The benefit of having instructions that perform
simple operations is that they make it easy
to implement the CPU at the hardware level.
So the CPU hardware is less complex and incurs
less power and space in your computer.
The main downside is that it is more difficult
to translate the high-level code into machine-level
instructions.
This makes it more difficult for the compilers.
The most popular RISC architecture used in
the market is ARM, which is commonly found
in smartphones, tablets, and low-battery platforms.