So here we see the MIPS mnemonic version of
our working assembly example.
We notice some clear differences from the
offset.
The first thing we notice is that each instruction
has an associated address.
This is the address of the instruction in
the code segment.
Note that these addresses are given in hexadecimal
format.
We also notice that the registers are given
using numerical notations, as is done in machine
code.
There are 32 general-purpose registers in
MIPS64, R0 to R31.
The last thing we notice is that the mnemonic
notation has the same fields as the machine
code.
Using the first Load doubleword as an example, we'll
see that the mnemonic notation has the base
and offset fields, just like the machine code
discussed earlier.