So, let’s go through a detailed example
of converting a high-level code in C or C++
to MIPS assembly and ultimately to MIPS mnemonic
format.
Consider the high-level code we have here
as an example.
Note that the values for A, B, and C, are
initialized in hexadecimal format
So when we successfully compile this high-level
code using our MIPS compiler, we get the software
binary that is compatible only to a MIPS processor.
This binary is the executable file of the
code.
And if we try to open this binary, what we
see is a bunch of ones and zeros representing
the bits for the machine-level instructions
that implement this high-level code
This binary itself is generally broken down
into two segments: a code segment that contains
the machine level instructions that implement
the functionality of the high-level code and
a data segment that contains the declared
static variables in the high-level code.
Each segment has a start address that we call
the base address.
Note that the addresses are given in hexadecimal.
In our example, the code segment base address
is F00 and the base address of the data segment
is A000.
Note that in the data segment, each static
variable is initialized to 64 bits.
This is the default configuration of the MIPS64
processor.
So ideally, what we would like to do is to
be able to understand how the high-level code
A = B+C maps to machine code However, this
is too complicated because working with the
bitwise representations of machine-level instructions
is tedious and error-prone.