However, assembly code doesn’t fully represent
machine-level instructions.
This is due to symbolic notations of the registers
and the memory addresses.
The processor doesn’t understand a memory
address labeled as B or a register labeled
as t1.
Let us consider the first Load doubleword
instruction we had earlier and let’s compare
it to the real machine instruction.
Using this example, we will see that the assembly
notation doesn’t have some of the fields
of machine-level code.
So in MIPS64 architecture, the most significant
six bits of a machine-level instruction represent
its opcode.
The opcode is a simple mnemonic notation to
encode the operation of the of the instruction.
In our example, the opcode 110111 means this
is a load double word instruction.
The assembly instruction also has a load doubleword
opcode.
The next 5 bits of the machine-level instruction
represent the base field.
This is the number of a general purpose register
number that holds the base address of the
data segment.
In our example, this register is register
number 8, or R8.
Note that there is no such base register field
in the assembly instruction.
Instead, it simply uses the label name of
the data as it was declared in the high-level
code.
The CPU cannot understand such high-level
label.
The next 5 bits of the machine-level instruction
represent the Rt register field.
This field indicates the destination register
where the double word will loaded.
In the machine-level instruction, this Rt
register is register number 9 or R9 and is
labeled as t1 in the assembly code.
This is still similar to the assembly level
code, though the labeling is different
The last 16 bits of the machine code is the
offset field.
It indicates where within the data segment
the requested value is located.
In our example, the offset is 0 because B
is the first value in the data segment.
Note that the assembly-level instruction does
not have such field.