So at the end of this instruction, we see
the value of R9 has been updated as desired
by the Load double word and the program counter
points to the next instruction.
The next instruction is also a load double
word and we see that the memory access column
indicates an instruction read to fetch the
instructions from the code segment, and a
data read, to read the double word data from
the data segment.
In addition, we see that the Program Counter
is incremented by four to point to the next
instruction to execute and we see that the
destination register R10 of the load doubleword
is updated with the appropriate value.
Everything else remains unchanged.
The next instruction is a Doubleword add.
This instruction takes the content of registers
R9 and R10, sends them to the ALU for addition,
and puts the result in the destination register
R11.
The instruction only does an instruction read
because it doesn’t access the data segment.
Its operands are only registers.
We see that the Program Counter is incremented
to point to the next instruction and R11 has
the result of the addition in hexadecimal.
The last instruction is a store doubleword.
It works in a similar fashion to load doubleword,
except that instead of loading memory to register,
it stores from register to memory.
Store doubleword uses its base register and
offset to calculate the target address of
the memory, then writes the content of the
register operands to the memory location indicated
by the calculated address.
As a Store doubleword, the CPU does an instruction
read and data write for this instruction.
We also see that the PC is incremented by
4, even if there is no such instruction at
address F10 in our code segment.
This is because the CPU does this increment
automatically.
At the end, this is content of the table.
It illustrates the different registers and
memory locations that are relevant to the
code and how they are impacted by each instruction
in said code.