Let us now go over the list of general purpose
registers in the MIPS CPU.
Remember there are 32 of them, labeled R0-R31.
R0 always contain the value 0 and it’s read-only.
That is, no code can write to it.
It is only used whenever we want to use the
value 0.
R1 is reserved for the assembler.
R2 and R3 are used to return results of function
calls.
If you have a function that returns an integer,
then it will be stored in either R2 or R3
after the function completes.
One interesting question is if we have a function
that returns something like a struc of 20
integers, how does MIPS return the 20 values
when it only has 2 registers.
I will leave it to you guys to find out.
R4 to R7 are used to pass parameters of a
function call.
Similarly, I will let you guys find out how
to call a function that passes more than four
parameters.
R8 to R15 and R24 to R25 are used to store
temporary values that are declared in a function.
So when then function completes, the values
of these registers are not saved.
We will primarily use these registers in our
MIPS mnemonic codes.
R16 to R23 are also used to store values in
functions, but they are stored and saved when
the function completes.
So they can be used across multiple functions.
R26 and R27 are reserved for the O.S.
R28 is the global pointer and it points to
the static data segment of the code.
R29 and R30 point to the stack and frame pointers
respectively.
The stack and frames are structures in the
CPU that store local variables of a given
function.
R31 holds the address to return from a function
call.
For our course, we will primarily use R0,
R8 to R15, R24, R25, and R31.
Note that we do not include the Program Counter
in this list because it is not a general-purpose
register.
It is a special register and cannot be accessed
by any user-level code.