There is a sequential flow IO expressions
arithmetic expressions and data of a type
int.
Today we are going to focus mostly on some
data types there are several data types that
are used in C++.
There is the int we already talked about.
We are going to talk about float and double
which are going to be used to represent real
numbers numbers with a fractional part.
There is a char that is used for characters
there is string for textual information and
there bool for Boolean values True and False.
We are going to talk in much detail about
each and every one of these data types.
We are going to start talking about int we
are going to do it right away.