Let’s take a second look at a problem we
already implemented the program that reads
from the user two numbers and print their
sum and see if we can find some of these constructs
some data expressions and control flow.
So here is the program we implemented you
can see that when this program is executed
it is executed line after line.
First there is cout that prints an instruction
to the user please enter two numbers.
Then there is the cin that reads from the
user these two numbers then we add them store
them into sum and eventually we print out
the message that whatever the sum is.
You can see that the program is executed line
by line we call this flow a sequential flow.
This is a default flow of a program that lines
executed one after the other.
You could also see that we have here some
data we have three variables numOne numTwo
sum they are all integers in C which is a
C++ which is a strongly type language.
Each data must have a type of its own in this
case both or all of our variables are integers
int.
There are also expressions here in our program
there is numOne plus numTwo there is an assignment
expressions there is a cout a cin an io expression.
So there are all the kinds of these constructs
here in this program.