If we print or cout x divided by 2 since x
and 2 are both integer the slash here is in
the context of div.
So it would print how many full times 2 fits
into 5 which is 2 in this case and if we cout
x mod 2 that would print the remainder when
we are dividing 13 by 5 or 5 by 2 sorry and
that is one.
Because this is the remainder when we are
5 by 2.
So when we are speaking about arithmetic operators
in the context of int we have the plus minus
multiplication div and mod.
One last operator I want to talk about here
is the assignment.
Formally an assignment is considered to be
an arithmetic operator.
Basically by using it we create an arithmetic
expression.
And when we set x to 6 there is a side effect
that basically sets the value of x to 6.
But this expression basically also has a value.
The value of this expression is the value
that is assigned to the variable.
So for example if we cout x equals 7 so first
the side effect of x getting the value of
7 happens but then the value of this expression
7 is also in this case printed.
Later on if we assign y to be x equals 8 once
again x equals 8 when it is evaluated sets
x to the value of 8 but the value of this
expression 8 goes into y.
So using assignment as arithmetical operator
we can for example create multiple assignments
in a single line of code.
So we can do y equals x equals 8.
Actually we don’t need the parentheses we
can just do y equals x equals whatever in
this case 9.
So these are the major or the fundamental
arithmetic operators when we are using integers.
And if we recap what we said about integers
about the int data type so they are representing
they are used represent integer numbers.
Each one has a fixed size of 4 bytes.
The data in these 4 bytes is represented using
a 32 bit 2’s complement method.
C++ has built in datas that are considered
to be integers basically the C++ literals.
We programmers just write integer numbers
in their decimal representation and C++ would
recognize them consider them to be integers.
And we can create arithmetic operators using
integers with arithmetic operators in between
them.