One more thing I want to talk about are our
operators that can be applied on integers.
Using our arithmetical operators basically
we create expressions so we have the literals
or the variables which are atomic expression
but combining them using arithmetic operators
we create more compound expressions. For example
plus we can add two integers and then create
a greater or a bigger expression. Expression
basically is a thing that has a value in this
case for example if we have x and y and then
x is set to 5 we create an expression x plus
5 basically 5 plus 2 or 7. If we cout x plus
2 the value of this expression would be printed
in this case 7 would be printed. But plus
is an arithmetical operator that can be applied
on integers x is an integer 2 is an integer
it is a C++ literal of type int and plus can
come in between two integers and create a
compound expression in this case x plus 2.
So we can print the value of an expression
we can set a variable to have the value of
an expression. Y equals x plus 2 basically
is an assignment when an assignment is evaluated
first the write inside is evaluated x plus
2 and then this value which is in this case
7 is set into the variable y. So given an
expression we can print it we can assign it
to a variable. Actually we can also just type
it X plus 2 obviously it is a useless line
of code here because no one does nothing with
the value x plus 2 but the x plus 2 on its
own is a legal expression in C++ and we can
write just like that. So plus is arithmetic
expression arithmetic operator sorry but then
we can have some more arithmetic operators.
For example minus and star for times so we
can subtract integers x minus 2 we can print
it and it could print 3. We can multiply x
times 2 5 times 2 which is 10 we can assign
it to y y would be 10. So we can apply different
arithmetic operators on ints. Plus minus times.
We can also apply the divider operator but
here it is a little bit tricky. What do you
think would happen if we for example cout
x divided by 2 5 divided by 2. I would say
that it would probably print 2.5 because 5
divided by 2 is two and a half. But then it
behaves a little bit differently.