Now that we're comfortable with the stack,
let’s take a look at our second data structure
which is the queue.
And the queue is our FIFO data structure:
it's a first in, first out data structure,
which means that whatever item is first in
queued, is the first item that's de-queued.
And this is exactly what you have at a line,
what we call in the United States we call
it a line, in Europe they might call it a
queue which is exactly what we're demonstrating
here.
when you arrive at the bank if there's a line
they have to get on you're going to enter
into the line and you're going to wait until
it's your turn.
if we used a stack for something like that
the first person to arrive in the morning
might not be serviced until the very end of
the day, but in the queue it's much more fair.
The first item that comes into the queue is
the first item that goes out of the queue;
so they go out in order as opposed to in reverse
order.
the FIFO buffer or the queue is often use
for storing information temporarily and then
releasing it later so called a buffer. the
functions that we have you might see them
called N.Q. and D.Q. and top, but a lot of
people refer to him just as push and pop and
top the same as they do with the stack.
So just be clear of what functions you're
using and what data structure you're using,
because it is possible you might have some
overlap between the names push and pop.
Of course, the supplemental functions that
we're going to have are still the same as
the stack; we're still going to have the clear,
we're still going to have the is empty, and
we're still going to have the size. and you
can see that the elements that get inserted
get inserted to the back of the queue and
when they get removed they get removed from
the front of the queue.
So it's our simple FIFO data structure for
just temporary storage of information.