So we’ve come to the conclusion, I think,
that we are going to use a linked list again
for this data structure.
And the implementation here is going to be
really similar to that of a stack; we're going
to have just a couple of minor changes.
Now, instead of inserting into and removing
from the same point, either the front of the
back, we're going to be removing or inserting
from different points.
So enqueue is going to insert on to the end
of the dequeue is going to remove from the
front of the queue.
We really have to make sure that the underlying
data structure of the linked list has both
head and tail pointers, so that way we can
do those constant time insertions.
If we have something simple like a singularly
linked list where we only have a head pointer,
then insertion is going to require us to iterate
or recursively go through the entire linked
list so that we can find the end and insert
on to the end and that's too costly.
It's far simpler to keep a tail pointer in
addition to the head pointer so that we know
where the end of the list is and then we can
insert on to the end of the list, and we can
remove from the front of the list.
So it's very possible to use a singularly
linked list in this structure.
We're going to just, again, use the STL list
class to make it easy.
But the STL list class is a doubly linked
list and of course there's overhead in that.
If we want to save some memory, we could create
a singularly linked list where we have the
head pointer pointing to the next element,
in other words the oldest element in the list,
and we can have the tail pointer pointing
at the last element.
When we do a removal, we just advance the
head pointer to the next element remove that
first element and when we do an insertion
we just make the tail pointer point to the
new node and then we can connect the previous
last node to the new node.
So we have options for doing the queue as
a singularly linked list.
But for our purposes we're just going to use
the STL list class, so that it's easier and
we can demonstrate it and it has all the big
three already built into it so we're not really
worried.