So now that we understand how a queue is built,
what do we use it for?
The fundamental way that we use queues as
storage buffer, so there's going to be a lot
of situations where we're bringing information
in.
For example you've already worked with the
IO stream and, whether we're talking about
a file stream or whether we're talking about
keyboard input, we are talking about bringing
in a large amount of data at first, storing
it temporarily, and then slowly feeding it
into your user program.
So in the case of reading a file, because
it's an expensive endeavor to actually read
data from the secondary storage device, what
we're instead going to do is grab a large
portion of the file, perhaps all of it, store
it temporarily in a structure in main memory,
and then as the program asks for it it's going
to be fed in slowly.
Now the best structure for that of course
is a first in first out buffer, or a queue.
So there's one situation is as there.
We might use it in operating systems, later
we're going to talk about memory management,
and we're going to talk about removing the
oldest page of main memory for example.
And how do we know which one is the oldest?
Well we keep a FIFO list, a FIFO queue, of
all the pages that are in main memory and
when we need to throw one away we throw away
the front of the queue, so there's options
for that.
Really anywhere in computer science where
we need in an ordered list; where we have
first in first out property.
That's where we're going to use a queue.
So there's a lot of situations that you're
going to see throughout your career in computer
science that you're going to use a queue and
they are a very popular structure.