So in this module, we took a look at the two
fundamental data structures in C++ that we
use stacks and cues.
And we saw how they work with how they were
implemented and what they're used for.
Hopefully have a better understanding of how
a stack works, how a queue works, and you
also can produce one if you had to yourself.
Now, fortunately, of course the STL took care
of all this for us so if we needed a stack
we could just pounding include stack and we
get stack, and if we needed a queue we could
just pound include queue and we end up with
a queue.
And all the features are there; all the functions
are there.
We have to push, the pop, the enqueue and
the dequeue, and you can use those without
having to build it yourself.
But even if you had to build yourself, you
realize now that it's only a couple of lines
of code and it's not really going to take
much to store it.
So I hope you enjoyed that module and we’ll
see you for the next one.