In this module we're going to talk about a
couple of data structures the two data structures
that we're going to talk about our stacks
and queues.
And these really popular data structures in
computer science and we use them over and
over and over again.
So we're going to talk about first the stack
we are going to explain what it is and how
it works and what it's designed for and then
I'm going to talk about some uses that we
could apply the stack to and then we're going
to talk about queues.
We're going to talk about the same thing what
it is and how it works and what it's designed
for and then what we use queues for.
So coming away from this you're going to have
a good look at two very fundamental data structures
in computer science and you should understand
both how they are built and how they are used.