So the two fundamental functions again are
push and pop and of course we'll have top
and that just accesses the highest element
on the stack.
But the push function is going to add to the
front of the stack and the pop simply removes
from the front of the stack and you can do
this for the back also it really doesn't matter.
But the point is that the push and the pop
are inserting and removing from the same place
so that means that when we do the latest push
the next pop is going to cause that item to
be to come out immediately.
So we don't have to or we are not looking
at further information down in the stack now
of course when we implement it will have to
implement all those supplemental functions
like clear and is empty and size.
And we'll also have to implement the big three
if we're talking about using an array.
Now for this demonstration we're not going
to use an array.
We'll actually use the STL list class which
already has the big three already built but
I just did that so that it's a little bit
easier for us to understand we don't have
to worry about the complexity of building
the big three.