So we're going to have to store all the information
from the stack so the user is going to give
us a ton of information through push operations
and we're going to have to put that information
somewhere and the two data structures that
we've worked with so far that we can use as
fundamental storage are the list and the array.
So we have to decide if we want to store the
information that's given to us as a list in
which case we have a linked list with each
node pointing to the next node or as an array
in which case we have sequential storage of
a limited size where we can add on.
So if we take a look at the comparison between
the two methods that we could use and we look
at each individual function.
You'll see that the list for example the push
operation is a constant time operation big
O of one.
Because every time you add to the list all
we're going to do is create a new node we
are just going to put it on the front of the
list and we're going to link it to the next
node in the list.
So a push operation is actually very simple
and it doesn't take anything more than constant
time we don't care if there's ten thousand
of these elements already on the stack the
next one that we're going to push isn’t
going to take any additional amount of time.
As a comparison we have the array and if we
do a push on an array sometimes it's constant
time if we have enough space left on the array
and sometimes it's going to be a linear time
of the big O of N. And that's because we may
have to expand that array if we ran out of
space we may have to expand that array to
create more space.
So sometimes it's going to be constant time
and sometimes it's going to be linear time
which creates a little bit of inconsistency.
If we need that consistency then that would
negate the possibility of using an array.
As far as a pop it's always going to be a
big O of one it is always going to be a constant
time removal from the list we just throw away
the top node.
From the array we could just reduce the size
by one the top element accessing the top element
should always be constant time and that's
really fundamental that’s important we want
that.
From the list we would just access that top
element through the head pointer from the
array we would just access the zero element
or if we wanted to size minus one element.
For clear it's always going to be constant
time for the array but it's going to be linear
time for the linked list and then with is
empty we always have just the size parameter
we can always check to see if the size zero.
And for the size well the array of course
is going to be a constant time.
How can we make the linked list be constant
time?
Well since we know how many push operations
there is going to be we can simply use the
size parameter we can create an integer and
store that size parameter so that we always
have it in a constant time access so we won't
have to run through the list and actually
calculate how many elements are on the list.
We’ll just keep an integer in the in the
class that records how many elements are actually
in the list at any given time.
So if you take a look at these we can compare
easily how the list works with how the array
works and we have now the tools to understand
the performance benefits.
So we can choose between either the list or
the array.