When we're working with binary search trees,
there are times that we want to process every
node in the tree.
And the way that we do that, and not by searching
I mean we actually want to go into each node
in the tree and do some activity…
If we're going to do that we have a number
of ways that we can do that and the order
of it really depends on how we want to go
through the tree.
Now if we're going to do the same thing to
every node really doesn't matter, we can just
do it using any of these orders, but if we
care about the way that the processing happens.
So, for search for example on a file system,
which is designed as a tree, on a search on
a file system we probably want to search the
higher stuff first and search the later stuff
later.
That's called a level order traversal, but
we may want to do different types of traversals
which are: in-order, pre-order, or post order
depending on when we want to search this note
or when we want to process I'll call it, this
node.
So what we're asking here is if we look at
it in a recursive fashion, when do we want
to search the root node.
So, we start the process does that mean that
we search the root node first or does that
mean we search the leftmost node, the minimum
node first.
So, in a binary search tree really in any
binary tree, we have to decide what the order
of traversal is.
So, in-order traversal processes the left
nodes recursively first and then it processes
the so-called this node and then a processes
the right nodes.
So, the pre-order traversal would just be
that we do this node first and then the left
and then the right.
And the post-order would be that we do the
left and then the right and then the this;
so it really decides when we process the this
node.
Level order traversal processes it based on
depth and this might also be known as a breadth
first search, it’s actually an interesting
problem but what we're doing is we're looking
at the tree and going out word on the tree.
So we're not going down one side and then
coming back and doing the other side we're
going outward on the levels of the tree.
And we'll see the code for this and it will
become a lot clearer in the next slides.