So here I want to show you the code for the
in-order, the pre-order, and the post-order
traversals in the tree.
And what you can see is that we've done, we're
taking in a pointer to a node.
That may not be the best solution to, in fact
we might have a driver function which calls
this for the root, but we do need to do this
recursively so it will take in a node pointer
to the node that we care about.
And what you can see with these three pieces
of code is that in reality they are the same;
the only difference is where we process.
And in this case it's just an output statement
where we process the current node, the node’s
data section.
So, in the in-order traversal it’s processed
in between the left and the right processing.
In the pre-order traversal, it's processes
the head of the left and right processing.
And the post-order traversal it's done after.
And since this is a recursive function that
really is going to consequently change the
output of the tree based on how we want to
go through each individual node.