Insertion into a tree is not terribly difficult.
The overview is kind of that we check to see
if the tree is empty and if it is of course,
this is just the first note on the tree will
create it that way.
If it's not then we have to go about and finding
the insertion point.
So, what I've done here is given you the code,
the first one is just the first thing is just
an if statement to check to see if the tree
is empty and if it is just pushing it on to
the tree.
If the trees down empty it's time to find
the insertion point and I do that by using
my two pointers temp previous.
And again, this should look very similar to
what we did with linked lists, in that eventually
temp will become null; temp will be the null
pointer.
And we're going to keep previous as one node
back from where we were.
when temp falls off into null, we can look
at previous and decide if we're going to push
on to the left or the right sub-child.
Now inside that while loop what we're doing
is comparing the item that we're going to
try to insert with the data that's inside
the node.
And in doing so we can decide if we should
go to the left or we should go to the right,
based on whether or not this is less than.
So if we go to the left and temp becomes null,
than the previous node is the node we have
to update to point to the new node that we
create.
And then that last if statement there just
does that same check again to decide whether
this should be a left child of the node or
whether it should be a right child of the
node based on whether it's less than an order
greater than the node.
There's no real recursion in this in this
algorithm; all it is, is a loop to find the
null.
And then once we found the know all to go
to the node immediately before that we saw
immediately before that an add the node on
as a left child or right child.
So as not it's not terribly difficult code;
It does involve the little bit of complexity
of pointers.
But if we keep track of where we were just
a moment ago using the previous pointer, then
when the temp pointer goes know all we know
where the nodes should be connected to.