Here's the code for deleting a node if it
has no children.
And what we're given is a pointer to this
node, actually it's a reference to a pointer
to this node.
The reason for that is that we're going to
be changing the pointer; we actually make
a change so that temp pointer.
So, what we do is to say if temps left is
equal to the null pointer and temps right
is equal to the null pointer: it just it has
no children.
So, there's no there's no work that really
has to be done here.
We’ll find out if the parent is the null
pointer, if it is then this is the root node
of the tree; it has no children if the last
note on the tree were done.
So, we can just set root equal to null pointer.
So, if we’re removing the last node in the
tree just remove the node.
And then of course will have to delete it
later.
And then we'll check to see if the parents
left is equal to this node.
So, if the parents left is equal to the node
that we're looking at, so we go up a level
and then we go back to the left then we're
going to have to set the parents left pointer
equal to the null pointer.
Remember this node has no children at all;
so if the parents left is this node that we're
looking at then let's delete the parents left.
If the parent's right, obviously if the parent
if it's not the parents left in the parent
exists then it's this must be the parent's
right pointer.
So, if the parent's right pointer is this
pointer, then we update that parent's right
pointer to get rid of this node and then we
actually get rid of the node.
So, in the no children case this is actually
pretty simple.
We basically just update the parent’s pointer
so that it points to null and then delete
the node.