If we have one child, then what we want to
do is promote that one child's data value
and delete the child node.
So, this assumes that we've already done the
check that we did in the previous slide to
see if both children don't exist.
If we don't have any children then we're going
to take care of it with the previous slide’s
code but now we recognize that there is one
child in either; we have a left child or we
have a right child.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to take a look and say if temps left is equal
to a null pointer, so we don't have a left
child that means by default we must have a
right child.
And the reason for that is that if we didn't
we would have gotten caught in the if statement
up above from the previous slide.
So, we're assuming now that we have this right
child and we're going to want to do is we're
going to want to get it to delete pointer.
This is just another pointer to say that this
is the node that we're going to delete.
And what we can do is promote the data value
up to the to the parent so now we copy to
delete data up to temps’ data, so we’re
copying the value from that right node up
into the parent node.
And then we'll copy the pointers up into the
parent node, and then what we can do is make
the pointer from our parent point to the new
node that we're going to delete.
And then we can delete the two delete values,
so in other words we're going to copy the
value up and then we're going to delete the
child node that does exist.
So that makes it a little bit easier that
we don't necessarily have to update the parent
pointers; all we have to do is make the data
values bring those pointers up to the to the
object that we're working in right now.
So the pointer for temp is actually going
to remain exactly where it is; the node temp
is remain exactly where it is.
And what we're going to do is move all the
pointers and the data values from the child
nodes up to the new temp.
We do have to take into account if the temps
left pointer exists, that its parent now is
going to change.
So, if we have a node on the left of the to
delete, we're going to have to change that
to deletes parent pointer to deletes left
parent pointer to the appropriate new value.
So, keeping in mind that we're not actually
going to delete the node that we are trying
to remove, we're actually just going to promote
the value and delete the node that's to the
right, and this case is to the right.
We're going to delete the node to the right
and promoted it’s data value.
If we're deciding that we're going to go to
the left then it's the exact same thing just
dealing with the left pointers instead of
the right pointers and keeping all that in
mind.
So it doesn't really require a lot of different
code it's really just flipping of the left
versus the right.
So it's just almost a copy of the same thing.
So that's if we have one child as opposed
to no children.
The problem with two children is well, bigger
and we're going to see that in just a minute.