We know that in a binary search tree, best
case scenario, the binary search tree is going
to result in big O of Log of N time for everything.
So insertion, searches, removals, all that's
going to take a Log N time.
Unfortunately, where BST's fail is if the
insertions that we're doing are already in
order.
And if they are, then all the insertions that
we do are going to result in right hand side
operations only.
So we're going to insert five and then we're
going to insert ten as the right sub child
of five, and then we're going to insert fifteen
as the right sub child of ten, and then going
to insert twenty is the right sub child of
fifteen and then we are insert twenty five
as the rights of child of twenty.
And what we end up with is all right children
and nobody on the left; the left is all equal
to null.
And so what we end up with really is a linked
list and we know that searching a linked list
is linear time, not Log N, linear.
So going back to our previous example of one
million elements now we've got to search five
hundred thousand elements because there's
no left elements at all; they're all right
elements.
And so this doesn't really work out very well
in the, in the easy binary search tree solution
because the operations that we're doing are
a little bit too simplistic.
What we really need to make sure is that we're
not constantly using the right subtree.
That we actually end up using those left pointers
to some extent and that we have a wider breadth
than we do depth, or at least equal breadth
and depth.