The solution of course is a balanced binary
search tree.
And the balanced binary search tree guarantees
that we use Log N or that we have Log N search
time.
To do that we need to do some additional work
and insertions and removals.
The d binary search tree does protect the
big O Log N insertion time.
Unfortunately as a result, insertions and
removals do take a little bit longer, but
they're still going to be close to Log N.
So, we're not changing this to a linear insertion
like we would have with a linked list or within
array; god help us.
But it does take longer than big theta Log
N so it's still going to be big O of Log of
N, but it's actually only something closer
to like two Log of N so the theta to does
change but the big O pretty much stays the
same.
There's two types of very popular balance
binary search trees.
There's one that's really easy to understand
but the performance isn't all that great,
called an AVL tree, and then there's one that's
really hard to understand the but the performance
is fabulous and that's called a red-black
tree.
If you were create a tree, if you were to
use a tree inside STL.
So, the STL actually does have two trees:
one is called a set and the other is called
a map.
And of course, there are multi-multi-mapped
trees in case we're interested in that.
But the STL set and the STL map are actually
implemented as red-black trees.
So here we actually have something that exists
in real life or in our real code life at least
that we're that we're studying at this point.