Here's an example of a good AVL tree.
So what we did was we did some insertions,
like we inserted the value of ten and we inserted
five and twenty and three, and those all got
inserted onto the tree.
What we have here is that ten has a height
of two.
Now how we calculated that was by looking
at the height of the left sub child and the
height of the rights sub child, and determining
that the maximum of those two heights is one
and then adding one to that.
So that's why the height of the node at three,
for example, is a zero because the height
of the left sub child is a negative one and
the height of the right sub child is a negative
one and we can add one to that, and add one
to the maximum of that which is the same value,
and we get zero.
So what we can do is say that this is a good
AVL tree because the height of all of the
nodes are, the height of all the left sub
child for every node in the height of all
the right sub child for every node, is equal
to a value that differing by only no more
than one.
So that the largest difference here is actually
if we get to the root node, if we take a look
at the root node, the height of the left sub
child five is one and the height of the right
sub child is zero, the value twenty.
We can also look at that node five which has
a height of the left sub child of zero and
the height of the right sub child as negative
one.
So, that's a difference of only, of only one.
So, in no case do we differ from the left
sub child to the right sub child by more than
one and so this is an acceptable AVL tree.