Here's an example of a really bad AVL tree,
or rather I should say one that doesn't meet
the AVL properties, right.
We call it a bad AVL tree but it just doesn't
meet the AVL property.
So, what happened was we inserted ten, we
inserted five, we inserted three, which sort
of looks like we had it before except the
ten’s left child is five and five’s left
child is three.
Now the height of three is zero, which means
the height of its left child is negative one,
the head of its right child is negative one;
that's fine.
They differ by no more than one.
The height of the node at five is one; the
height of its left sub child is zero, the
height of its right sub child is a negative
one.
So that differs by no more than one.
Where the problem comes as at that root node
ten there, which is a height of two.
And the height of two; the left sub child,
five, has a height of one but the right sub
child has a height of negative one.
So the difference there is two and now we've
got a problem.
And we can see this starting to form the same
classic problem where we had the right, right,
right, right, right problem from the previous
slide, where all the nodes are being inserted
as greater values.
Here the nodes are all being inserted lower
values, lesser values, so it's all going to
the left.
Regardless, if we let this propagate this
is going to end up as a linked list, we're
going to have the really poor insertion and
searching times that we had with linked lists.
Another example of a bad AVL tree here.
We can see that we did, it looks like the
insertion of ten, five, three, and twenty
and that all was fine; everything was okay
from the same as the previous example.
Except now we take the added component of
adding four, so here we added four onto the
right sub child of three.
And what happened was the node at four is
balanced, left sub child is negative one,
right sub child is negative one.
The height at three is balanced; left sub
child is negative one, right sub child zero.
The height at five, well that one we've got
a bit of an issue here because the height
of the node five, the left sub child is one
and the right sub child is a negative one.
So, that causes us a little bit of heartache
we're going to have to deal with that.
Unfortunately, we have to deal with these
as two different problems, because the solutions
that we use are different based on what whether
or not, well we'll see them in a later slide,
but they're based on a little bit of difference
in how we did the last insertion.
Either way these trees do not meet the AVL
property.
So, we do have to do some work to get them
to balance again.