What happens when we do have that outside-inside
insertion?
And in either way whether we're talking about
left right or whether we're talking about
right left, what we're saying is that the
heavier node is a different child than what
we decided on the parent.
So when we're looking at the grandparent node,
in this case we have twenty: the left child
of twenty is ten, the right child of ten is
fifteen.
We've got is a problem in which a single rotation
would not solve this.
What we really need to do is reorganize these
as a double rotation.
And a double rotation is actually pretty simple
because all we need to do is first do a counter
clockwise rotation around ten, so that we
end up in the same situation.
So first we'll do a counter clockwise rotation
about ten.
Which means the twenty's left sub child will
be fifteen, and then fifteen's left sub child
will be ten.
So, initially we sort of make the problem
not go away but we put the problem in a solution
that we can solve because we're going to generate
an outside-outside problem.
So initially the single rotation would not
solve this at all.
If we only used a single rotation we would
still have the problem of, even if we promoted
ten to be the root its right sub tree would
be twenty and the left sub child of twenty
would be fifteen.
So that's doesn’t solve the problem but
if we do a single rotation about the parent,
not about the grandparent but about the parent,
if do the single rotation about the parent
first.
Then what we end up with is a problem that
we can solve.
So we end up with twenty; its left child being
fifteen, fifteen’s left child being ten
and that's just a single rotation that we
can solve.
The end point is that we have fifteen as the
root; its left some child is ten and its rights
of child is twenty.
And that's the way that double rotation is
done.
So in fact if you look at the code, a double
rotation is actually done by two calls to
the single rotation function: once clockwise
and the others counter-clockwise so there's
not really much work that has to be done there.
But the double rotation problem does exist
and we do have to recognize it.