Red-black trees are designed to try and solve
the problem of the balanced binary search
tree.
One of the issues that comes up with AVL trees
that we kind of glossed over Is the need to
calculate those heights.
And unfortunately, whenever we do an insertion,
the heights are going to change.
Whenever we do a removal, the heights are
going to change.
Whenever we rebalance, the heights are really
going to change, so if we do a rotation, really
going to change.
And unfortunately, that means that we're going
to have to calculate those heights which takes
Log of N time, so really we're adding Log
N time on top of Log N time and that's two
Log N for big Theta.
It's not terrible, by no means, I mean it
would be much worse to put this into a linked
list but we can do a little bit better.
So the red-black tree aims to avoid the problem
of having to go back and recalculate heights
every time.
And the way that it does that is by four laws
and the four laws are kind of cryptic and
really doesn't make sense until you see it.
So, we're going to see it in a later slide,
but let's go over the laws and just get a
good idea.
So, the basis of the laws is that all nodes…
First law, one, right.
All nodes are colored either red or black.
Well that's not hard because all we have to
do is put a Boolean in there, in each node,
to say it's either red or black.
It's just a Boolean value so that's very simple.
The root is always black, and for that we
just say if we ever find that the root is
red we'll just recolor it to black; it has
no impact on anything.
So law two is very easy to comply with; if
the root is ever turned red, we just make
it black again.
Here's where life gets a little bit tougher,
but it's good to keep in mind that the purpose
of these laws is to determine when a rotation
is going to be necessary.
So, what we'd like to do is try and determine
when the rotation is necessary.
Keep that in mind as we go through laws three
and four.
Law three says that a red node cannot under
any circumstances have a red child.
Now, don't read any more into it than just
that, because it doesn't say that a black
node can't have a red child and it does not
say that a black node can't have a black child.
All it says is that if we have a red nose,
we cannot have a red child.
So that's the only restriction there.
What happens if we try to insert a red node
onto a red child well then we're going to
recognize that it needs to do a rotation or
we need to do a rebalance or something is
going to have to change.
Perhaps the color of the parent node is simple
enough that we can just recolor it to black;
maybe it's the root.
But we'll take care of that as we go through
more and we look at the actual code for this.
The core of this is that law three: a red
node can never have a red child.
The really hard one to maintain is that all
paths from the root to all children have to
pass through the same number of black nodes.
And this is where life gets really, really
confusing because if we're going through a
node we need to count it.
Now, how do we go about recognizing this without
going through all the paths.
It's important to keep in mind that the purpose
of the laws is only to recognize when a rotation
is necessary.
So, what we do is we'll say that we start
off with one node, the root, and the root
is always black; there's two nulls, one on
the left than one on the right of the root
node.
So if we go through and find the left null,
we've gone through one node, if we go through
and find the right null that we've gone through
one black node and that's no problem.
Insertions into a red black tree are going
to be red nodes.
So whenever we do an insertion of a new node.
We'll color the new node red.
That's not a law, that's just an implementation
factor.
So when we implement a new node we're going
to insert it as a red note.
So, if we had a value, for example of twenty
and we inserted ten is the left sub child
Then the left sub child will have two nulls
and that changes the number of paths but it
doesn't change the number of black nodes that
we go through.
We're still only going through the one black
node at the root.
So that's why this makes this makes some semblance
of sense.
Now you're going to ask yourself what happens
if we need to insert another node onto the
left some child of ten.
And the answer that is well it would be a
red node of a red child and all that means
that we're violating a law three, and that
we need to recognize that a rotation is necessary.
So, we've got these sort of solutions that
we can use to not violate the laws.
And we’ll talk about that later in the next
slide or in a later slide.
But what we're going to say is that these
are the laws of red black trees and we need
to recognize and maintain them; how we do
that is a much bigger problem.