The question that we have to ask first is
what is a tree, and the answer to that is
that it's a data structure designed to hold
items in a hierarchical pattern.
Now we talk about a hierarchical pattern and
what we mean by that is that there's one node
that's at the very, very top.
And that there's a bunch of nodes that are
down further, and some that are at the very
very bottom.
This is often used for searching; the tree
can be used in a lot of for an index for a
database for example.
Or we might use a binary search tree, hence
the name search tree, for searching information
that we might store.
Every node has one and only one parent node,
and that gives us that hierarchical fashion
so that every node has a parent.
Now of course there's one node that's a special
node which is at the very, very top and it
has no parent and that's called the root node.
Every node will have at least some storage
for pointing to children.
So, every node has zero or more children;
it may not actually have children but each
node is going to have the capability to point
to children nodes.
The storage for this is actually as a pointer,
just to the first node in the tree to the
highest node in the tree, and that's the root.
So, when we look at the class that we're going
to design.
It's really only going to have one pointer,
very much in the way that we did a linked
list is going to have one point there which
is the pointer to the root of the tree and
that's the highest node in the tree.
It's not necessarily the first node in the
tree it's not the lowest value, but we may
keep it as the center; this is the highest
node in the tree.
We'll talk about what that looks like.
The great thing about trees is that every
node looks like its own sub tree.
So every node looks like a tree by itself.
Now we know that naturally the root is the
natural start of the entire tree, but each
node could pretend to be a tree by itself.
And that leads us to a discussion of course
that going to come up again and again and
that is that recursion is going to happen
a lot in trees, because each node looks like
a tree and there's one node that is the root.
But we can treat all the nodes as if they
were their own tree.