We need to get through some definitions first.
The first one that we want to talk about is
a binary tree.
And a binary tree is a simple tree, remember
has a parent, has some children, except the
binary tree has a maximum of two children.
What we usually refer to them as is the left
and right child only for simplicity sake we
don't have any reason to call them left or
right, but we do have a maximum of two children
in the binary tree; doesn't mean that we have
always two children, of course some nodes
will have no children and some nodes will
have one child and then some nodes will have
two children, but the maximum is two children.
We can talk about the size of a tree.
The size of a tree is the number of nodes
that are in that tree.
So if we look at the size of the root node
of the tree, we're looking at the size of
the entire tree.
If we're looking at the size of a node that
has no children, that size is just one because
it's just that node.
And if we're looking at a size of a node with
a couple of children well then we have to
do some calculations to try and figure out
how many nodes are actually on this tree.
And we’ll see that in a later slide.
We could talk about the height of the tree
which is the distance or the number of links
from the root to the farthest child.
Now we could say that the height of a null,
for example the height of a null so no node
would be negative one, because it doesn't
have any height it’s actually a negative
height.
If we're talking about the height of a node
with no children at that height would be zero
because the distance from the node from the
root to its far this child is actually itself,
so that's a distance of zero.
And if the root node has only one child and
that no doesn't have any children, then the
root nodes height is one and the only child's
height is zero.
So that's a simple way to look at height and
give us an idea.
We'll use that in a later slide to talk about
the balance binary search trees.
We can talk about depth which is the distance
from the node to the root and that's actually
the inverse of the height.
So the root node, for example, has a depth
always of zero the distance from the root
node to itself will always be zero, of course.
And if we're talking about the most sub-child
than that's the actual depth that means the
depth would be equal to the height of the
root node; so the farthest child from the
root depth is actually equal to the roots
height.
So they are inverse to each other.
We could talk about a leaf node, which is
a node that has no children.
So the left in the right pointers for example
in a binary tree would be null.
And we can talk about a full node which is
the maximum number of children.
Obviously, if we're talking about a generic
tree, where there's no maximum number of children
then it's impossible to have a full node.
In a binary tree, any node that has two children
would be considered a full note; it can't
have any additional children.
So we use these definitions throughout the
discussion so that we have an idea of what
we're talking about.
The importance here is that you take away
these definitions because they're used in
our language for talking about trees and binary
search streets.