For trees that have an unlimited number of
children, so not binary search trees, but
trees that have an unlimited number of children.
The child storage pointers have to be stored
either as an irregular as a linked list.
And for that we really come up with two different
forms of storage that are common for this.
Now this is looking at each individual note
as it exists in main memory, so in main memory
if we look at the individual node what exactly
does that look like.
The first one is a parent-multi-child and
the parent node has an arrray of child nodes
contained into it.
Oftentimes, this is just a vector of child
pointers: so, pointers to tree nodes for example.
We would store in the node, we would store
the data; would probably also store a parent
pointer, but I haven't shown that here.
We have a data section and then we just have
an array or a vector of pointers to children
for however many children we have.
Obviously, if we have no children we don't
want to use any storage any additional storage,
so that's where the vector comes in handy
because it keeps track of that and it'll adjust
itself.
Now the other option is that we have a parent-child-sibling
structure, which more closely represents the
linked list.
The parent would point to the first or the
favorite child, we won't get into that discussion
report to the first child and the first child
would point to its sibling and the sibling
or point to its sibling and so on and so forth.
So what we've done is we've allowed the parent
to access all the sibling, all the children,
by accessing from the first child and then
the first child has access to the sibling
and the sibling has access to a sibling and
so on and so forth.
So it much more closely represents that of
a linked list: the child nodes’ are on a
linked list and the head pointer for that
link list is actually the child pointer from
the parent.
So we can represent this using a either a
parent multi child solution or parent child
sibling solution.
Now in the case where we have a value, a limited
number of children, an N value as we'll call
it.
If we have an N value, which is the number
of children that this node might have, then
we can just set up the node with that number
of pointers and it's not terribly difficult.
So we're going to go forward and consider
that we do have a limited number of children
because the unlimited number of children problem
doesn't often come up.
The unlimited number of children problem means
that each node has a variable number of children
and that complexifies has the issue quite
significantly, so we want to kind of avoid
this.
But I wanted you to see it just so that you
know in case you get into trees that might
need an unlimited number of children.