Now that we understand what a binary search
tree is and how it's created, let's talk about
what we need it for.
The best thing that we can do with binary
search tree, the benefit, the huge benefit
that we get is that a binary search tree provides
in best case scenario that searching the binary
search tree will take Log of N time.
So, we can go through a binary search tree
in Log N times because what we've done is
spread out the accesses, so that each level
creates a doubling effect of how many nodes
we can have on that level.
So for example, if we take a search which
would have let's say an array of a million
elements.
If we were to have a linear search through
that on average it would take five hundred
thousand accesses through the array to find
it; we have to go through half of the array
before we find the thing that we're looking
for.
But if we have it inside of a binary search
tree the magic number there, the number of
searches that it takes is twenty, not five
hundred thousand and twenty because the log
of a million is twenty.
Each time we look at her node we're saying
whether we should go to the left or go to
the right or if we're lucky we found it inside
the node, so inside the node once we make
the decision to go to the left and go to the
right or go to the right we've eliminated
half of the possibilities.
So, every iteration through this searching
algorithm eliminates half of the possibilities
from the from the set and that means that
we have a log N problem.
So searching in a right of a million elements
would take five hundred thousand accesses;
searching a binary search tree of a million
elements takes twenty, which is a huge difference
of course.
Insertions also should take Log of N time.
Deletion should take a log of N time or close
to that we're going to see that it's not exactly
that in a later slide but it's pretty close.
So, the benefit here is that we get for large
sets, we get a really significant savings
in time when we use a binary search tree to
keep this in order.
We can use these for in order storage of any
items which can be compared using a less than
operators, as long as the less than operators
overloaded for that class, you can go ahead
and use that.
for in order storage of elements the binary
search tree is a really effective and efficient
solution for the storage.
If we don't need to keep it in order then
it's not so much a concern, we can keep it
in an array, but if we do need to keep water
on these values than a binary search tree
is really beneficial.