I wanted you to see the code here for the
binary search tree node, and this helps us
a little bit to understand what we're looking
at when we see the binary search trees no
order when we're talking about the binary
search tree.
What I've got here is just a data element
and it looks very much like we had with the
linked lists.
There's just a data element and I have a templated,
so it's a template type T. And then we have
a pointer to the parent, pointer to the left
sub-child or pointer to the rights sub-child,
and that's it.
That's all the storage that the entire BST
node class has.
I had a constructor in the same way that I
have a constructor for the linked list; it's
just useful for setting things up and it makes
creation of nodes a little bit easier later
on.
I have a friend just like I did in the linked
list, so the very common, a very much common
with the linked list here except that we've
got two pointers, a left and right child.
We're going to get into this getSize class,
in just a minute of the getSize function in
just a minute, what it's going to do is just
tell us how many nodes there are as children
and this node for the node.
So, we're talking about the size really that's
by definition if you remember back from the
definitions we did a couple of slides ago,
this is just the size of this individual node.
So this is the format for the BST node class
and you're going to see a lot of commonalities
with the linked list.