hello everybody I wanted to show you a
simple example of how we could create a
dynamically resizing array or rather how
we can dynamically resize an array and I
wanted to do that by starting out with
just a simple array its size is 10 and
it holds some stuff you can see the code
on your screen I hope we're looking at
just an array that holds 10 things and
we've gotten to the point where we'd
like to add one more element so we'd
like to add that one more element into
the array and unfortunately because the
array is already full we don't know how
it's possible that we could add any more
elements into this array so what we're
going to do is write a very simple
function which is going to resize the
array and we're going to give it the
array itself as well as the current size
and the new size and we're of course
going to have to go ahead and write that
function so it's not going to return
anything and it's going to be called
resize array and it's going to take the
array as a pointer now we have to
recognize that the array will change so
it's important that we pass that array
by reference or rather that pointer by
reference because in this case the array
is going to have to be resized and the
only way that we can resize an array is
by destroying it and creating a new one
in its place with the old data so we
have to take into account I'm going to
call this current size we have to take
into account that that array pointer
will actually change which means it does
have to be passed in by reference and
we're going to take in new size so we're
going to create this function which
takes this array the current size and
the new size and the purpose of this
function is to grow the array into a new
size and we can talk about how to shrink
the array we can do that as well but
that's not the core of what we're trying
to do here so I'm not going to focus on
that so when we look at this the first
thing we should recognize is that we're
going to have to create a new array so
we're going to need a temporary pointer
and that temporary pointer should point
to an array of size new size so we're
going to create on the heap a new array
that is pointed to by temp so temp is
going to point to an array of new size
and then we've got to go through and
copy over all the elements
of the array into the new array so one
by one we're going to have to go through
the old array and copy the elements and
we can do that just by saying temp at I
is equal to AR are at I okay so we've
got now two arrays the original array
ARR and new array pointed to by 10 and
they effectively hold the same data and
the only difference is that ARR is
completely full and temp now has a
little bit of extra space left
so temp has some free space which we can
recognize as the new size of the array
and then we're going to just take care
of deleting the old array so now we've
done a new operation we know that if we
don't do a corresponding delete
operation we're going to have a memory
leak or garbage on the heap so what we
can do to take care of that is delete
the array
ARR which cleans up the memory space
pointed to by arr now obviously that
means everything in there is deleted but
that's ok because we've made a copy of
all that into temp and then here's where
it's really important that we pass this
array in by reference we're going to
make a are are equal to temp that's
effectively resizing the whole array so
right now those couple of lines of code
there what we've done is created a new
array temporary array of the new size
that we want we copy over each of the
individual elements and then we delete
the original array and make the original
array point to the temporary array the
effect of that is that we've resized the
array now obviously this is a very
involved operation and it's going to
have to go through each element of the
array in order to make the copy so we
don't just want to go up by a small
amount what we'd like to do is say that
the new size should be something like
double the size so down here in main
I'm going to say that the new size
should be the size times 2 and then I
can say size equals new size because
we've now updated the size of the array
and we can put our new element into the
additional position so ARR at size plus
plus is equal to
one more and that has the effect of
taking our original array which was only
ten elements and now storing the same
information in a new array that has 20
elements and then storing the position
10 which of course would be the eleventh
element the element that we're trying to
store
so we have the capability now not just
to create a static sized array we have
the capability to create an array that
can grow and we can do that on the heap