Hi.
My name is Jerry and I will be your instructor
for the Computer Architecture and Organization
Section of the CS-Bridge Program.
So far, we have covered several paradigms
and techniques of computer programming.
And these techniques have enabled us to write
software code for different purposes.
So in this section, we will cover how the
CPU interprets this code and executes it.
Then we will discuss what is inside the CPU
that allows it to execute such code.
More specifically, we’ll cover the assembly
language and mnemonic machine code, which
are human-readable representations of machine-level
instructions, we will go over the CPU execution
steps, and we will detail the microarchitecture
of the CPU.