Here we put the full version of the code segment
in MIPS mnemonic notation.
The semicolon indicates the beginning of a
comment.
So anything following the semicolon is a comment.
This is similar to the forward slashes in
C or C++.
Regarding the data segment, we know that each
double word data is 64 bits, or 8 bytes, because
we are using MIPS64.
So once we know the base address of the data
segment, we can find the addresses of all
data in the segment.
Note that this is the same approach that the
CPU uses to determine the address of data
that it accesses.
That is, the CPU uses the base address of
the data segment and the offset of the target
data within the segment.
So putting it all together, we get the following
notation for the code and data segments in
MIPS mnemonic.
Note that all addresses are in hexadecimal.