Let’s illustrate this with the A = B+C example.
Recall that MIPS64 is a RISC architecture,
so there must be four machine-level instructions
to perform A = B+C: two instruction to load
B and C to registers, one to add the registers,
and one to store the result back to memory
location of A. Since there is a one-to-one
mapping between machine code and assembly,
we can convert this high-level code into four
assembly level instructions.
The first instruction copies the value of
B from the data segment to a register; let
us assume the assembly labels the register
using the symbol t1.
The second instruction copies the value of
C from the data segment to another register,
say register t2.
At this point, the value of B and C are in
t1 and t2 respectively.
The third instruction adds the the registers
t1 and t2 and puts the result into register
t3.
The last instruction copies the value of t3
into the data location that is allocated for
A.
Here we see the more formal assembly language
code for this high-level operation.
The first two assembly-level instructions
are load double word, or LD.
In this respect the double word indicates
to the processor that the data to be loaded
from memory to register is of size double
word, or 64 bits.
The third instruction is a double word add,
or D--DD, where the ALU adds the two registers
t1 and t2 and puts the results in t3.
The final instruction is store doubleword,
or SD, where the content of t3 is copied into
memory address of A. Note the syntax of the
assembly-level instructions.
For load doubleword, we see the destination
register is put first, followed by the label
of the memory address.
For the doubleword add, the destination register
is put first, followed by the source register
operands.
For the Store Doubleword, the source register
is put first, followed by the label of the
destination memory location.
So, since assembly language has a one to one
correlation to machine code, we can map each
assembly instruction of the A = B+C operation
to a machine-level instruction.