Although assembly-language provides a one-to-one
correlation with machine code, it still has
some limitations with fully illustrating how
the CPU interprets the machine-level instructions.
And since this is a computer architecture
and organization course, we want to have as
good of a feel as possible of the CPU inner-workings.
With that in mind, we use MIPS mnemonic format
to represent software code.
We can think of mnemonic format as a readable
version of machine-level code.
It interprets all of the fields of machine-level
code to better illustrate the inner-workings
of the CPU.
When writing in MIPS mnemonic notation, we
generally use hexadecimal format, except for
register names.
For some cases, the hexadecimal notation of
number may take too much space.
In such cases, we use the decimal notation
of that number and explicitly say it is the
decimal notation.
For example FFFF in hexadecimal is equal to
-1 in decimal, so we put -1 in parentheses
and add the 10 subscript to indicate this
a decimal notation.
This is just to make it easier to write MIPS
in mnemonic format.