We will now show how to execute this MIPS
code in table representative of the components
of the CPU.
So the table has the following columns: an
instruction column that lists the instructions
in MIPS mnemonic format; a PC column, where
PC stands for program counter.
The Program Counter is a special register
in the CPU that holds the address of the next
instruction to execute.
Then, there is a column for each register
used in the MIPS mnemonic code.
Since our example uses registers R8, R9, and
R10, there is a column for each.
There is also a column for each data in the
data segment.
Since there are 3 pieces of data in the data
segment, there are three columns and we use
their addresses to label each.
The last column is a memory access column
to indicate what kinds of memory accesses
the associated instruction makes.
Since we are using the MIPS mnemonic format
for the table, the content of the table will
be in hexadecimal, unless stated otherwise
using the subscript notation.
The first column of the table is ALWAYS the
Initial column.
This column illustrates the state of the CPU
before execution of our code.
At the initial state, the data segment has
the original data of the variables in the
code.
So we write those values in their respective
columns in the table.
In addition, during initialization the CPU
writes the address of first instruction in
the Program Counter and writes the base address
of the data segment in the R8 register.
Remember that the Program Counter stores the
address of the next instruction to execute.
So since the next instruction to execute is
the first one, it make sense that PC has that
address before any instruction is executed.
Since we don’t initialize the values of
the other registers, we set them as question
marks.
For each instruction, the first thing the
CPU does is it reads the instruction from
the code segment; that is known as an instruction
fetch or instruction read.
We concatenate it as INS read in the memory
access column.
The CPU uses PC to get the address of the
instruction to fetch
Since the Program Counter points to the address
of the next instruction, once an instruction
is fetched, the Program Counter has to be
updated to point to the next instruction.
Generally, this update is done by simply incrementing
the Program Counter by 4, because instructions
are 4 bytes long.
Later in this course, we will when Program
Counter is not always incremented by 4 due
to branch and jump instructions.
We then analyze the instruction to see what
it does and update the columns of the table
accordingly.
In our example, the instruction is a load
double instruction, where the base address
of the data segment is in register R8, the
offset is 0, and the destination register
is R9.
So, the CPU first calculates the address of
the data in memory.
This is done by adding the content of the
base register to the offset.
Once the address is obtained, the CPU reads
the memory at that address to get the data.
Since this is a memory access, we update the
memory access column to indicate a data read.
Once the value data is obtained from memory,
the CPU writes it in the destination register.
For all registers and memory locations that
are not modified by this instruction, we put
an NS label to indicate Not Stored.
In other words, this instruction does not
store anything in those registers and data
locations and their values remain the same
as before.