Let us now discuss the syntax and semantics
of the Load doubleword, doubleword add, and
store doubleword instructions that we have
already covered.
Here we see the syntax and semantics of the
Load doubleword.
Rt is the destination register, Rs holds the
base address of the data segment and the offset
holds the position of the data relative to
that base address.
The offset is always at most 16 bits.
To calculate the address of the target data,
the CPU adds the value of the base address
in Rs to the offset.
But Rs is a 64-bit register, and the offset
is 16 bits.
The addition requires both values to be the
same size.
To change the size of the 16-bit offset to
64 bits, we perform what is called a sign
extension.
The basic idea of a sign extension is to increase
the number of bits used to represent a value,
while keeping the sign.
So the naïve approach to extend a 16-bit
value to 64 bits would to append 48 zeros
to the left of the original 16-bit value.
However, this approach doesn’t work if the
number is negative.
This is because if we extend a negative number
with zero bits, then it becomes positive because
the most significant bit is now 0 instead
of 1.
So sign extension works by first looking at
the most significant bit of a binary, and
using the value of that bit to extend it to
the desired bitsize.
The three examples here show how to sign extend
different 16-bit values to 64 bits