Let's analyze the running time of selection-sort
and see how efficient this algorithm is.
Before we analyze selection sort, let's start
by analyzing find index of min, this helper
function, so we would know what's the cost
of each call there and then we'll just use
that when we are analyzing a selection sort
algorithm.
So let's start with a find index of min; let's
find the running time and the running time
of that function.
Like all algorithms that we are analyzing,
we need to give the running time as a function
of the size of the input.
So, in this case the size of the input N would
be the number of elements in the range were
searching for the index of min; so let’s
have N as the number of elements between low
and high, arithmetically we’ll just have
high minus low plus one, that the number of
elements between low and i so this is our
N. And let's analyze the running time as a
function of N.
So once again, before we start the for loop,
we are doing a constant amount of operations
and after the for loop we are having a constant
amount of operations.
So min equals ARR low, minInd equals low,
that’s theta of one, and return min Ind
that’s also theta of one.
And we’re mostly interested at the cost
of this for loop.
Once again the body here, each iteration is
constant; it's only two or three primitive
operations so that’s theta of one.
Which means that the number of iterations,
that’s basically the cost of this for loop.
Here the number of iterations is N, so the
entire cost is theta of N.