Let's go to the selection-sort algorithm now
that we know that find index of min is theta
of N, in other words is linear, let's use
that when we're analyzing the selection-sort
algorithm.
Once again let's define N, as the size of
the input ARR size in this case, and let's
try to figure out what T of N is.
So, we have a for loop that we need to figure
out what's the cost of this for loop.
But not like the other algorithm we had so
far, each iteration the body costs differently.
And let's try to see what the cost of each
iteration.
So basically the most expensive, I would say
operation here, is the call of the function
find index of min.
And then since the range changes from iteration
to iteration, basically the linear cost or
the number of elements that we are going over,
changes from iteration to iteration.
I would say that the cost of the body could
be described as theta of N minus i, right.
So when i equals zero, when we're going over
the entire range, we are basically paying
N, right.
When i equals one, when we're going over one
item less we’re basically doing N minus
one.
And when i equals two, we’re doing N minus
two and so on.
So basically when we are summing up all the
cost of calling find index of min, we'll pay
N for the first call, and we'll pay N minus
one for the second call, and N minus two for
the third call and so on and so on, till the
last call would be two and one.
So that's basically the cheapest score.
So the entire set of calls to find the index
of min would be the sum of that, of these
numbers: N plus N minus one plus N minus two
and so on.
You know that this here, actually we've seen
it in one of our previous models, that we
can think of it as a kind of a triangle inside
a square.
And we know that it is theta of N squared.
You can look at the exact formula and figure
out where it's theta of N squared but we've
already seen that this kind of a sum is a
quadratic running time.
Yeah, so basically meaning that selection-sort
is a quadratic running time algorithm for
sorting.