The second sorting algorithm we're going to
talk about is called merge-sort; it is a recursive
algorithm, a recursive sorting algorithm.
We can think of, again a few approaches to
recursively sort a sequence of numbers, but
let me show you how merge-sort works.
So for example we have this array of numbers:
fourteen, five, eight, ten, thirteen, one,
eighteen, and three, and we want to sort it.
One way of doing it is to have a three step
process.
First step, would be, would say let's store,
let's sort, recursively the first half of
the numbers: fourteen, five, eight, and ten.
Again it’s recursively, so our assumption
is that when we are trying to sort it, it
would just do the job basically sort the elements
so it would reorder the elements in a sorted
order.
So, first step would reorder the first half
of the numbers to be sorted; kind of a magic,
but okay, that's one part of the job.
Step two, you can probably guess would say
sorts recursively the second half of the numbers,
in this case: thirteen, one, eighteen, and
three, should be sorted in an increasing order.
That would reorder them to be: one, three,
thirteen, eighteen.
Now that we have two halves that each one
is sorted on its own, we would need to merge
these two halves into one sorted sequence.
So step three would say you merge these two
halves together into one sorted sequence.
So after doing step three, we would have the
numbers all sorted together: one, three, five,
eight, ten, thirteen, fourteen, eighteen.
Let's do it one more time.
Step one: sort the first half of the numbers.
Step two: sort the second half of the numbers.
And step three: combine these two sorted halves
into one sorted sequence.
Cool; not very intuitive.
But yeah, actually that that's a recursive
algorithm.
We’ll implement it first and after that
we'll try to trace the execution and see how
the recursion here unfolds into sorting the
entire array.
Let's go ahead and implement.