So let's execute and implement the merge-sort
algorithm.
So I have a min here that we have an array
of eight elements, obviously not sorted: fourteen,
five, eight, and so on.
I’ve declared ARR size to be eight.
I did all hardcoded but you can see how we
can make it in a general form.
And then we're calling merge-sort, in order
to sort this array.
Initially, it will pass ARR in the entire
range of elements as our low and high; basically
low is zero and high would be the last index
ARR minus one and then we're calling print
array in order to print the array after merge-sort
basically sorted the elements.
Merge-sort is a very simple function that
just iterates over the elements, prints them
with a space and a new line at the end; so
just prints the array one by one, element
by element.
And merge sort as we have seen before is a
recursive algorithm it knows i don't equal
anything otherwise we set the min index to
be low plus high div two, we call him merge-sort
with the first half from low to min index.
And then we call merge-sort just for the second
half from an index plus one to high and then
we merge these two halves together, basically
having the first half from low to mid-ind
and the second half ending at high.
We now only have to implement the merge algorithm.
We've described before but let's implement
it in C++.
So we have the prototype; let’s take it
over here and implement it.
Okay.
So first thing we have the low left, high
left, and only right, so let’s declare low
right variable, just so we can set it to be
high left plus one, right.
That's where the right side starts: one element
after the left side ends, right.
So now we have low left, high left, low right,
and high right.
Another thing, let's also figure out how many
elements we're trying to merge together so
let's have a size variable.
Let's set size to be the high right minus
low left; that's basically the entire range
we're sorting, we're merging plus one, so
that's the size here.
And then we need to create an array for the
result of the merge sequence; so let's have
pointer int star merged array.
And let’s allocate memory for that array:
merge ARR equals new int of size elements.
Again, we cannot do the merge in place because
we'd be stepping on values that we’re not
necessarily done working on.
You can try thinking why we can't implement
this merge in place, basically on the same
array we are reading, we have the sequence
on, so we're using an additional array.
And again, since we don't know how many elements
we're going to have in this array; it would
kind of be a static array, has to be in a
dynamic array, that's why we're using the
memory allocation here to allocate a new array
of size elements.
Now that we have this array and we have the
input arrays, the two halves, we can start
merging them into the merged array.
For that as we've seen we would need three
indexes: one for the current element we're
looking in the first half, then for the first
element we're looking in the second half,
and then the index where we are currently
writing our result.
So, let's declare these three indexes here:
we'll have the index of the right side, the
index of the left side, and let's also have
the index of the results.
So I’ll have iRight, iLeft and iRes.
Let's start with iLeft; let’s set iLeft
to be the low left, right; that's where the
left side starts.
iRight would be where the right side, starts
basically high left plus one or we have low
right that we created.
So we have iLeft and iRight set to the beginning
of the left and right side.
iRes would be set to zero, right, because
that's where we want to start writing the
result into the merged array.
And then we should over and over repeatedly
choose the element, the smaller element, between
the one at the iLeft position and the one
in the iRight position; so we’ll use a while
loop here, again, let's keep the Boolean conditions
for a later stage.
And then each iteration, let’s pick one
from iLeft and iRight, so let's ask: if the
element at the iLeft position is less than
the element at the iRight position that means
that this element should be taken, right,
there the iLeft one is smaller so it should
become first.
So, let's put at merged array at the current
position, at iRes, let’s put there the element
from iLeft, this element here, right.
So we are writing to the result array the
element that is currently smaller between
iLeft and iRight, the left one in this case.
Then we need to increment iLeft and also obviously
increment iRes, since we’ve written to that
position.
Otherwise, if basically ARR iLeft is not less
than the iRight one, we should take one from
iRight.
So let's put it at the merged array at the
iRes position, in this case the array element
from iRight, and now we should increment iRight
in addition to incrementing iRes, right.
So each iteration we are choosing one from
iLeft or iRight to write to the merged array,
depending on which one is smaller; either
rewriting iLeft incrementing iLeft by one,
or writing the iRight elements to the array
and incrementing iRight.
We do that over and over and over, as long
as we have two candidates to choose from.
Eventually one of them would go over the entire
range of the array and we would have to take
the tail of the other array.; so we can keep
on going while they are still validly inside
the range of their halves.
So basically let's keep on going while the
current index in the left is still less or
equal to the high left, right; that means
that the letter iLeft is inside the left half.
And we also need the same for the right side,
so the iRight is less or equal to the higher
end of the right side, high right, right.
So while they are both inside their arrays,
we want to choose one of them.
Eventually one of the halves, we would end
our work on it and then we would need to take
the tail from the other parts.
So we could either use an IF statement here
to see which one ended and copy the rest,
or we can just use a while, actually two while
loops here that…
So we'll have a while here and a while loop
just after that.
This one would take care of the tail we have
in the first array, and this one would take
care of the tail we have in the second array,
we are certain that after the first while
loop, after this loop, there would be only
one tail so currently only one of these two
whiles would be executed.
If there is a tail here it would be copied
and then this while loop won’t even execute
once or if there is no tail here, so this
while won't be executed and this while would
copy the data from the second half.
So, let's take care of the first array first
half.
So while, again, iLeft it is less or equal
to high left; that's basically saying there
is a tail in the left side that should be
copied.
In this case, we should do what we've done
here: basically taking two of the merged array
at the iRes position, the element at the iLeft
position, right, incrementing iLeft and iRes.
So, that takes care of the tail left in the
first half in the left half of our array.
And if there is no left half then this while
won't be executed at all right.
If iLeft is not less or equal to high left,
this body won't be executed.
And same thing for the right side, so if iRight
is less or equal to high right then again
the merged array at our current position would
just be the element from iRight and then let’s
increment this value and iRes.
So now that's basically it; now we've picked
the right candidates between iLeft and iRight
over and over and over, when one of them ended
we just copied the remaining tail to the merger
array.
After these three whiles, we are definite
that all the elements are at the merged array.
Since we said that the merge function originally
should reorder of the elements in the array
from lower left to high right, it's not good
enough for us to have the merge sequence in
a totally new array, right.
So we would need to copy the elements from
the merged array back to our array.
So for that we would have a for statement
and let’s do something like, we would need
to copy from the merged array to the original
array and the merged array basically ranges
from zero to the size, right size minus one,
where the array we want to put the elements
not from the zero index but from the low left
index.
So we would need to set two set of indexes
here; we would need i for the merged array
and let’s do ARR that would be low left
for the second array.
Okay, something like that.
Let's just declare i and iARR, so we have
these two indexes.
And in the second you’ll help me figure
out what we want to do here, but basically
the body would be copy to ARR at iARR position,
the element from the merged array at i index.
So we'll have both indexes increasing or getting
bigger simultaneously, so we need i plus plus
and i ARR plus plus.
But they start at different positions, so
we want i to be an index in the merged array
starting at zero and want iARR to be an index
if they are are a starting at low left.
So we just set them initially with different
values, each time we’ll increment them,
we just need to do it the right amount of
times; we can either use our iARR to control
it or i to control it.
Let’s just do less than size; size, if you
recall, that’s number of elements we have
all together that we want to merge or in other
words the size of the merged array.
So we can go from zero to size, each time
incrementing by one copying this element to
the corresponding position in ARR, basically
the iARR position.
After we've done doing that copy, basically
we’re done, right.
So we have the merged sequence in our ARR
array, what we need to do now is just delete
the memory, the location we had for the merged
array.
So for that let’s use the deleted operator,
which is an erase so I’m using empty brackets,
that seems to be this function here.
And now that we have merge-sort and everything,
let's just try to execute it; see that it
really sorts.
We have the sequence sorted increasing order:
one, three, five, eight, ten, thirteen, fourteen,
and eighteen, which is exactly the sorted
sequence in the array.
So it seems to be working fine.
So merged is a fun function; we had a few
details when we worked on it.
It's a cool function but I think more interesting,
more surprising here, is the merge-sort algorithm,
where we surprisingly called merge-sort two
times assuming it sorts the first two halves,
and apparently it does.
All we have left to do is just merge them
together and we've implemented the merge function,
so that it is kind of surprising, you can
think.
But let's go ahead and trace the execution
and convince yourself how this basically works.