Let's take a look at selection sort.
As I said earlier it's very basic our sorting
algorithm, maybe the most intuitive or naïve
algorithm we can think of; sort of how you
would explain your kid how to sort using this
approach.
So, let me demonstrate the idea here.
So, assuming we have a collection of elements,
obviously not sorted: five, fourteen, ten,
eight, thirteen and so on.
It would be an iterative process each time
placing the minimum element at the next position;
so it's going to work something like that.
So let's take a look at the entire range we’re
sorting and first iteration, we are looking
to place at the zero position, in the first
position, the minimum element.
So we’ll search for the minimum element,
we’ll get this one, index-five, and then
we'll just swap them.
So one would be at the beginning and five
would be somewhere at the rest of the elements.
So our range would now be only the elements
from the second on.
This iteration, second iteration, will place
the second minimum at the second position;
we’ll search for the minimum in that varied
range: that would be two and we'll swap the
two in fourteen placing two at that position.
The range is shorter now; we'll search for
the minimum that would be three and we'll
swap them, three and a ten, so three would
be in the right position.
So now we have one, two, and three already
ordered, and next we find the minimum in the
valid range.
That would be three in the index-eleven and
we'll swap them.
So, three would be at the right position and
so on and so on.
Yeah, let’s try to implement this idea.