Let's implement a selection-sort algorithm.
So we'll write a function, selection-sort,
that is given an array, basically the starting
address int ARR brackets and logical size
ARR size, and this function should reorder
the elements so they would be in an increasing
order.
No return value here, so it would, it's a
void function basically.
As we said it's an iterative algorithm, so
we need to iterate over the elements one after
the other, over the indexes basically or the
positions, one after the other each iteration
placing the correct element, i-th order element,
in the i-th position.
So we’ll use a for loop to iterate over
the indexes, and we'll use an index i ranging
from one up to ARR size minus one; so i goes
from zero less than there ARR size plus plus.
Each iteration will search for the index where
the minimum element is so we'll have min index
equals to the location where the minimum element
is.
For that we would define a function: find
index of min, right.
So each iteration min index would get whatever
find index of min function returns and after
we do that we need to swap them.
But let's first define the prototype of find
index of min.
So find index of min would get basically the
array but it also should get the range where
we are looking for the minimum index.
So initially it would probably be the entire
array, then it would be with one item less,
and another item less and so on and so on
through.
So let's assume that find index of min would
get the low index and the high index to represent
the range where we’re searching for the
minimum index.
So find index of min is given the position
where our array starts, low and high indexes
to indicate the range we’re searching the
minimum in, and it should return an int, basically
the index of the minimum element in the positions
between low and high.
So, assuming we have this function, in a minute
or two we’ll implement that as well, but
assuming we have this function each iteration
we need to find the index of min in the current
valid range.
So first iteration it should be from zero
to the end, then it should be from one to
the end, then from two to the end, and then
from three to the end, and so on.
So basically we are searching for the index
of min on the array ARR starting at index
i, right; first iteration starting at index
zero, second iteration the starting index
is one, the next iteration the starting in
the two, and so on.
And every iteration we stop at the end of
the array; so first edition it goes zero to
the end, then one to the end, then two to
the end, and three to the end.
Each time we're searching for the minimum
index in that range.
After we get that min ind for each iteration,
we're just swapping the current element ARR
i with the element at the min index, ARR min
Ind.
That's basically it; that’s the selection-sort
algorithm.