Let's implement the find index of min so we
would have that as well.
So once again find index of min is given the
starting index, the starting address of the
entire array, but in order to indicate the
range we are searching for the minimum index
we have low and high, two indexes that basically
indicate that range.
We would need to accumulate the index of the
minimum element; actually, let's accumulate
two things, not only the index of the minimum
value, but also the minimum value itself.
So that have two variables min and min ind.
And let's accumulate these two values over
the path of the elements between low and high.
So initially, let's set min to be the first
element: ARR at the low position, the min
ind would be low obviously.
And then, we’ll iterate over the rest of
the elements using a for loop basically iterating
from low plus one to high, accumulating the
minimum and the minimum index.
Eventually after doing all of that, we would
just return the index of the minimum: the
min ind.
So let's just iterate and accumulate that
value.
So we'll use an index i ranging from low plus
one, low is already taken care of before the
loop, so we’ll start at low plus one, up
too high so for i goes from low plus one less
or equal to high incrementing by one, i plus
plus.
Each iteration let's compare ARR i, the current
element, to the minimum we've seen so far,
right.
So if ARR i is less than the minimum we've
seen so far that is the new minimum.
Basically we’ll assign min to be ARR i and
also save min index as our current location
as i.
So if we first set min and min index to be
the first element, then we’re starting to
iterate from the second and on up to i, each
time checking whether we need to update the
minimum index.
We are accumulating both min index and min
itself, eventually we can just return the
min index.
So all together, we have a function that finds
the index of min in a range from low to high
and by calling it over and over on range that
changes each time and the swap, we are basically
sorting the entire array.