Let's implement this sorting algorithm, and
it's a recursive algorithm, so let's do it
correctly.
So we’ll write a function merge-sort, it’s
supposed to rearrange the elements so is doesn’t
need to return any value since it's a void
function.
And the parameters are obviously the array
and basically something to tell the range
of elements.
So we can do it in two ways, either pass the
starting address of our current part of the
array we're trying to sort and the logical
size, or we can always pass the starting location
of the entire collection.
And in order to indicate the range we're trying
to sort, we'll have two indexes, low and high,
that kind of indicate the range.
Something similar to what we've done in the
find index of min at selection-sort, where
we had the starting position sticked and the
low and high indicated where we we’re searching
the index of min, same thing here.
We want to sort only in the range from low
to high but it's located in a more bigger
sequence starting at address ARR, so merge
sort would get the starting position of the
entire sequence and low and high to indicate
the current range we're trying to sort.
Okay, so that the prototype of the merge-sort
algorithm.
And then since it's a recursive algorithm,
we need to start with the base case.
So if we're trying to sort the smallest sequence
possible, basically the sequence of a single
element or in other words if low and high
are equal to one another.
In this case, it is already sorted so we don’t
need to do anything, just return an empty
return statement with no value because it's
void we don’t need to return any value,
just break out of the function.
Otherwise, if it is not a single element,
a collection, we have a real range of elements
we want to sort.
Let's do it with the three step algorithm
we've just described.
So we have our array, right.
We have low and the high, indicating the range
of elements we want to we want to sort.
And then first step is basically for the first
half of the elements.
So we would need to figure out where this
first half starts, yeah we know what starts
at low, but where it ends.
So we would need some kind of an index mid;
let's define this mid.
And just as we had in the binary search algorithm
in our previous model, mid would be the average
between the low and the high, basically low
plus high div two.
Now that we have mid, let’s sort the first
half, right.
Let's make it in increasing order, so let's
call merge-sort; it's a recursive algorithm
so merge-sort would do the job, basically
sort the first half of the numbers if we call
it correctly.
So in order to indicate the range of the first
half, the starting address would be the same
array, but the low and the high, in this case
would be low and mid.
We want to sort the elements starting at low
ending at mid.
After we've done that, so this line here sorts
the entire first half of the elements.
Then we need to sort the second half of the
elements.
Once again, let's call merge-sort in order
to recursively sort.
And then, let's pass the second half as a
parameter.
So that, in order to create that half we need
to know where it starts; so it starts one
after where the first act ended at mid plus
one and where it ends, obviously at high.
So let’s call merge sort with the same starting
address ARR but the range of elements we want
to sort now is starting at mid plus one ending
at high.
So after these two calls, we have the first
half of the number sorted and the second half
of the number sorted, we now just need to
merge them together into one whole sequence.
For that we better create unique function,
a designated function, to do that job.
We'll call it merge; and merge should take
these two halves and combine them together.
So the parameters for merge would be the starting
ARR, and some values to indicate where the
first half starts, where the first have ends,
where the second half starts and where the
second half ends.
So we would have the low left and the high
left, to indicate where the first or the low
left index is and where the index of the high
element of the left side.
And instead of having low right and high right
to indicate where the right side starts and
ends, we don't need both of them because the
right side starts right after the left side
ends, right.
It should start one after high left.
So, we don't need to pass that as a parameter;
let’s only have the high right.
So we have where the left side starts where
the left side ends, and where the right side
ends, obviously we know where the right start
starts.
So the prototype would be: ARR low left, high
left, high right.
And it's a void function, it rearranges the
elements, it doesn’t need to return any
value.
So assuming we have that, we’ll make and
implement this function in a few minutes,
assuming we have the merge after calling the
two recursive calls; after having the first
to have sorted, we just need to merge them
by calling the merge function that just passed
the right values for the parameters of merge.
So, let's call merge with our ARR low and
mid for the bounds of the left side, low is
the low left, mid is the high left, and mid
plus one would be the low right, but obviously
high that’s the high right.
So, this call basically merges these two halves
together and after sorting the first half,
sorting the second half, merging them, we
have one long sequence from low to high that
is sorted.
That's basically the merge-sort algorithm.