What we need to do now is basically implement
the merge algorithm.
Let me demonstrate how we should merge two
sorted sequence into one big sorted sequence,
and after we do that let's go to the computer
and just implement it all.
But let me first show you the idea so it would
be easier for us.
So, assuming we have two sorted sequences:
one, three, six, ten, and four, seven, eight,
thirteen, fifteen, twenty, so two sorted sequences.
We want to merge them together into one big
sequence, to a new big sequence.
We can do it in a lot of ways but in order
to take advantage of the fact that these two
sequences are already ordered in an increasing
order, already sorted, we can do something
kind of cool.
If you think about it, obviously the first
element can't be, I don't know six or ten
or thirteen or twenty one, it could either
be the first element in the first one or the
first element in the second one.
So basically we should choose one of these
two to come first in our resulted emerged
sequence.
So we have two candidates for the first element,
in this case when we are comparing one and
four we would obviously want take one to be
the first element and then we can pick another
candidate to be the next element.
It would either be three or four.
Now that we have taken care of the one, we
have to pick between three and four to be
the next element.
In this case it would obviously be three.
Now we have two candidates for the next element,
either six or four, right.
Obviously it can’t be ones that are greater
than six and ones that are greater than four
before we put the six and four in their sorted
merged output.
So then we’ll obviously pick four and then
we'll have to pick between six and seven;
we’ll choose six.
And then we'd have to pick between seven and
ten, and we pick seven.
And then we'll have to pick between eight
and ten, and we’ll pick eight.
And then we need to pick between thirteen
and ten, obviously we'll take ten.
And then basically we're done, adding all
the elements from the first array but then
the second array still have a tail of elements.
So let's just take all this tail and copy
it to the remaining positions in our result
merged array.
And that basically completes the merging of
these two sorted sequences into one big sorted
sequence.
So let's take the merge-sort algorithm, the
merge idea, implement them all on our computer
and make sure it works.
After that, we’ll also trace the execution
of these runs.