Let's trace the execution of the merge-sort
algorithm.
So at first I want to make sure that all of
you get inductive idea here, where we have
three steps first sorting the first and then
sort of the second half and then merging them
together and logically understand why these
three steps, in that order, basically soars
the entire sequence.
But I think it would be even more convincing
if in addition to that we would also trace
one execution from start to end.
My suggestion is don't do it too many times
because understanding the inductive idea for
recursive algorithm, that’s the important
thing.
But let's do it for merge-sort.
So, we have eight elements sequence: fourteen,
five, eight, ten, thirteen, and so on, which
we want to sort.
So we are basically sorting the first half
and the second half and then, since it's a
recursive call each one of them is going to
sort its first half and second half.
So we have calls for two element array and
each one of them also would call two sorting
halves of one element and that would be the
base condition.
But that's not the order that these calls
are called; let's try tracing the merge-sort
algorithm now in order.
Okay.
So we're first calling the original eight
element array.
It, as step one, calls to sort the first half
of the elements; the first four elements,
right.
And then when this function executes, it's
also a recursive call.
That's not the base condition so we also called
to sort the first half of the elements; basically
sorting fourteen and five, and fourteen and
five is also not the base case so it also
calls to sort the first half of the elements,
which is fourteen.
Fourteen: that's a single element array that
is already sorted, so nothing to do here just
return.
And then fourteen five calls to sort the second
half, which is five, so now fourteen and five
after having two halves that are sorted it
should merge them together to a sorted sequence.
Basically reordering them to be five fourteen;
that's the merge.
And then the four elements: fourteen, five,
eight, ten, now need to call to sort the second
half, basically eight and ten.
Eight and ten, that's not the base, so it
calls to sort the first half of eight which
is sorted. and then it calls to store the
second half of ten, which is sorted and then
it merges them together.
In this case no reordering is needed the assorted
sequence is eight and ten.
Now the four element array has two halves
that are sorted by fourteen and a ten.
We need to merge them together in order to
get a four element sorted sequence: five,
eight, ten, fourteen.
So that's basically the end of the first step
in the original call; merge sort of the first
half it would recursively merge-sort that
half.
And eventually would have the elements, five,
eight, ten, fourteen, in the sorted order.
And now would come the second step, basically
sorting the second half of: thirteen, one,
eighteen, and three.
That's not the base case so we would start
by sorting the first half of that, which is
thirteen and one.
That's not the base case so it starts by sorting
the first half of that, thirteen which is
sorted, and then sorting the second half of
that, one which is also sorted.
And then we need to merge them into: one,
thirteen.
And now we need to sort the second half of
the four element, which is eighteen and three.
Not base case, so let's recursively sort the
first half: eighteen which is sorted.
Let’s recursively sort the second half:
three which is sorted.
Let's merge them together to three, eighteen.
Now we have two sorted halves of the four
element array.
We need to merge them together into one sequence
of four elements that are sorted: one, three,
thirteen, eighteen.
That’s the end of the second step of the
original sort of eight elements.
We've sorted the first half recursively; we've
sorted the second half recursively.
And now comes step three, where we have the
two halves sorted that are needed to be merged
together.
And that’s step three of the merge function,
basically merging them into one sorted sequence:
one, three, five, eight, ten and so on.
It's a bit crazy way to trace this execution,
but that's how basically it was.
I think it's easier and more understandable
to think of it inductively.
Basically, thinking step one would do the
job basically sort the first half, step two
would do the job basically sort the second
half, and then we just need to merge them
together to get the entire job done, basically
sort the entire sequence.