Now that we know how merge-sort works; now
that we've implemented merge-sort, we've even
traced the execution of merge-sort.
Let’s try to analyze the running time of
merge-sort and try to compare it to the selection-sort,
or the most basic sorting algorithm, that
by the way executes in a quadratic time.
I hope merge-sort will give us a better result
than quadratic; otherwise it wasn’t worth
all the effort we gave to that.
It's not as easy as it sounds to analyze this
kind of an algorithm because it's not as like
we had an iterative process where we just
summed up the number of operations we're doing
each iteration so it was all like in front
of our eyes and we just needed to figure out
what's the body's cost and just add more and
more values to figure out the total cost of
the iterative process.
In the case of a recursive call, a lot of
operations kind of sneak in between the calls
and we need to better model the number of
operations that are done during the process
of executing a recursive algorithm; very common
model to do that is called a recursive tree
model and it works something like that.
We'll try to basically show all the recursive
calls and their costs, all together, so it
starts like that.
We first have a call of an array of size N.
This call has two or calls two times to a
function of size N by two, each one of them
calls two times to a function of size N by
four, each one of them calls to N by 8 and
so on; they kind of keep on splitting, here
we have a lot of calls to a single element
array of size one.
So this is the entire set of recursive calls
and their sizes, but it's not that each call
here is constant, there are calls that cost
us constant amount of time but there are calls
that are much more expensive.
So let's try at the side of each call, each
circle here, write the cost of that call:
how much operations do we need to pay for
that call.
So the first one in addition to the recursive
calls, we need to merge to N by two element
arrays into one N element array.
The merge function, I don't think we've mentioned
it explicitly but it's a linear function;
its cost is basically the sum of the sizes
of the arrays we're trying to merge.
So if we are merging two N by two arrays,
the cost of merge would be N, right, the number
of elements we are writing basically to the
merge ARR, basically copying to our array.
So the cost here of this call, in addition
to the recursive calls, is another N. And
each one of the N by two calls costs the merge
basically N be two, so the first one costs
N by two and the second course costs N by
two.
And each one of the N by four costs N by four,
right?
Basically the cost is the cost of merge and
that's basically the size of the elements
that we're trying to sort, that’s the number
of elements who are basically also trying
to merge.
And so on and so on til the base case; each
one costs one.
So in order to figure out the total cost of
this execution, we need to sum up all the
reds here, all the extra costs.
And if we know how much all of the merge function
cost together, that would be the total cost
of merge-sort.
It’s kind of difficult to sum up all the
red here but then a nice observation says
that it would be easier for us to sum the
reds in each level first and then if we know
how much a level cost, we would be able to
some all the levels sums up and that would
be the total cost.
It works something like that.
So let's try to relate the level number to
the cost, the total cost of that level.
In order to do that we would need two additional
values that we want to relate here: that the
number of calls in the level, number of circles
basically, and the cost of each call in the
level, a single red cost.
Let's start here; so in level number, the
first level, I prefer to name it level to
start numbering here at zero.
So at level number zero, the number of calls
is one, right.
There is one node at the first level.
The cost of this call is N, right, and then
the total cost of the first level is basically
N times one which is basically N.
So the first level costs N, we can see that
the first level costs N. The second level,
level number one has two calls, right.
There are two nodes here; each one costs N
by two, therefore the total cost of the level
is two times N by two which is also N. Interesting.
Third level, level number two, four calls
each one costs N by four, once again not surprising
four times N by four that would also be N.
Next level would have eight nodes, each one
would cost N by eight, right, and that would
also sum up to N. I have a feeling that all,
each one of the levels here with sum up, would
total up to N; let's try to justify it.
So for example level number K: how many calls
are we expecting there?
You can see the relation here between the
level number and the number of calls; it’s
two raised to the power of the lever number,
right.
Eight is two to the power of three.
Four is two to the power of two.
Two is two to the power of one.
One is two to the power of zero.
Therefore, the number of calls in level number
K would be two to the power of K and the cost
of each call is N over that.
So it would be N over two to the power of
K and then the total cost would be two to
the power of K times N over two to the power
of K; you can see that that is also N.
So I'm kind of convinced now that not only
the first four levels sum up to N, but all
levels with this behaving like that also sums
up to N. The big question is how many levels
we have here because if we know how many levels,
let's say we have thirteen levels then it's
going to be thirteen times N obviously the
number of levels depends on N, it's related
to N, so can be just thirteen.
So the big question mark is: what's the level
number of the last level.
Once we figure that out, we know how many
times we need to multiply by N, right.
Let's do that.
So the most obvious thing we know about the
last level is that the cost of each one is
one, right, because size is one and we know
that the cost here should be one.
If you look back at the calculations we've
done in Binary search, we've already seen
that the value of K where N over two to the
K equals one is when K is Log of N. That means
that the level number that gives us cost of
one should be Log two of N which means that
the number of calls in that level is two to
the power of Log two of N.
If you're familiar with the logarithmic rules,
you know that two raised to the power of Log
two of N basically equals N, so we have N
calls, each one costs one that also adds up
to N.
Not surprisingly we've seen that; so basically
we know that we have N in each level, Log
N times.
So the total, T of N here, is N times Log
N or Log N times N.
So the running time is paid theta of N Log
N, which is better than N squared, N times
N.
We know that N times Log of N is significantly
better than N times N, so N Log N merge-sort
is a much preferred algorithm, sorting algorithm
than for example selection-sort.