You can see that since our computer uses zeros
and ones, different number systems use different
symbols for the digits.
If we want to use only zeros and ones, base
two would do exactly that.
For base two, the only digits we would need
to use is two and one, because two objects
are grouped together.
Let’s start counting in base two, in the
binary base system, and so it's zero, one
after that would come ten.
We're grouping the two ones into a single
binary ten and no additional ones, after that
we would have eleven.
What comes after eleven?
100 right, because we're grouping two ones
into a ten then we would have two ten's that
would be grouped into one hundred.
After that we would have 101, 110, 111 and
then 1,000.
See how fast we got to 1,000.
Actually it makes sense because we group much
more often; every two elements are grouped
together.
Not like in the decimal number system that
ten objects would be needed to grouped together
to a ten and then only 10 tens would be grouped
to a hundred in only 10 hundreds would be
grouped to a thousand.
Here, much more often we are groupings, our
numbers grow along much faster.
So, we can keep on counting in binary.