The same thing would work when we are counting
in other number systems as well.
I'll talk about some of the more important
ones.
One of them is the octal number system, short
for base eight.
The digits here would be zero to seven; we're
going to group eight objects together, so
we need symbols zero up to seven.
It would start zero, one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven.
After this seven, we would have one group
of octal ten and zero ones, eleven, twelve,
thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, sixteen, seventeen.
After seventeen, the next one would be grouped
into another ten.
So we would have two tens, zero ones and so
on.
Again, try to think what comes before a hundred.
Hope you got it right, it's 77 right?
After 77, the next object would be grouped
into another ten, the next eight tens would
be grouped into one single object of 100 or
100 things.