Okay, so now that we know the technique of
how to convert the hexadecimal to binary and
backwards binary to hexadecimal.
Let's try to say a few words justifying why
this magic here works, that we can translate
each digit individually, independently without
caring with its surrounding.
I'll try to give you the intuition of the
argument, basically demonstrating it on a
specific binary number and how to convert
it into hexadecimal.
Hopefully you would be able to take this calculation
here and generalize it into formal proof,
general proof for all cases.
So, let's look at this binary number and I'll
try to make some mathematical equations, or
quantities, that eventually would end up with
the hexadecimal equivalent.
But, as we go, you’ll see how we are relating
back to the table and converting each 4 bits
independently to its hexadecimal digit.
So, let's get started: so we have this number
here, it's a binary number, therefore we can
write it equivalently as a weighted sum of
powers of 2.
So, it is 1 times 2 to the 0, plus 1 times
2 to the 1, plus 0 times 2 to the second,
and so on.
We can go up to, I think it goes out to 0
times 0 to the power of, raised to the power
of 11, and now let's look at this sum here,
with 12 errands.
And probably, not really surprisingly, we’ll
divide it into groups of 4 errands.
So, let's start with the first 4.
In this case, let's take the first 4 errands
and just actually copy them.
So, we have 1 times 2 to the 0, plus 1 times
2 to the 1, plus 0 times 2 to the square,
plus 0 times 2 to the power of 3.
So, obviously our first 4 errands in the upper
side are equal to the first 4 in the lower
one.
It won't make any difference if I also multiplied
by one, right?
Or in other words, instead of one I can just
write 2 to the power of 0, exactly the same,
right?
So that's what we do with the first 4 errands,
we kept them equal just wrote it a bit differently.
Let's take the next 4 errands, in this case,
instead of just copying them as is, we'll
factor them by 2 to the 4.
So, instead of 1 times 2 to the 4, we do 1
times 2 to the 0.
And later we'll just multiply it by 2 to the
4 and 0 times 2 to the 5 would be 0 times
2 to the 1 and 1 times 2 to the second, and
1 times 2 to the third.
So, taking these 4 errands in the parenthesis
and multiplying them by 2 to the 4, would
give you the second 4 errands up there.
For the last 4 errands, we’ll do something
very similar.
We’ll write them but will factor them in
this case by 2 to the 8.
Right.
So, the first one would be 0 times 2 to the
0, plus 1 times 2 to the 1, and so on.
You can see that each parenthesis here has
some combination of the first 4 powers of
2.
Let's take a look at these ones for starters.
Let's go back to the table and if we take
a look here, at this line here, this number
0011 actually equals to 1 times 2 to the 0,
plus 1 times 2 to the 1, plus 0 times 2 to
the second, plus 0 times 2 to the 3, which
is equivalent to 3.
So, this thing here is equal to 3, same thing.
So, we can write it 3 times, to do the same
thing with these 4 errands in the second parenthesis.
Again, it's a combination of the first 4 powers
of 2.
Going back to the table, it would match exactly
this line there with 1101.
Because 1101 basically stands for 1 times
2 to the 0, plus 0 times 2 to the 1, plus
1 times 2 to the second, plus 1 times 2 to
3, which is equivalent to 13, hexadecimal
D. but it's equivalent to 13.
So, this thing here is 13 times 2 to the power
of 4.
Same thing with these 4 errands, we’ll look
at the table.
It matches this line and it adds up to 6.
So, we can write 6 times 2 to the 8.
So, again, as we said it's not a coincidence
that our table there gave us all the combinations
of 4 bits.
Because when we do the math, we would get
some combination of the first 4 powers of
2: 2 to the 0 through 2 to the 3.
Now, let's take a look at the powers of 2
that we have there.
2 to the 0, 2 to the 4, and 2 to the 8, so
2 to the 0 is basically 1, which is also 16
to the power of 0.
You see like I'm getting us towards a hexadecimal
representation, something times powers of
16, so this would be 3 times 6 into the power
of 0.
Fortunately for us, actually it's not very
fortunate, it just works, 2 to the 4 is 16,
which is 16 to the power of 1.
So, this digit here is also 13 times a power
of 16, and 2 to the 8 is 2 to the 4 squared,
or in other words, 16 squared.
So, we get 6 times 16 squared.
So, we can view that as a hexadecimal representation
because it's 3 for the ones digit, 13 or D
for the tens digit, and 6 for the hexadecimal
hundreds digit.
So, that very long binary number is equivalent
to 6d3 hexidecimal.