Okay, so now that we know how to work with
other number systems, we know how to a convert
from one system to another.
Let's see how we can do some math; how we
can do some arithmetic in different number
systems.
Let's start with addition: how we can add
numbers to one another.
So again, let's start with a decimal number
system.
And make sure we get exactly what we do there,
and then, try to generalize it to other number
systems as well.
So, for example, let's try to add 325 to 692,
two decimal numbers.
We start, I think third grade, our teacher
said start with the ones digit.
So, we add 5 and 2, we get 7.
And then, for the tens digit we had 2 tens
and 9 tens, that would give us 11 tens, which
would, 11 tens would be grouped into 100 and
an additional ten.
That's why we write 1 in the tens, and carry
over an additional hundred.
Then we have 100 plus 300 plus 600, it adds
up to 10 hundreds.
And we have, therefore, 0 for the ten hundreds
and 1 for the thousand because these 10 hundreds
were grouped into one group of a thousand.
So, we have 0 hundreds and 1 carried to the
thousands, which would then be dropped down,
and all together we have 1017.
Let's try to do the same when we add, or we
try to do some additions, in the Octal number
system.
For example, a 365 plus 243 Octal.
Again, we start with the ones digit, 5 plus
3.
When we add 5 plus 3, we get 8.
But we don't just write 8, because in the
octal number system, 8 ones are grouped into
a single ten.
So, after grouping these eight ones to a ten,
we have 0 additional ones and a carry over
of a ten.
Then, we add a 10, another 6 ten and another
4 ten, that would give us 11 tens, right?
Maybe let's try to count it; count it up starting
at 6.
So, we kind of have to add: 6 plus 5.
So, let's add 5 to 6.
Let’s count.
After six comes seven, after seven we have
ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, so we have
thirteen in the tens position.
So, we group ten of them to hundreds, we are
left with 3 tens and one hundred is carry
over.
Then, we have 3 plus 1 that's a 4, plus 2
that's a five, a six, that would give us 6.
So all together, 365 octal plus 243 octal,
gives us 630 octal, right?
Same thing as we've done with the decimal,
we are working in the octal.
We just keep in mind to group items when we
have eight individual ones.
Same thing would work when we try to add binary
numbers: 0 plus 1 would be a 1, 0 plus 0 would
give us 0, 1 plus 0 would be 1, 1 plus 1 that
is 2 obviously.
That would be 0 plus 1 of a carry over, 1
plus 1 plus 1, that's a 3, that would leave
1 plus 1 of a carry over.
1 plus 0 plus 0 would be a1, 0 plus 1 is 1,
and 1 plus 1 is basically 2, or 10.
Or a 0 plus a 1 carry over, which then drops
down.
And that is the result of adding these two
binary numbers.
Try a few on your own, and make sure you get
how to add the numbers in terms of alternative
number system.