Okay, let's see how the ‘Two’s Complement’
representation method works to represent positive
and negative numbers.
So, when you want to represent the number,
assigned number, in the Two’s Complement
representation method it kind of matters how
long, how big you want, how many bits you
want in this representation.
So, let's let me give you a general definition
here: so, for presenting a number in k-bits,
it has two major properties that you should
know about.
The first is that if your number that you
want to represent is positive, then the first
k1, (k. minus 1) bits are represented as the
unsigned binary representation, basically
the regular base 2, and then the last bit
would just be a 0.
So, in order to represent a positive number
just take its base 2 representation in (k.
minus 1) bits, and the k-th bit would be a
0, on its left.
And another important property for the Two’s
Complement representation method is that if
you add a number and its additive inverse,
its value with the sign flipped, then the
sum would be 2 to the power of k.
I suggest you write these two properties down
when you look at the next example.
So for example, if we want to translate the
decimal value 26 into Two’s Complement using
8-bits, okay so our k now is 8.
So it's 8-bit Two’s Complement representation.
Then, since it's a positive number we should
look at 26 as in a binary representation,
basically in seven bits so the first seven
bits would be the binary representation of
26, like that.
And then the left-most bit would be 0.
Very, actually, very straight forward.
Let's try to figure out how negative 26 would
look like, in once again, an 8-bit Two’s
Complement representation.
So, we said that adding a number and its additive
inverse should give us 2 to the k.
In this case, adding 26 to negative 26 should
give us to 2 in this case, k is 8, 2 to the
8.
So 26, we know how it looks like, right?
2 to the 8, if you think about it, it is 1
and eight 0s; just as 10 to the 8 decimal
is one and eight zeros, in binary 2 to the
8 would be one and eight zeros.
You can figure out the weight of each digit
and the ninth digit, basically, is 2 to the
8.
But now let's try to figure out what negative
26, would, should look like.
So we know that if we add 26 to negative 26,
they should add up to this 1 and eight 0s.
So let's try to figure out negative 26, digit
by digit.
So zero plus what, would give us the zero?
Zero, obviously.
One plus what, would give us a zero?
It could either be zero or one, obviously,
it's not a zero.
So it must be a one, but not only that it
gives us a 0, it also carries another 2 to
the next position.
So 1 plus 0 plus what, would give us a zero?
That's 1 plus 1 would give us a 0 and another
carry over of 1.
1 plus 1 plus what, would give us a zero?
1 plus 1 plus 0 would give us a 0, with the
carry over; 1 plus 1 plus 0 with the carry
over.
1 plus 0 plus what, would give us a zero?
1 plus 0 plus 1 would give us a 0, right?
It's basically a ten so it's a 0 and the carryover
of another 1; 1 plus 0 plus 1 and 1 plus 0
plus 1.
So, taking this number here of 11100110, this
thing here, that's the 8-bits Two’s Complement
representation of negative 26.