Okay, so we know how to take a number in an
arbitrary number system in base.
B. and figure out it's decimal value.
Now, let's try to do the other way around:
take a decimal number and try to find its
representation in base B, an arbitrary number
system.
Actually, I want to demonstrate it only on
base 2, on the binary number system, basically
to convert the decimal number into a binary
number.
We can then generalize this method, translating
decimal into other number systems as well.
Let's take, for example 75, the decimal 75,
and try to find its representation, its binary
equivalent representation.
So let's think how we can get started here,
so obviously the binary number is going to
be a sequence of digits, each one is going
to be a zero or one.
We just have to figure out which digits is
a zero and which one is the one, since it's
going to be a binary number, each digit has
its own weight.
So, we have the 1s, 2 to the zero, 2 to the
1s (the 10s), 2 to the 2s (the hundreds),
2 to the 3, to the 4, and so on.
Just to be more explicit, let's write these
powers of two with their decimal value: so,
2 to the 0 is 1, 2 to the 1 is 2, 2 to the
2 is 4, and so on, 8, 16,32, 64, 128, and
so on.
So, each digit here has this weight and we
need to figure out for each position, whether
it's going to be a zero or a one.
Let's start with this position here, with
the digit in with the weight 256.
Should that be a zero or a one?
I believe most of you said that it must be
a 0.
Let's try to argue why this is indeed right,
or the only possible value for this digit.
Actually, it makes a lot of sense because
if we would put a 1 here, only this digit
would give us the weight of 256 which is greater
than the total weight we're trying to represent,
the total value of 75.
So, there can't be a one in this position.
This position, therefore, must be a 0.
Actually, not only this position of 256, but
all digits that their weight is greater than
75: the 128, 256, 512, and so on.
All of these digits must be a zero, right?
The real question is what would be the value
with the rest of the digits.
So, all of them together should represent
or should add up to the value of seventy five.
And, let's try to go over them one by one
and figure out whether they should be a 1
or a 0.
We’ll go over them from left to right, starting
with this digit here, with a 64.
What do you think, should this digit here
be a 0 or a 1?
I believe most of you said that it should
be a 1, and by the way I agree it would be
a 1, but I want to argue why it must be a
1, why it can't be 0?
Because my concern is that maybe this digit
would be a 0 and the rest of the digits, some
way, would add up to 75, even though this
digit here is a 0.
So, this is not possible but maybe it is.
How can we argue that this scenario here is
not valid?
So, a good argument would say that the rest
of the digits, or using the rest of the digits,
the largest value that they can represent
all together is having them all be ones, right?
Taking all of their weights, that would be
the greatest value we can have using only
these digits.
And then, when we add 1 plus 2 plus 4 plus
8 to 16 plus 32, it add up to 63, which is
by the way even less than 64.
It's obviously less than 75.
So, having the 0 at 64 won't allow us to add
up to 75 as total, which means that this digit
would have to be a 1.
But, before we say that, I just want to you
to note a very important thing regarding the
sum of geometrical progression.
So, if you add up the geometric progression
of 2, for example 1 plus 2 plus 4 plus 8,
up to for example, 2 to the power of K., you
know what this sum adds up to?
So, this sum adds up to 2 to the power of
K. plus 1 minus 1.
Basically, 1 less than the next power of 2
in that sum.
So, in this case, 1 plus 2 plus 4 plus 8 up
to 32, is one less than the next power of
2, one less than 64, which is exactly 63.
So, there is a very important property, we're
going to use it a lot in computer science,
so just make sure you know the sum and memorize
it.
So, in this case we agree that this digit
here with the weight of 64, must be a 1.
After having a 1 here, out of this 75, we
already used 64, we already represented 64,
which leaves us with 11.
So, the rest of the digits must add up to
11.
If we need to add up to 11, 32 must obviously
be a 0 and so is 16.
The weight of 16 is greater than 11 itself,
right?
The question again comes when we are in a
weight that is less than 11.
8, in this case, should this be a 0 or 1?
I believe most of you said 1, but let's give
this argument again.
If for some odd reason, we have a 0 here,
the greatest value we can have with the rest
of the digits would be 7, right?
1 less than this 8, which is obviously less
than 11.
So this bit here, must be a 1.
Having the 1 in this position out of the 11,
we already represented 8, which leaves us
with 3 for the rest of the bits.
So, the four must be a 0, and the 2 must be
a 1, which leaves us 3 minus 2 with the 1
for the rest of the bits.
And that is exactly the value that we're going
to put for the 1 digit.
So, you see that this method here figures
out the 75.
Now that we can copy these bits up there and
see that it is 1001011, whatever, and more
importantly, this method exposed the bits
from left to right.
There is an alternative method that would
expose the bits from right to left, and won't
talk about it now but you can look it up on
Wikipedia.