Well let's look at the benefits of paging.
There’s no external fragmentation; every
frame of main memory is equally good, and
we can put any page in any frame and there's
no detriment.
So, there's no reason to keep pages together,
which means any pages, any frame is available
for use as long as of course it's not occupied.
So, there's no external fragmentation.
Some argument is that there's a minimum of
internal fragmentation.
Okay, yes there is internal fragmentation,
but how much?
We're talking the maximum amount of internal
fragmentation we could have is four kilobytes
minus one byte.
So, if the process is going to use one extra
byte beyond the end of a four kilobyte page,
then it's wasting four thousand and ninety
five bytes of main memory.
A process wasting four kilobytes of main memory
is not terribly significant, even if we had
one hundred processes running on the system
that means a maximum of four hundred kilobytes
of main memory wasted and that's insignificant
in today's environment.
So, we don't care about it; so we say yes
it's going to have some internal fragmentation
possibilities, but it's so small we just don't
care.
Protection is really easy because if the process
is making a reference beyond the end of its
page map table, the hardware memory management
unit won’t be able to convert that into
a physical memory address.
We know there's a problem and we can interrupt
and call the operating system immediately
to say that something's gone wrong.
So, protection becomes really easy the process
literally cannot access anything outside its
own memory space.
relocation becomes easy and, in fact, relocation
now is talking about relocating a page.
We don't necessarily have to relocate the
entire process; we could if we want but if
all we need to do is relocate one page, we
can just update the page map table to indicate
where the new the pages now located what the
new frame number is and we're done.
It really doesn't take a lot of effort, of
course we have to copy those four killer bytes,
but copying four kilobytes is not terribly
significant anyhow.
Besides why would we do relocation?
There's very little reason in an simple paging
system, there’s very little reason to move
a page from one to the other.
And then easy sharing which we're going to
see a little bit later on.
If we just have two processes that want to
share a page and it's allowed to do so, doesn't
violate protection, if they're allowed to
share a page then we can simply enter the
same frame number into their page map tables
at the same location and we don't have any
problems with that.
So, there's a huge number of benefits to paging
and that's why we'll never go back to the
old fixed and dynamic partitioning systems.