Of course the benefits of a virtual memory
are huge; the programmer can look at this
as a much larger memory space.
So, now each program, or each process even,
can view main memory as completely available
purely to itself.
In a thirty-two bit address space, each process
is going to think that it has four gigabytes
of main memory available; it doesn’t.
There may not even be four gigabytes of main
memory available in the system.
But that process is going to think that it
has four gigabytes because it's using virtual
memory.
In a sixty-four bit operating system, we’re
going…
The programmers are going to perceive a eighteen
exabyte memory space which is just enormous,
but that's what we can view this as.
Even if the system doesn't have that much
memory the program can be written as if it
were available.
The system the operating system can remove
unused pages, so pages like that splash screen
I talked about a few slides ago, those can
be eliminated out of main memory; they're
not going to ever be used again.
So, let's take them out of main memory, store
them in a second or storage device, just in
case because we have no guarantee that they're
not going to be used again, store them in
the swap space and when they're never used
again, we just don't put them back in main
memory; so freeze up that main memory.
More processes can run in the system and that
means we have better performance, that means
more processes generally means that there's
a higher probability that a process will find
itself in the ready state, so that will find
a process that's in the ready state.
So, ultimately we can result in better system
performance just by having more main memory
available.
Huge benefits available for virtual armoring,
which is why it's the standard today.