So this is a very simple view of what the
clock page replacement algorithm here is.
We have just end pages, end frames available,
and what we're going to do is keep a pointer
that goes around and that's why we call it
the clock page replacement algorithm.
Now when we load up a page, we're going to
set it’s use bit equal to one and that's
fine.
So, we're going to have N frames and let's
just say it's ten frames, just for easy math.
We have ten frames and as the frames, as the
pages are loaded up into those frames, we
said all their use bits equal to zero and
the pointer is pointing at let's say a page,
frame number two, as you see it in the the
left side image.
When it's pointing at page number two, you
can see that the use bit for frame number
two page forty-five is set to one, the use
bit for frame number three page one-ninety-one
is set equal to one but the use bit for frame
number four page five-hundred fifty-six to
set equal to zero.
So, what happens now when we have a page fault,
we’re going to have to remove a page and
we're going to have to load up the new page.
So, to do that what we do is real look for
advancing the pointer; we’re looking for
use bits of zero.
But if we find a use bit of one, we’re going
to reset its value back to zero.
We're not going to steal it quite yet.
We just set the use bit back zero.
So, frame two and frame three as you can see
they their page numbers didn't change but
their use bits didn't change to zero.
Now we need to load page seven-hundred twenty-seven
but page five-hundred fifty-six, which is
loaded in frame four is unused.
So, when the pointer gets around to that point,
we're going to remove that page stored in
a second or a storage device if the modify
bit or whatever, and load up page seven twenty-seven
and set its use bit equal to one.
The reason that this is effective is because
if page forty-five is no longer in use, then
next time the clock pointer comes around to
frame two, the use bit will still be set to
zero because it's not in use and page forty-five
will be stolen now.
So, the clock page replacement algorithm does
have a very high efficacy rate; it's very
effective in not throwing out pages which
are actively in use, and it does have a pretty
good rate of throwing out pages which aren't
in use.
So, we can save a lot of memory using this
and it's really very simple to implement doesn't
require a lot of effort to implement.