Resident set management actually asks two
different questions or two different problems.
One of the problems is now how much memory
do we give to each process? How much main
memory does each process deserve? So, notepad
for example, might only ask for one megabyte
of main memory and Chrome might be asking
for one gigabyte of main memory; should they
get the same amount? And the answer probably
is no, but how do we make the decision of
how much to give each process. Now if we use
smaller allocations, if we minimize the allocations
then that means we have more processes but
that also means we have more page faults because
each one has, each process, has a smaller
allocation. If we choose larger allocations,
well that means we might have less page faults
but less processes as well. So, it's sort
of a give and take that we're going to see
in the next slide, where allocations that
are larger tend to mean less page faults and
allocations that are smaller tend to mean
more page faults. But how do we make the decision
of what, how much notepad gets and how much
chrome gets? So, that's one of the issues.
And then the next issue is when a process
page faults, we're going to have to steal
a page where, we’re going to have to make
room for the page. And are we going to choose
this process, that it's page faulting to steal
out of in order to make room for the new page
or are we going to say that the entire system
is open for stealing, and we can choose from
any process? And obviously it means that that
has a a role in whether or not the allocation
is a variable allocation, meaning can change
over time, or is a fixed allocation. Meaning
that it's always going to be exactly the same.
So, resident set management tries to deal
with these two problems.