So, I'm looking at this chart and what the
chart is showing you is the page fault rate
as compared to the number of frames allocated
to the process.
Now if we take a look, obviously if we only
have one frame for the process it’s going
to create an almost infinite number of page
faults; every memory access, almost, will
need a page fault.
And on the other side if we have an infinite
number of frames, enough that it fits the
entire process into main memory, then we have
no page fault.
But where it's interesting is that there's
a non-linear progression between those two
points.
If we look at the process that has all the
memory that it could possibly want and we
remove just one frame, we only cause a very
small number of page faults. and on the flip
side if we look at a process which only has
one Frame and we double the number of frames,
that’s going to result in a massive decrease
in the number of page faults.
So, there's a non linear progression between
the two.
And one of the things that we can extrapolate
is that there is a sort of optimal location,
where the process is not faulting too much
but also is not is faulting a little bit.
In other words, we’re saying that page faults
are not necessarily a bad thing; that since
main memory is a quantity which is not infinite
that we would like to have some number of
page faults to indicate that the process hasn't
been given too many frames, in other words
that were starving other processes.
And we can use a couple of algorithms to try
and cause the process to try, and manage the
resident set, to cause the process to fall
in between the upper and lower bounds.
If it's above the upper bounds, we can increase
the number of frames that are available to
that process thereby, effectively decreasing
its page fault rate.
And if it’s below the lower bounds, then
we can decrease the number of frames in the
process give them to somebody else to hopefully
lower its fault rate.
And we can leave it in between this upper
and lower bounds so that it has enough frames
to do the work that it needs to do, but not
so many friends that it's starving other processes.