One of the algorithms for resident set management
that we're going to talk about is the page
fault frequency algorithm or the PFF algorithm.
The PFF algorithm tries to look at the frequency
of the page faults by looking at the time
between the current page fault and the last
page fault.
And we have some value that we'd like to hit,
we have some value we call F. And the F says
if we're page faulting more frequently than
F, in other words, if the time between page
faults is less than F, then the solution is
to add a frame.
And what that's going to do is if we're page
faulting too often it should decrease the
page fault rate because now we've given it
more memory.
But if the page fault rate is greater than
F, then we can use those use bits look at
all the used bits of zero discard those pages
they're not use anymore, reset all the used
bits of the remaining pages to zero and load
up the the frame, the page, that we need into
an available frame.
So one of the points of the PFF algorithm
is that we can manage the resident set, how
many pages are loaded into main memory, by
I looking at how often the algorithm is or
how often the process is page faulting.
One of course the difficult values is how
to figure out a value for F. One of the difficult
things is how to figure out a value for F.
How do we set a value for F?
How do we know what a reasonable F is?
And in fact there isn't a reasonable value
for F. As you saw in the previous slide it
would be better to have an upper bounds and
a lower bounds, so that we're not looking
for a moving target, we're not looking for
F and deciding whether it's too frequent or
too infrequent.
We can use an upper bounds and lower bounds
to say we might add a frame, or we might steal
from the current process, or we might steal
from the global set.
So, there's a number of different variations
on the PFF algorithm that we can use to to
make it more effective.
One problems of PFF though is that when the
process moves from one locality to a completely
different locality; so, it's starting in one
area of its code and it jumps very far to
do some other work.
And it's going to be in the new locality for
a long period of time, during a locality shift
those pages in the new locality probably are
not loaded.
So, we'll have to load all those pages from
the new locality and then when we're in the
new locality, the page fault rate will decrease
significantly because we have all the pages
that we want.
And so now we would, the next time try to
unload those old pages from the old locality
but unfortunately if we never fault again,
for example, unlikely.
But if we never fault again we're never going
to clear out those old pages.
So, the page fault frequency during a locality
shift can result in both the old locality
and the new locality using memory and that
means double the memory and that's a huge
waste.
So, there are some downsides to using the
PFF algorithm.