Another issue that we can use page faults
to look at is what we call load control, or
we can use the number of page faults that
are happening in a system to make a decision
of whether or not to swap a process altogether
out.
Now the benefit, of course, of swapping a
process is that we get all of its memory,
not just a portion of its memory.
But that whole amount of main memory is going
to be removed and reallocated to the other
running processes and of course that process
can be brought back at a later time.
We can do that we've always been able to do
that but now we can do it on a much grander
scale.
So, now we can use the number of page faults
to tell us when it's time to choose a process
to swap.
But the question then becomes which process
do we swap?
And we have a couple of options, of course,
if we have priorities in our processes, we
could use the lowest priority process.
We could also choose the faulting process
as it's the greatest probability that it doesn't
have its working set in the resident.
So, the faulting process of course, if we
swap that out, that means we don't have to
recover a page; we don't have to deal with
the page fault, we effectively deal with the
page fault by swapping the entire process.
The last process activated is certainly the
least likely to have its working set resident.
We could also choose the process with the
smallest local resident set because it's the
one that's going to be easiest to offload
and easiest to onload later on, when we decide
to run this process and finish it up.
We could also choose the largest process,
the exact the opposite, because we get the
most amount of main memory and it's most likely
that we're going to be able finish those other
processes If we get back a large chunk of
main memory.
If we know how long we expect this process
to run for, we can look at the process with
the largest remaining execution window.
And because the if we aren't going to finish
this process for another five hours, who cares
if it's another five hours and five minutes
more.
So, load control can be done by looking just
at the number of page faults and it is a reasonable
solution for the medium term scheduling algorithm.