The operating system has to meet a number
of requirements, in terms of taking care of
main memory.
The first one is relocation.
In years past, the operating system, or rather
the program, would be the only thing running
on the system.
If we look back at the old era of the IBM
mainframes, or even older than that when we
look at really big computers, there was only
ever one program running on the system at
any given time, and since there was only one
program that program had access to the entirety
of main memory; it could do whatever it wanted
with it.
So, in reality the programmer had access to
all of main memory inside his program and
the programmer could put portions of the program,
portions of data, portions of code, anywhere
he wanted inside main memory.
Unfortunately, that's not true anymore.
We're looking at a system where we have a
lot of programs running, and we don't know
what the order of the programs is that are
going to start; we don't know what's free
when a program starts, we don't know what's
occupied when a program starts.
And the operating system is going to have
to be responsible for putting a running program
into a particular space in main memory and
during its lifetime even while the program
is running, not actively running on the CPU,
but maybe in the ready state or in the block
state or even in one of the suspended states.
The operating system should be able to relocate
that process to a completely different section
of main memory, I mean actually take it and
move it to a different place in main memory.
And so, that's relocation and the operating
system has to be able to do that, so that's
one of our requirements.
Another requirement is protection.
The operating system will be the only entity
in the computer system, which is allowed to
access all of main memory.
A program cannot be allowed to access another
program's memory space, and that's a prime
tenet of memory management.
So, that we need to make sure that one program
cannot interfere with another running program
in the system.
In fact, one program shouldn't even know that
another program is necessarily running without
the intervention of the operating system.
Now obviously, two programs may need to communicate
and we have facilities for doing that; we
have the inter-process communication facility.
But overall, we should say that protection
should be enforced, such that one program
cannot access another program's memory space.
And we saw this in when we've talking about
pointers in earlier modules, because if we
let the pointer go outside the memory space
of the program then the program would be shut
down and that was protection.
If you remember or if you ever saw that message
that came up in Windows it says, “Microsoft
is sorry but your program has performed an
illegal operation,” that's a protection
mechanism.
Your program, probably via a pointer, was
trying to access memory outside of its memory
space, and so Windows intervened and said
that's not allowed and it shut your program
down immediately.
One of the problems with this is that the
operating system can't prescreen.
We can't go through and look at all the memory
accesses that your program is going to do
before you actually do them, because that
would take just too much time.
It has to be done dynamically.
So as you make a memory request, the CPU,
the hardware actually has to look at the memory
request and decide whether it's in your memory
space, your program's memory space, or outside
your program's memory space and should be
terminated.
So that's protection.
We also have some situations where sharing
might make sense, and we'll talk about these
later on.
Where the process is actually going to share
code with another process.
In fact we're going to talk about one situation
where we execute a process, and then we fork
and create an exact duplicate of this process
as a new process.
So, we'll talk about that in a little bit.
We can talk about logical organization where
we create modules.
So, a lot of programs are written these days
using shared objects or dynamically linked
libraries and what this is is rather than
creating every possible function.
So, for example when you were writing your
“hello world” program, your simple “hello
world “programs, you didn't overload the
output operator for the IO stream class.
You had a library that did that for you and
all you had to do was pound include IO stream.
Well what that did was tell the operating
system that, through a lot of steps I'm oversimplifying
it, but that tells the operating system that
you're going to use a library and one of the
libraries is the Microsoft Visual C++ library
MSVCRTDLL.
Inside that library is the code for the function
on how to output to C-out to the O-stream
class.
So you don't write that code, it's already
in Windows and every program that uses C++
has use for that code.
Well we don’t want to load that code with
every program.
We want to load that code once and have it
shared between every program that was written
in C++.
So that might be seventy programs and we only
have one copy of that MSVCRTDLL, it's not
a large DLL maybe it takes up only one megabyte
or two megabytes.
But if we're talking about seventy different
programs using it.
That means we're saving between seventy and
one hundred forty megabytes of memory and
that all of a sudden becomes significant.
And then we'll talk about the memory management
requirement of physical organization, which
is really just how we map a logical memory
addresses to physical memory addresses.
So, these are the requirements that we have
to meet.
So, we've got relocation, protection, sharing,
logical organization, and physical organization.
And those are the requirements that the operating
system has to meet in order to complete its
memory management tasks.