When the system boots up, we’re looking
at what is effectively a desert.
There is nothing in main memory, short of
a couple of locations where we can communicate
with hardware, but the majority of main memory
is simply completely empty.
And as the operating system, it becomes our
responsibility to divide main memory into
sections where we're going to allow programs
to use.
And we're going to have to talk about a number
of different partitioning strategies for how
to get that done.
So, the core of the idea is that we're going
to look at a way to break down main memory
into different sections so that the programs
can all be in their own individual sections,
so that's again part of our part of our relocation
of protection requirements, more protection
than anything else that we can set guidelines
we can set borders for a process.
But we have to recognize that when the system
starts memory is just empty and it's just
available for us to use.
So, some of the strategies we're going to
look at our fix partitioning and dynamic partitioning.
We’re going to take a look at a buddy system
which is sort of fixed and dynamic both.
Then, we're going to look at paging and segmentation
and paging segmentation is really what's done
today.
But we have to understand fixed in the name
of partitioning before we can get into the
more advanced stuff.