Alright, fixed partitioning didn't work out
great.
What if we took an opposite end of the spectrum
and said, okay let's make dynamic partitions.
Let's ask the process exactly how much memory
it needs and let's give it exactly that much
memory.
So, if a process says it needs ten megabytes;
we’ll give it ten megabytes.
Now that causes a problem with the process
decides to grow to later on we don't have
an issue, we don't have a way of dealing with
that.
But if a process is in a particular memory
space, it can grow as much as it wants inside
that memory space.
So, once we allocate a memory space for that
process, it really can't grow but it can use
up everything that that's inside that partition.
But what this causes is actually external
fragmentation, extremal fragmentation is caused
by the dynamic partitioning and what this
is is wasted memory between allocations.
Now what's happening here as you can see in
the diagram, is that we created three different
processes.
We created three processes and the middle
process sort of disappears, it ends.
Now we've got that little chunk of memory
free, but what we would like to do is run
a program that's just slightly larger than
the space that was allocated there.
And unfortunately because it was larger, I
can't allocate that space; because the new
process is larger than the space that was
allocated, I can't put that new process into
that memory space.
So, what I have to do is put it at the end
and that means we're we're using up more and
more and more at the end.
And then of course what happens if all we
have are these little slivers of memory left
over and I want to run a big process, which
is not so large that it would that we don't
have enough memory free memory for it, we
have enough free memory for it but we have
as these little segments of free memory.
And we have to compact all the running processes
now into the beginning of main memory to make
a big space at the end, so that we can run
the new process and that of course requires
a lot of copying of memory, a lot of CPU time
and that's a big waste of time.
We have an issue with dynamic partitioning
in that the data structures for the operating
system get rather complex because we have
to record both the start and the ending location
of the process.
And then the last problem is where do we choose
to put a process if we have enough space available,
assuming that we have enough space available,
where to be choose to put a new process into
its into what partition.
So, we could have the best fit which is the
area size closest, and of course larger, than
what the process is asking for.
If the process is asking for ten megabytes
and we have an eleven megabyte sliver of available
then, we can put this ten megabyte process
into the eleven megabyte sliver of available
space.
Well of course unfortunately that means that
the last one megabyte is not inside of partition,
it's still available space we didn't know
allocate it but it's never going to be used
because its so small; we’re never going
to a process that so small it'll fit into
a one megabyte little sliver of space, and
that's called external fragmentation because
it's outside of the area of an allocation.
We could use first fit, which just says the
first spot that we becomes available when
we start looking, so once we start looking
from the beginning of main memory.
If a spot is available that's larger than
what the process is asking for we'll just
put it in there.
And the next bits as we begin looking from
where we last left off.
Of all the options it actually turns out that
next fit has the minimum CPU time with the
best average utilization of memory, but the
point is moot because we don't do this anymore.
Dynamic partitioning has so much overhead,
that we just can't do it in today's environment.