Ok so we have a program that can be executed
by the computer.
It looks as a sequence of zeroes and ones
that represent instructions for the CPU to
execute.
These instructions are very low level they
can add things multiply move data from one
place to another jump to another position.
Very simple set of instructions.
We are not going to program with zeroes and
ones.
This kind of programming language is called
machine language that is obviously understood
by the machine by the CPU by a computer.
We are going to program and write and implement
our algorithms using a high level language.
There are a lot of high level languages we
are going to write in C++ but there are also
Java Python C# and C and Pascal and Scheme
and a lot of high level languages.
A program let’s say in C++ would not look
as a sequence of zeroes and ones it would
look more like that.
Which is a text in English contains the English
alphabet you can see we don’t understand
exactly what it does but you can see it has
a text Hello World it has some English words
you can probably recognize like main and include
and return and stuff like that.
So we write in something that is much closer
to our natural language not zeroes and ones.
But then the computer doesn’t understand
this type of language.
So we need to translate this code here into
a machine language code.
This kind of translation or this process of
translating a high level language into language
the machine the computer can understand is
called compilation or a build process and
we lucky for us it is an automated process
since even high level languages are very strict
and we have to follow the rules accurately.
And automated process can just take the code
in the programming language and translate
it into machine language.
So we just have to start this process and
then our computer will be able to execute
the program we write in the high level language.
I will show you how we do that as we write
our first program.