Hi there.
Today we are going to implement our first
C++ program.
Typically a first program in a programming
language is a Hello World application that
reaches out to the user saying ‘Hey I am
here’ or printing Hello World.
We are going to write a slightly different
first program but before we do that let’s
take a closer look at the process at how an
application is executed inside a computer.
Let’s focus on three main components inside
the computer we’ve talked about a few.
Let’s focus on these three the memory the
main memory the ram and the secondary memory
whether it is a hard disk or a solid disk
drive.
And obviously the CPU which is the central
processing unit that does all of the job inside
a computer.
So both memories ether it is a second memory
or the RAM are basically contains a lot of
zeroes and ones.
Everything inside a computer is zeroes and
ones as you all know.
And these bits of zeroes and ones encode a
lot of information.
The bits are collected into collections of
eight bits each collection of eight bits is
called a byte and they are stored inside the
memory.
For example the first byte that was eight
bits located in a physical address of zero
the second one would be one two and three
and all.
So there is a very long sequence of bits each
one containing zeroes and ones.
This is used to represent all types of data
with zeroes and ones we saw how we could represent
numbers but using numbers we can represent
audio we can represent video we can represent
documents spreadsheet.
All types of data can be represented with
zeroes and ones.
One other kind of data that is represented
is a program or an application.
An application is basically a set of instructions.
For example these 95 bytes here are a sequence
of instructions for a program named prog.exe.
Typically that’s the file extension for
an application it is executable .exe.
So assuming these bytes here are a program
prog.exe we can execute it and make the magic
of this application happen.
What happens when we double click an application?
When we want to start executing a program?
So there are a few steps that are happening
first thing that happens is obviously the
program is stored inside our secondary memory
so the first thing that happens is this program
is copied into our main memory in order for
the computer to have fast access to this set
of instructions.
And then these instructions are starting to
execute one after the other.
Obviously the CPU is responsible for that.
The CPU has a program counter register that
says where or what’s the next instruction
that would be executed.
It is initialized to 100 which is the first
instruction in this program and then the fetch
decode executes cycle is starting to happen.
Each cycle the instruction that the program
counter points to is fetched from the main
memory into the CPU.
Then the CPU decodes it understand what the
meaning what it has to do with this instruction
and then it executes it.
And over and over so the program counter is
increased and the next instruction is fetched
decoded and executed.
Program counter is increased and the instruction
is fetched decoded and executed.
This happens literally million times each
second and each the instructions are just
executed one after the other.
Whatever the program is intended to do basically
happens.