So, let's look at something that actually
happens in today's environment: it’s called
paging.
What we do is take main memory and we break
it down into a lot of equal size frames, and
each of the frames are the same size, every
frame is the same size.
And it's something small like four kilobytes;
it's not something significant.
Then what we do is we take down a process,
take a process and we break that down into
the exact same size pages.
So, we’ll take the process and break it
down into four kilobyte pages.
Now I'm sure you can see where this fits,
and that is that one page fits exactly into
one frame.
This is RAM okay, and what RAM means is that
we have random access memory, that means that
every single frame, in fact every single byte,
can be accessed all at the same amount of
time.
So, there's no benefit to keeping the process
as one coherent entity.
There's no reason we should keep the process
in sequential memory; that wasn't a failed
assumption that we had for fixed and dynamic
partitioning.
That we had to keep the process all together;
we don’t.
If we have bits of the process at the beginning
of main memory and bits of the process the
end of main memory, it doesn't matter as long
as we can keep track of them in order.
We can access the front of main memory and
the back of them in memory all at the same
time.
So, there's no reason that the process needs
to be continuous.
Now the operating system is going to have
to keep track of where each page is located
in main memory; what frame number each page
is loaded into.
And it can do that, it does that, in what's
known as a page map table or some books call
it or just simply a page table.
And the page map table is simply in an array
of frame numbers and if we look at index three,
for example into the page map table.
That's going to tell us where the fourth page,
zero one two three, where the fourth page
of the process is located; what frame number
the fourth page of the process is loaded into.
So, we can look now into the page map table
and find out where each of the pages in the
system is in physical memory, and that's exactly
what the hardware memory management needs
to do.
Whenever any logical memory request is made,
to a logical address, basically to the offset
from the beginning of the program, the hardware
memory management unit needs to calculate
how to convert that logical memory address
into a physical memory address.
And it doesn't take a lot of effort to do
so it can simply do a number of bit shift
left and bit shift right to get the the physical
address from the logical address.
and one of the features that it's going to
have to do is a look up into the page map
table.
So, the format of the page map table now is
going to be defined by the hardware manufacturer
and not by the operating system designer,
because the hardware needs to know first where
the page map table is stored and each process
is going to need its own page map table; each
process has its own page map table.
And the hardware memory management unit is
programmed, during a switch, during a context
switch, it's programmed for where that page
or app table is.
And the hardware memory management unit will
look up in the page map table where the appropriate
page is loaded and do the conversion between
page number and frame number and then look
at the offset.
So, this conversion process is a little bit
involved, and we’ll see it a little bit
later on.
But the benefit here is that we can use paging,
and we'll see the benefits of paging the next
slide.