I wanted to just look a little bit more at
how we convert a logical address to a physical
address in a paging system, and I know it
sounds a little bit complex but we're going
to boil it down and make it really easy.
We have to ultimately remember that what we're
trying to do…
We're given a logical address that is the
offset from the beginning of the program,
and the program doesn't know that it's not,
that it's memory is not completely sequential.
The program doesn't know that; it sees logical
addresses that are all completely sequential.
So, what we're going to do is use a very simple
calculation, which is going to be that the
physical address is equal to a look up in
the page map table for the logical address
divided by the page size multiplied by the
page size plus the logical address mod the
page size.
And you see that that's a divide and a mod
operation and you say, well wow that's got
to be a lot of work; it would be if the page
size were something other than a multiple
of two a factor of two.
And that's what makes this really easy because
the divisions and the mod operation are now
simply going to become bit shifts.
So, because we have the bit shift, and bits
shift really doesn't take much effort inside
the CPU certainly not in comparison to a divide
operation.
To calculate the page number: we’ll do bit
shifts to find the page number, we’ll look
up the page number in the page map table,
we’ll find out what the frame number is,
do the bit shift again as is the multiple
of the page size, and then we'll add the offset.
And to calculate the offset we simply looking
for the latter half of the physical, excuse
me, of the logical address.
So, we can do an XOR to wipe out the early
parts of the logical address and end up with
just the offset, and that tells us where the
page is located (what frame number it's in)
and how far into that page the offset we're
looking for for that particular byte of memory
that we need.
And that's how we convert a logical to a physical
address in a paging system.