The idea of segmentation makes sense and there's
a lot of systems that do it today; it’s
very popular.
Fortunately, it's not substantially different
than paging.
The only key difference here is that we’re
now allowed to have unequal sized partitions.
So, in paging system, we're assuming that
somebody came down and said that it's going
to be a four kilobyte page size and you might
argue well what if I don't want a four kilobyte
page size, for some reason I want something
larger or something smaller.
Segmentation says, in a simple segmentation
system,you could use any segment size and
we don't call it a page anymore, we call it
a segment; you can choose any segment size.
But now the logical addresses really have
to change because we need to talk about not
just the the logical address, we need to break
the logical address into two parts: a segment
number and an offset into that segment.
And then the operating system can keep different
segments in different locations, of course,
we need space for different segments.
So, this is kind of leading to a more dynamic
partitioning strategy, but the segments don't
necessarily have to be contiguous, so we can
now divide them up.
This isn't as as universal as you might see
a paging system.
What usually happens in a segmentation system
is the CPU designer will give you a few options
of segment sizes to choose from and so you
might not have just four kilobyte pages, You
might have four kilobyte pages, sixteen kilobyte
pages and sixty-four kilobyte pages.
The reason for this is that the operating
system if it knows it's going to need a lot
of main memory for this process, we can use
all sixty-four pages and then we have less
of them.
So, the page map tables are smaller and simpler
to maintain.
So, we don't really have the exact dynamic
partitioning or the design of a simple segmentation
system, where we have an infinite number of
segments sizes.
Instead we just have a few limiting segments
sizes and the CPU designers decide what segment
sizes we have as options.