If we're using a paging or segmentation system,
we have to recognize that the process is only
going to be making one memory reference at
any given time.
Now I know that's an overly simplistic view
of things, it's actually going to be making
a lot of memory references.
But one of the things that you can see is
that the memory references are all going to
be pretty much clustered together.
If we, for example, start a process and the
process throws a splash screen up on the screen.
You know starting Word or PowerPoint, that
splash screen will never appear again during
that run of the program.
But that splash screen takes a memory, there's
code that tells it how to display that splash
screen, and there's the splash screen itself
probably an image.
So, that memory is loaded into main memory
and it's never going to be used again.
So the question then becomes: why should still
be loaded in main memory, which is a finite
quantity very much in demand, why can't we
take it out of main memory and put it on the
hard drive?
Somewhere that we can bring it back if we
ever need to, if the process never needs it
again then it can just be deleted off the
hard drive and never recovered.
But what if the the process was never going
to use that splash screen for that run of
the process again.
And what if we just took it out of main memory
and left it on a hard drive.
And if we did that we would free up some main
memory and we would allow that main memory
to be used by other processes.
So, this is the concept known as virtual memory;
what we're doing is we're using a separate
portion of the hard drive, it’s not where
the process is normally stored.
It's a separate portion of the hard drive;
Windows calls a virtual memory, I think Mac
OS calls it the swap space, most Linux and
Unix clones call it a swap space.
But we have this area of a Hard drive dedicated
for storing pages of main memory, which are
no longer in main memory, which are no longer
going to be used.
Now the operating system can decide, dynamically,
which pages to save in main memory, which
pages stay in memory and which pages come
out.
And there has to be some operations that has
to go back and forth between main memory and
the secondary storage device, but it's a mechanism
for actually saving a lot of main memory for
more processes than would normally be allowed
to fit.
So, now if we say have only four gigabytes
of main memory, and we want to run one hundred
processes, each of which needs a gigabyte
of main memory, under normal circumstances
there's no way that we could do it.
But with virtual memory, we would be allowed
to do that; each of the hundred processes
would have a portion of the four gigabytes,
a portion of itself loaded in the four gigabytes,
the rest of it would be on secondary storage
and available.
So, we have to move these pages in and out
into main memory, and a lot of discussion
to talk about how that's done, but we have
that available now.
We can use more memory than is actually in
the system.