So, what do we keep in main memory and what
do we throw out?
What is the process going to use and what
is the process not going to use?
How do we is the operating system, a group
of people who had never seen this program
before, decide what the process should be
able, to be allowed to keep and what it should
throw out?
Well the first issue that comes up is that
we have a resident set.
The resident said is that portion that's in
main memory, and we have a working set and
that's the portion of the process wants to
use.
Now in order to run, the working set has to
be in the residence set.
So, the working set must contain the residence.
So, we have to have the stuff that we want
loaded into main memory.
We're going to extend on that page map table
that we talked about just a few slides ago
and we're going to say that it now has an
a present bit, and of course that means we
have to update the hardware memory management
unit and that's a much more involved process.
The memory management unit has to know about
all the stuff that's going on with virtual
memory and it does, these days we know about
it.
The page map table is going to contain what's
called a present bit, a P bit and the present
bit tells the memory management unit whether
or not that page is actually in main memory.
If the page is not in main memory, then the
present bit will be unset and then we know
that we have to look for that page on a secondary
storage device if the process wants it.
We also have something known as a modified
bit, and the modified bit is useful because
we're going to make copies of pages in secondary
storage before we realize that the the process
doesn't need them anymore.
So, what we would like to do is make duplications
of the main memory into the secondary storage
device, so that when it's time to decide to
remove a page from main memory we can look
for a page that has the modified bit unset.
And what that means is that the copy on the
secondary storage device Is the exact same
as the copy in main memory, which means we
don't have to go to IO to actually do the
write operation we can simply erase the page
out of main memory and trust that the copy
on the secondary storage device is valid.
As I mentioned the hardware memory management
unit has to know what happens when it finds
a present bit set to zero, and what it does
is whenever it looks at the page map table
and finds the present bits at zero, it's what's
called a page fault.
and the CPU stops running the process and
instead switches to the operating system,
very much in the way that an interrupt would
occur, it switches to the operating system
and begins running code to handle the page
fault.
And then the operating system can make the
decision on whether the page fault was caused
by a page which is no longer present, or perhaps
was caused by a page which the process should
not have any access to to begin with.
And that's a page fault that's going to result
in an exception error; that's going to shut
down the process.
That hardware memory management unit also
has to recognize that the modified bit has
to be changed any time we make a change to
that page in main memory, so any write operations
to a page in main memory would cause the modify
bit to get set.
But now the hardware memory management unit
knows all about that and as the operating
system we're just responsible for writing
the code that brings in and out pages, and
updates and maintains the present bits, and
works with the modified bits.