Well one of the problems that we get now is
that memory management is always going to
require two look ups.
So when we're talking about accessing any
memory space, any logical address, it Now
requires to look ups into main memory.
So the M.M.U. is going to have to first look
up in the page map table where this is located,
and then translate that into a frame number,
and then access that frame number.
So every main memory access now, by a process,
is going to result in two main memory accesses.
Now main memory is fast; There’s no question
it's that.
But when we're doubling the price of everything,
It really starts to add up and it slows down
the C.P.U.
So with the C.P.U. implemented with C.P.U.
designers implemented that we just have to
take into account, There’s not much as the
operating system we need to do about it.
but what the C.P.U. designers implemented
was what's called a translation look aside
buffer. and the translation look aside buffer
is a type of content addressable memory, which
stores a cache. and I've got a picture here
for you So that you can see it.
it stores a cache of those entries in the
P.M.T. which have been retrieved recently,
and what it basically is is a table where
we're looking up the virtual page number,
which on that image that you're seeing is
the the V.P N in that table; the virtual page
number with a physical page number.
so that virtual page number to physical page
number mapping is only temporary, It’s only
there for a short period of time.
in fact once we have a context switch, we
basically have to dump the translation look
aside buffer.
But that virtual page number to physical page
number mapping can be looked up because this
is content addressable memory, It can be looked
up in a time a big O of one, constant time
search through the entire V.P.N. table.
So the V.P.N. table Can be looked at and if
the the virtual page number entered is there,
then we'll get back the physical page number
and we can use that immediately inside the
C.P.U. without accessing main memory.
So it's just for speeding things up, so that
we can avoid one of those memory references
that we can avoid going to main memory and
asking for that value.
if we don't have the value from the page map
table already loaded in the T.L.
B, then we have to go look at the page map
table and there's no way of to avoid that.
But the the the page map table is not going
to change while the process is running, of
course because we can't do relocation while
the process is running.
So the translation look aside buffer is a
way to avoid that double memory access for
multiple accesses to the same virtual page
number.
and it does work, It's not a huge savings
but over the course of a run of the program,
It does cut the memory references not in half
but certainly significantly less.