What happens when we run out of main memory?
I mean it can happen ultimately, since we're
giving each process as much memory as it wants
affectively there's going to be a point in
time when main memory runs out.
And of course we're still going to be using
virtual memory, so the swap space is going
to start to be used, but what happens when
we physically run out of main memory.
Well now we're going to have to make a decision
on which pages to pull out of the main memory,
which pages no longer needed in main memory,
and which we should load.
This is called stealing; the choice of pulling
out a page, and pulling a page out of main
memory, it's called stealing.
And unfortunately if we choose poorly we can
really cause a lot of performance issues because
if we remove a page which is going to be used,
that's going to require an IO operation, it's
going to require us possibly writing that
page to the secondary storage device if the
modified bit is set, we’re going to have
to write it to the secondary storage device
then remarked the present bit to zero.
And when the process runs again and wants
to use that page, We're going to have to have
a page fault and bring that back in.
So, one one way of looking at the performance
of virtual memory is to count the total number
of page faults that are happening perception
and if that number is is too high then one
of the problems might be, the first obvious
problem is that we have an insufficient amount
of main memory.
But the second obvious problem might be that
we're choosing the wrong pages to remove;
we’re choosing pages that the process will
immediately will want.
We have a number of different algorithms that
we can use for choosing which page the process
might want.
One of them that we call…
One of them we call the optimal algorithm
or this might be called the crystal ball algorithm.
Because what it is is we look into our crystal
ball, not literally of course, but we would
look into our crystal ball and decide which
page is not needed for the longest period
of time.
Now of course without looking at the process
and what it's going to do in the next execution
cycle, we can't know how long it's not going
to need a page for.
So, this is more a comparison algorithm, we
can look at the memory accesses that a process
did in its entire history and use that as
a judge for deciding what would have been
the optimal choices for page replacement,
but ultimately we can't do this in real life.
There's also the LRU algorithm, the least
recently used, and in order to do this we
would need a timestamp on each page to tell
us when the last time that page was accessed;
not modified, accessed.
And unfortunately, we don't have time stamps
on every page and it's too much overhead inside
the CPU to timestamp every page.
So the LRU is not really feasible either.
The FIFO algorithm is really simple; we just
throughout the oldest page that we've brought
in.
But that doesn't say anything as to whether
or not we're actually still using that page,
and if we're still using that page and we
throw it out it's going to immediately cause
a page fault.
In other words, it might be the oldest because
the one that's needed the most.
The last algorithm is relatively easy to implement
it does require use bits.
And thankfully, the hardware memory management
units did recognize that, and what we have
is the clock page replacement algorithm.
So, we're using use bits to indicate when
a page was used and what we do is…
The hardware memory management unit updates
those used bits whenever a page is used.
In fact, it doesn't even have a problem with
the translation look aside buffer, because
what the hardware memory management unit does
is when it loads the physical page number,
sorry the frame number if you will, into the
TLB it's going to update the use bit to be
a one.
So, the use bits just indicate whether or
not the page was used recently and that's
going to allow us to do the clock paid for
placement algorithm which we're going to see
in the next slide.
So, we have to choose a replacement algorithm
in some way to choose which slide is going
to be, sorry to choose which page is going
to be stolen, but if we make the decision
with some reasonable piece of information
then we can make it an effective decision
making process.