We're going to look at what the operating
system has to do to take care of all of main
memory, all of the RAM in the system, and
there's a lot that has to be done.
So, in this module we're going to cover what
the needs are for memory management: some
requirements that we have to meet for memory
management.
We're going to talk about logical addresses
and physical addresses and how to convert
between them.
We're going to talk about a few partitioning
strategies for dividing up main memory.
We're going to talk about what is virtual
memory, when it's in use, how it works, and
that sort.
We're going to talk about working set, and
resident set strategies related to virtual
memory, and what the those definitions are.
We're going to talk about load control and
we're going to talk about how pages and memory
can be shared between processes.
So, we’ve got a lot to cover in this module;
let’s get to it.