The variable interval sampled working set
or VSWS algorithm tries to solve PFF’s problems
by setting a number of different parameters.
The first one is an M value, a minimum value
for clearing out the unused pages.
If we’re ever below M, we’re always going
to add on a new page.
If the page fault ever happens below M, we
always add on a new page.
Then we set a Q value, and we say if we're
above M and we've reached Q page faults.
We've had Q page faults since the last time
we reset all the used bits and threw out the
unused pages, then let's go ahead and do that
algorithm again.
So between M, above M and above Q, we would
throw out all the unused pages and reset the
use bits.
Even if we’re above M, but we've only had
a very small number of page faults then it's
too much work to go through the whole algorithm
of resetting the used bits and throwing out
the unused pages; so, we'll just add a page.
But once we get to L, L is the maximum limit.
Once we get to L time units then it's time.
It doesn't matter how many page faults we've
had; this process had its chance.
It's now time to throw out the unused pages,
reset the use bits ,and let the process run
again.
So, even if we don't get a page fault by the
time we get to L, we now say it's time to
run this algorithm and clear out the old waste.
And that's the point that VSWS solves the
PFF shortcomings by through setting the L
value to say that even if we haven't had a
large number of page faults by the time we
reach L, there's got to be some stale information
there and we'll throw out that that old locality’s
information.
So, it does actually solve the problems of
PFF and it actually works fairly effectively.