I recognize that if we're using virtual memory
and/or paging, then we can understand that
we can share structures; we can share portions
of a process.
And the way that we can do that is quite simple:
we can just have duplicate entries, duplicate
frame number entries in a page map table.
So, since the code doesn't change, for example,
if we opened up five copies of Chrome would
we need five different copies of the code
for Chrome.
The answer is no, not necessarily.
The operating system may be smart enough,
may be capable, of recognizing that multiple
copies of the same program are running and
it will share the code pages, not the data
pages, not the context, just the code pages
of that process because the code is not going
to change from one process to the next process
as long as they are the same program.
So, if we're running Chrome twice, we should
probably only load it's code once; it will,
each copy will have a different data section
but who cares because at least we're saving
the memory for the code.
Now there's also the possibility that a process
will want to share data pages, but unfortunately
if we're going to share data pages any changes
to those data pages have to result in a duplications
of those pages of data; not necessarily the
entire portion of data but just those pages
that are going to change.
So, even if you're just changing one byte
inside a page, we have to make an entire copy
of the page.
Now this is what's called copy on write, or
cow, and it allows the sharing of the pages.
The page table is now extended to the to have
a read only attribute and if the page is marked
as read only any attempt to change that page
is going to result in a call to the operating
system.
And the operating system can then say this
process is trying to change a page which has
COW enabled.
And when we change that page the operating
system will make a duplications of just that
page, update the appropriate page map tables,
unsetting the read only bit and then re running
the instruction.
So, that the the operating system can intervene
only of course when necessary, make the copy
of the page, and then the processes can run
again not realizing that the pages are now
separate and different.