The greatest example of this is the Unix FORK
function; it’s been around for a while but
it really does work quite well.
The Unix FORK function when you call it, it
actually returns two values.
The reason or returns two different values
is because it's going to create an exact copy
of the entire current process.
Now this is useful if, for example I'm just
using this as an example.
It's not actually how it works, but if for
example in Chrome you click the button to
create a new tab, we wanted different version
of, we want to a different process for example,
but it might be the exact same code.
You might have not just a brand new copy but
a duplicate an exact duplicate of the existing
page.
And so what we can do is call the Unix FORK
function.
FORK will return I believe it's a zero if
the child, if the process is the child process
what's known as the child process which is
the new process, or it return the process
identifier of the child process if this is
the parent process.
So, we're creating two processes it's sort
of like, the creation of a new amoeba out
of an existing amoeba, right.
That's an exact copy of the existing process;
but how does it do this?
Well, with the operating system will do is
create a new PCB a new process control block,
it creates all the new page tables, but the
page tables are an exact copy of the original
page table and everything in both page tables
is marked as COW, Copy-On-Write. if any of
the process in either process changes the
page then that page alone is duplicated, but
it saves the operating system having to actually
go into main memory and duplicate all of main
memory for this process into a new process.
All it does is duplicate the page when it
changes.