We covered a lot of material in this module,
and memory management is not a simple task
at all, we know that.
The operating system does a lot of work for
memory management.
But we did cover the need for memory management
and we covered the memory management requirements;
we understand those requirements of protection,
and relocation, logical organization, sharing,
physical organization.
We talked about partitioning strategies.
We talked about logical versus physical addresses,
and how to convert them, specifically in the
paging scenario we did a lot of calculations
on how it works.
We talked about virtual memory.
We talked about the working set strategies
and the resident set strategies and we used
resident set strategies to determine how we
can control the load of the system, how many
processes we really have running.
And then we talked about shared pages and
copy on write and then the magic of the Unix
FORK function.
So, we certainly covered a lot on memory management
there, of course in a current and current
system today's environment, there’s a lot
more that has to go into memory management
and these are only the basics.
But at least with the basics we can get started
with understanding some of the more complex
features, and the operating systems courses
are going to cover a lot of memory management
techniques that we just kind of glazed over.
So, there's a lot more out there; some of
it that Microsoft will even tell us about
we have to find out manually.
But there's at least a good basics in this
module.