When we look at the operating system, we're
looking at a multiprogramming system.
And in a multiprogramming system, obviously,
we're going to have a lot of processes running
all at the same time.
And since we're going to have a lot of processes
running all the same time, there's never going
to be enough main memory.
And I've been in this industry now for over
twenty years and I can tell you that the problems
never change.
The sizes certainly do change; when we started
out, when I started out in this industry we
were talking about main memory sizes of probably
around one-hundred twenty-eight megabytes
or two-hundred fifty-six megabytes.
So, your average system might have two-hundred
fifty-six megabytes of main memory and if
you bought a system like that today it would
be absolutely useless.
And we look at more common systems today of
eight gigabytes, sixteen gigabytes, probably
thirty-two gigabytes is not in the very far
distant future, and we think that the problem
is solved by adding more memory and it isn't.
There will never be enough main memory.
Wherever we add memory, programmers tend to
use that memory.
So, it's always a little bit of a battle between
hardware and software with the hardware trying
to keep up, usually, and the software trying
to use more and more memory to do more and
more work.
The operating system is going to be responsible
for allocating memory to lots of programs
running in the system all at the same time,
and the operating system is going to need
to move parts between main memory and secondary
memory.
So, there's a lot of work that the operating
system has to do even though we have main
memory and main memory just looks like a very
large array.
We're going to have to divide that up and
share it among a lot of different programs
that are all running at the same time; that
all want access to that main memory, and that
all want to use more and more and more.