The operating system understands physical
addresses, and the computer system, of course,
understands, as you saw back when we were
talking about instruction sets, the computer
system understands physical addresses.
main memory is broken down in physical addresses.
so if you have four gigabytes of main memory,
for example, you have adverse zero through
Agis four point two billion.
So, the computer system understands a physical
address and expects to be communicated with
physical addresses.
Unfortunately, the programs will only be able
to use logical addresses.
And that's because the program has no idea
where it will be loaded physically.
So, we can do this quite simply, we can think
of this quite simply, as a relocation problem.
If we can use the offset from the beginning
of the program, since the program should have
no access outside of its own memory space.
If the addresses that the program is going
to use for all the pointers, and all the code,
and all the jumps, and everything that it's
going to do, if those addresses could be logical
addresses relative to the offset from the
beginning of the program, then the program
doesn't really need to know where it's physically
loaded in main memory.
So, if we have that then we're going to recognize
that those logical addresses need to be converted
dynamically at run time into physical addresses.
And so what we can do is use what's called
the hardware memory management unit, CPUs
have now created they were evolved in the
1980’s to have this hardware memory management
unit, and that would be responsible for converting
during run time the logical address to the
physical address.
And it's not a difficult calculation, in a
very simple example, we can say that the hardware
memory management unit can know the starting
address of the program.
and then when it sees a memory reference,
when it sees a pointer, when it sees it jump
to code, or anything like that, when we see
that logical memory reference the hardware
memory management unit will convert it by
adding the base address of the program into
the logical address that the program is trying
to reference to produce a physical address.
And then the CPU will actually access that
physical address, rather than accessing a
logical address that the program is asking
for.
So, at run time without the operating systems
intervention because remember the operating
system is asleep while the program is running,
the program will make a reference to a logical
address and then the OP, the hardware memory
management unit, will convert that logical
address into a physical address and make the
appropriate reference.
So, the program doesn't have to know anything
more about where things are physically located,
and it meets our relocation and protection
requirements because we can now physically
move the entire process to a completely different
location, while it's not running and then
update the hardware memory management unit
the next time it runs to tell it where the
new, where the process is now.
And then the hardware memory management and
of course will do that calculation at run
time.
So it doesn't require a lot of work it meets
our protection and relocation requirements;
this is a perfect solution.