What we do in fixed partitioning is when the
system boots up, we can divide main memory
into some static number of parts.
Let's imagine a situation where we have four
megabytes, four gigabytes of main memory and
we're going to divide it up into let's say
sixteen different partitions, now those could
be either equal sized partitions or unequal
sized partitions.
And if they are equal sized partitions, then
let's imagine that those sixteen different
partitions, each run two-hundred and fifty
megabytes in size, so our four gigabytes of
main memory is broken down into sixteen equal
partitions of two-hundred and fifty megabytes
each.
Now that works; it’s fine.
It means we have a maximum limit of running
sixteen different processes; we can't run
any more than sixteen different processes.
and one other problem is if we start up notepad,
and notepad is going to just edit a small
text file and it only needs one megabyte of
main memory, well the smallest we can put
it in is two hundred fifty megabytes, because
we have equal sized partitions.
So, what that means is that we're wasting
two-hundred and forty megabytes of main memory
and that's pretty significant.
That's what we call internal fragmentation.
We have this division allocated, for notepad,
we give it two-hundred and fifty megabytes
for notepad and notepad only really wants
one megabyte.
And the other two hundred forty megabytes
now are wasted in internal fragmentation.
One solution that we could use is to maybe
use unequal sized partition, so partitions
which are differing in size.
And if we do that we might say there are sixteen
different partitions, one partition is very
very big it's one gigabyte, and other partitions
are very very small there might be ten meg,
ten megabyte partitions or just slightly larger.
The point is that we're always going to have
some internal fragmentation with these solutions,
but we're going to maybe minimize the amount
of internal fragmentation.
Now if we use unequal sized partitions, we’re
going to have to worry about which partition
we decide to place this process in.
Let’s say we open up notepad and we open
up a small text file and so the operating
system decides, okay we'll put it into one
of the ten megabyte partitions and then somebody
chooses to open up an enormous file of one
gigabyte file.
Let's say a video file but they're opening
in Notepad.
Well now the operating system has to move
that process out of its memory space; we can
do that because of relocation and move it
into the one gigabyte partition that we have,
the only one gigabyte partition that we have.
And what happens if that one gigabyte partition
is taken by something else, maybe chrome,
and now notepad cannot run at the same time
as Chrome, because they both need that one
gigabyte partition.
So, there are some real disadvantages to having
fixed partition.
But one of the big advantages of it is it's
really simple, really requires very little
effort on the part of the operating system.
But the downside is that we have very limiting
factors on the number of processes that we
can run, and we also waste a lot of memory
in internal fragmentation.