The buddy system is actually a compromise
between the fixed and the dynamic partitionings.
And again there's not a lot of operating systems
that do this today, in fact I don't know any
of them, but for example, Linux uses this
for what it calls its kernel slab allocator.
So, when the kernel itself needs to create
some memory for the kernel, it will use a
chunk of memory and divide that chunk of memory
as a buddy system, just to make smaller partitions
of a larger chunk of main memory.
So, while we don't do this on a large scale
for all of main memory, there are certainly
situations where even Linux today will do
this for parts of its slab allocator for creation
of, or for allocation of smaller parts of
main memory for kernel purposes.
Anyhow, what it does is we take main memory
and divide it in multiples of two.
And the reason of course that we're doing
multiples of two is because it makes it easier
on the calculations; we don't have to necessarily
record the starting in the ending point, we
can record what multiple of two this is and
so on and so forth.
Let's take for example, a two megabyte memory
allocation, so let's say the the Linux kernel
has a two megabyte memory allocation for it
and wants to divide it up for purposes for
storage of an IO table, or storage of a main
memory management table, or who knows.
It’s got to store some portion of information
but two megabytes would be a huge waste, it
needs something much smaller.
The kernel means is let's say one hundred
kilobytes, for whatever it's going to do.
The process then is that we take that two
megabytes and start breaking it down into
divisions, so you can see that what we've
created initially, we take the two megabytes
and divide it in half so that we end up with
the a one thousand and twenty four kilobyte
allocation and another one thousand twenty
four kilobyte allocation.
But that's way over what we need of hundred
kilobytes, so we break down one of the one
thousand twenty-four kilobytes into two five
hundred twelve kilobyte allocations.
Then we'll take one of the five hundred twelve
kilobyte allocations and break that down into
two two hundred fifty six kilobyte allocations
and that's still too much.
So, we take that and divide it down again
into two one hundred twenty eight kilobyte
allocations.
If we were to divide the one twenty eight
KP allocation again, it would be a sixty-four
kilobyte allocation and that's too small to
fit the hundred kilobytes need that we have.
So, we would have to we would have to stop
there and use one hundred twenty eight killed
by an allocation.
Now this results of course in internal fragmentation,
because it's going to end up where… we’re
going to end up allocating one hundred twenty-eight
kilobyte, when only one hundred kilobytes
was needed.
But we're talking about twenty-eight kilobytes
so it's not an overly significant factor.
We might end up with some extra fragmentation
if we have a lot of these small slivers but
one of the nice features of the buddy system
is what's called coalescing.
We can take those two hundred twenty-eight
kilobit allocations, and recombine them up
into a two hundred fifty-six kilobyte allocation.
and we can keep doing that ultimately getting
back to the original two megabyte allocation,
if we ever need to.
So, coalescing allows us to bring these back
into a larger hole.
If we have a large number of hundred kilobytes
processes, we might take that hundred one
hundred twenty eight kilobyte allocations
that we already have but we'll also divide
the two fifty-six into two one twenty-eight.
We divide the five twelve into two two fifty-sixes
in each of those into one twenty-eight.
So, we can we can create a lot of one hundred
twenty-eight kilobyte partitions out of this
original two megabytes.
So, we end up decreasing the amount of internal
fragmentation, overall, because if we had
only two megabyte allocations there would
be one point nine megabytes of completely
wasted space, because we'd have to allocate
two megabytes for one hundred kilobyte allocation.
It makes the operating system structures easier,
because they're beginning and ending on a
two to the N boundary it.
It actually does work quite well, the only
problem is coalescing back does take some
effort.
And so Linux actually delays that, it's called
delayed coalescing.
It waits until much later on, when the operating
system is not very busy and it says: “you’re
probably not going to use these anymore”
and then it recombines them back up.
But ultimately this does work; it doesn't
work on a grand scale, it works on a micro
scale.
But it is a solution that involves both fixed
and dynamic partitioning and it is a compromise
between the two.