Let's use the strong induction technique to
prove some claim.
So let's show that every natural number N
can be written in the form of two to the power
of I times J, where I is a non-negative integer
and J is odd.
Basically, we’ll try to show that N can
be written as a power of two times an odd
number.
For example, forty: we can write forty as
two to the power of three, which is eight,
times five.
So, it's a power of two with the non-negative
integer exponent times an odd number.
That is true, we should show it not only for
forty but for all natural number N.
For example, for six: six can be written as
two to the power of one times three, and seven,
for example, can be written as two to the
power of zero times seven.
And we’ll show that any number, any natural
number, can be written in this form: some
power of two with a non-negative exponent
times an odd number.
Let's go ahead and show it.