Let’s try to convince ourselves that this
magical implementation here really works.
So, I’ll do it in two separate ways.
first you've executed it and probably saw
that it basically works, but let me try to
convince you a first more logically some kind
of a bottom up argument, just like I show
you that recursion basically prove that P
of N is always true, so that would be one
way for me to convince you that this implementation
basically is fine.
The second is a more formal tracing of using,
I don’t know, runtime stack and stuff like
that.
but let's start with a more logical argument
here to show that print ascending, for example,
one four basically prints the values one,
two, three, four.
To do that, as I said, I'm going to make a
bottom up argument.
Let’s first convince ourselves that print
ascending one and one basically prints the
values in that range, basically prints one
correctly.
So if we’ll execute print ascending one
one we’ll first evaluate the condition if
start equals to end, it would be true.
We would print start, in this case one and
our function with the end after that.
So, print ascending one one prints one which
is exactly what it should do; remember that
for the future, so print one one works fine.
Now let's try to trace the sending one and
two.
So when we look at the Boolean condition start
equals end for one and two that would be false.
We’ll go to the else clause in this case
we will print the sending start and in minus
one which would be one in one.
We know that from the sending one one prints
one we don't need to re execute it we already
know that when we call print the sending one
while we get one as an output.
So this line would print one after that we
would print the end which is two, both of
them together would print one and two.
So print ascending one two also works as we
expected to; it would print one and two, so
keep that in mind to.
Now let's see how/what print ascending one
and three does.
Once again start equals two and is false here,
so we go to the else clause.
We call print ascending with start and end
minus one, in this case it's a one and two.
We’ve already seen that print ascending
one two prints one and two, so this line would
print one and two.
After that we are printing end for all so
together we are printing one, two, three,
four.
Print ascending one and three prints the numbers
one, two, three, just as required; keep that
in mind so print ascending one and three prints
one, two, three.
Let's finally see how print ascending one
and four prints one, two, three, four.
Once again, the Boolean condition is false;
we go to the else clause.
We call print ascending for one and three;
we know that this call would print one, two,
and three.
After that we print end, which is four, all
together it prints one, two, three, four.
That shows that print ascending one to four
prints the entire range of one two three four.
I hope that this argument here convinced you
not only for one and four that print ascending
works properly, it would convince you that
any range of size one works.
Therefore, any range of size to works properly
and equal for range of size three works properly.
Therefore, any range of size four would work
properly and so on.
So, print ascending basically this implementation
is basically fine.
next video will talk about the runtime stack
of this execution.