Hi there, hope you're having a great day.
Today we're going to talk about recursions;
recursions are basically a very powerful problem
solving technique that we're going to explore
and see how it works.
But before we do that, let's talk a bit about
mathematical induction.
I know the two are very related to one another;
there is a very close relationship between
mathematical induction and recursion.
I’m not sure exactly how much you're familiar
with mathematical induction so let me do a
short overview of mathematical induction.
First, so methodical Induction is a technique
to prove statements; it's a mathematical technique
to prove statements.
Basically it's used to prove universal statements
that are of the form P of N is true for any
natural number.
So, for all of the natural numbers P of N
is true.
This is the form of statements we use mathematical
induction proving technique.
When we prove using mathematical inductions
or there are basically two steps in our proof:
there is the base case and there is the inductive
step.
In the base case, we typically prove that
P of one is true, that our statement is true
for the smallest natural number for one P
of one is true, that's the thing we do in
our base case.
In the inductive step, we show that P of N
minus one implies P of N.
So, if we know P of N minus one is true, we
can also show that P of N is true too.
And we show this statement P of N minus one
implies P of N for any natural number greater
than or equal to two.
When we use these two steps to prove a universal
statement as we said, basically we're not
showing in a straightforward manner that P
of N is true for all natural numbers but we
say that after proving the base case and the
inductive step we can conclude that P of N
is true for all natural numbers.
And let's get convinced that these two steps
basically imply that P of N is true for any
natural number.
So, let's see what we've proved and what conclusions
can we make out of it.
So, obviously when we prove that P of one
is true we can say that P of one is true.
But then we also prove that P of one implies
P of two, now since we already know that one
is true, this implication would lead that
P of two is also true.
And we've proved this P of N. minus one implies
P of N, not only for one and two but for any
natural number so we also prove that P of
two implies P of three given that we already
have concluded P of two is true.
These two together would lead us to say that
P of three is true and once again P of three
implies P or four and P of three is true,
so P of four is also true and this keeps on
going.
And that way we can just say that P of one,
P of two, P of three, P of four, or basically
any P. of N for all natural numbers are true.
That's like the bases of mathematical induction.