Let's write another recursive implementation.
This time let's implement the function are
all even; this function gets in the range
of integers as a parameter and its logical
size N. and it should return true if all of
the elements in this array even, if not all
of them are even it would just return false.
For example, if we’ll call this function
with an array, let's say four, six, zero,
and two and the logical size four, obviously
it would return true because all of the elements
here are even.
If we'll call this function with the array
four, seven, zero, and two with logical size
four, it would return false because not of
all of the elements here are even.
For example, seven in this case is odd.
Let's try to have a recursive implementation
using a computer; let's do that now.