Let’s show that every natural number can
be written as a power of two times an odd
number.
Once again you can see that this statement
is of the form for any natural number some
P of N is true; this is our P of N and know
that N can be written in some form.
Let's go ahead and prove it.
Actually before we start proving using strong
induction, let's see that just the regular
mathematical induction can't really help us
here.
So, in regular induction we would probably
say that we assume that P of N minus one is
true or basically N minus one can be written
in the form of two to the power of some I
times an odd number J, so let's assume we
have that.
And given that, we should show that N is also
some power of two times an odd number.
The only straightforward way I'm thinking
of combining N with N minus one is just adding
one to it, but then if N minus one is two
to the I times J, if I'll add one to it, I
won't get something of the form some power
of I times J. But then if we know that this
thing is true, not only for N minus one but
for all other values of N.
For example, I know that N is two times N
by two.
So, if I know that N by two, for example,
is two times two to the power of I times J,
then N would be two times two to the power
of I times J, which would be some power of
two times an odd number.
So, using the assumption on a smaller value
than N minus one, in this case N by two, seems
to be helpful more than using the assumption
of N minus one.
That's why a strong induction here is better.
Let's use a strong induction to show exactly
that.
Okay.
So, a proof will prove by a strong induction
on N. And once again, we have two steps: the
base and inductive step.
So for the base, we should show that P of
one is true.
So, for any cause one, we should show how
we can represent one as some power of two
times an odd number.
So, that's very easy cause one is two to the
zero times one.
So, if we take our power of two to be zero,
the exponent to be zero, and our odd number
to be one we get that one is basically two
to the zero times one, just as requested.
And now, let's do the inductive step.
In this case, we should assume that P of N
is true for any value smaller than N. And
using that assumption, we should show that
P of N is true, so let's have this assumption
ready.
So we assume that every K smaller than N can
be written in the form of K equals two to
some power of I times J, where obviously I
is a non-negative integer and J is odd.
So, this is our assumption; it's cement.
And now we show that N itself can also be
written in this form.
Now we show that N can be written as two to
the power of I times J, obviously other I's
and J’s here, with I and J as described.
So, this is what we need to show.
So, we’ll use this assumption here in order
to show that N can be represented this way
and this assumption is for every value of
K; for K equals N minus one, N minus two,
N minus three, and so on.
Also for K equals N by two, which would be
the value of K that we would like to use this
assumption on.
Yeah, so let's do that.
The only thing is that we need to take care,
or in other words, not every N has an integer
N by two; odd numbers you can't really divide
by two and get another integer value after
this division.
So, let's separate to the two cases when our
N is odd and when it's even and do all of
that.
So, we have two cases to take care of: the
first is that N is odd; the second is that
N is even.
So, for the second case that's the main part
of this proof is when we're going to use the
inductive assumption on N by two.
The first case is quite easy when N is odd,
obviously you can represent it as a power
of two times an odd number, just take the
power of two to be zero, so it would be one
times N itself.
So, in this case, if we take I to be zero
and J to be N, we get that N equals two to
the power of zero times N, which is obviously
N, and I and J are as requested; so, we're
fine.
In the case where N is even, now we're going
to do what we basically said we'll do here
in this case.
Since N by two is less than N, by the inductive
hypothesis, if we take K to be N by two, we
get that N by two is then equal to two to
the power of two to the power of some, let's
say, I prime times J prime for our non-negative
I prime and all J prime.
And now we can, given that, we can present
N in other requested form.
So, since N is basically two times N by two,
in the case where N is even, that is exactly
the case.
We get that N is two times two to the power
of I prime times J prime, which is basically
two to the power of I prime plus one times
J prime.
Therefore, if we take our I to be I prime
plus one, the value that the inductive assumption
gave us for the power of two for N by two
plus one and J prime to be or our J to be
the same as J prime.
Then, we get a N written in the requested
form.
That concludes our proof here using strong induction.