Probably the most important consideration
here is what the CPU does when it has to execute
instructions.
And it performs what’s called the fetch-execute
cycle, or the fetch-decode-execute cycle.
What it does is move one instruction from
main memory, which we haven’t talked about
but we will in just a minute, it moves it
from main memory into a register in the CPU,
which is known as the instruction register.
And then it decodes the instruction and if
necessary moves in any necessary parameters,
so it copies those parameters in from main
memory.
And once everything is complied in the CPU,
once everything is loaded in the CPU, then
the CPU can actually execute that instruction
and do whatever the task is that is asked.
For example, if we had an add instruction
which added two numbers together, the fetch
would be for a particular memory location.
And we would bring that memory location to
the register, and we’d add that to a value,
maybe that’s already in the CPU or maybe
its in main memory.
Once the operation is complete, then we repeat
the process with the next instruction in the
sequence.
So this operation happens very very very quickly
in the system and it has to happen literally
millions of times per second in the CPU.
Which means each operation could take as little
as a bout 10 nanoseconds to perform this operation
which is unbelievably small.
Nano is one times ten to the negative nine,
so we’re talking about something happening
incredibly quickly inside the system.
So while it happens very frequently, literally
millions of times a second, it happens very
very quickly.