Computers only understand very basic commands
and I've listed some of the commands here,
so you can see them: move, add, subtract,
multiply, compare, and jump.
You're not seeing any of the higher level
commands that you might see in a high level
language.
So there's really no function calls; there's
not a lot of not a lot of commands that we
would see except for very basic math operations.
There are a lot of machine language instructions,
but this set of machine language instructions
is limited and we can't really add to it.
The machine language instructions are designed
physically into the chip.
So the chip is programmed by its manufacture
and it's written in silicone in the chip.
So we can’t expand on that we have no capability
to add instructions, but we have the capability
to build higher level languages and make the
higher level languages convert to the machine
language instructions.