RAM is another term that we use for main memory
and that's because of it's the way it's constructed
it's known as random access memory because
any place in the memory can be accessed in
the same amount of time, which in computer
science is known as random time.
So we can access any byte of main memory at
the same amount of time.
The areas of main memory inside RAM are broken
down into bytes and each byte is access independently,
so we can access all of the bytes of main
memory as individual bytes or we can group
them together in terms of known as a word
or D word or cue word double word or quad
word.
Usually they're accessed in terms of the data
types which we're accessing might have a particular
size.
So for example in C++ it's very common to
have an integer which is a size of four bytes
which is equivalent to a D word or double
word.
Unfortunately was RAM, as we said when the
computers turned off everything in RAM is
lost, all of it is completely erased and that's
by virtue of its design.
So once the electrical power is shut down
to RAM, then the RAM no longer contains any
information.
When running a program all the machine language
instructions are brought into RAM and then
there one by one pulled by the CPU during
the fetch and execute cycle into that instruction
register and then process.
So RAM is an absolutely critical portion of
the system and we have to know how it works
in order to use.