So in this image, we've got what looks like
the inside of a desktop computer and you're
seeing hopefully what you would expect to
see when you open up a regular desktop computer.
In the upper right there we've got the power
supply, which has the big label that says
Dell on it.
And below that is what we call the main board
or motherboard of the computer where we have
most of the main components related to the
computer.
Down below it you'll see the CPU.
The memory is off to the left.
A little bit further than that you have the
secondary storage device which in this case
looks like a spinning hard drive.
All the way up in the upper left we have the
tertiary storage device which looks like a
CD-ROM and then run about the middle we have
the video controller card.
So these are the major macro components of
what's inside of a computer and each of them
communicate with each other through the main
board which has components known as the system
bus, which we're going to talk about in a
little bit.