In this first module we just want to give
everybody a start off with a basis on what
a computer is and how it works.
In the future modules we're going to be doing
a lot of programming.
We're going to be doing a lot of operating
systems concerns.
We're going to be doing a lot of things that
you need to know about what goes on inside
the computer and so in this module we just
like to start you off with the very basis
of what's inside the computer and how things
work.
We don't know what your background is we don't
know where you come from or what your history
is so if some of this is a little bit basic,
then we apologize but for everybody we'd
like to start off on the same foot.