Just like the ofstream object, we have an
ifstream object which we can use to read information.
And we can use the dot open or we can use
the constructor for the object to open the
file.
Unfortunately, input files are a lot more
likely to fail when they're opening and the
reason for that is more than likely somebody
inputted a bad filename.
Remember that we're not selecting the file
graphically for through a graphical user interface,
we're writing in the filename.
So if you miss typed the file name, what should
the program do.
Well when you try and open the file using
the ifstream dot open or using the constructor,
if the file doesn't exist opening that file
will fail.
And we won't get a message back from C++;
we have to check actively on whether that
succeeded or did not succeed.
So there's really no response from the dot
open function, we just make the attempt to
open the file and then it's our responsibility
to use an IF statement to check to see if
opening that file succeeded.
Now we can use a simple bool member function
inside the ifstream class which allows us
to simply say if in file and that's enough
to check to see if the file is open and connected
properly or if it rather if the ifstream object
is open and connected to the file properly;
but if we attempt to open it once and it fails
then who's to say that the second time we
try to open it will succeed.
So the problem of course with an if statement
is that we're only going to check it once,
it's actually better to use a while statement
and put all the code for opening the file
connection inside the while statement because
if the while statement doesn't succeed we
won't continue on.
So doing while in file, as you'll see in just
a minute, is actually a better solution because
it allows us to prohibit continue continuing
the program until the file actually is opened
successfully; whereas, if will only try once
and then whether it succeeds or doesn't succeed
it's going to continue on.
If you are going to try opening the file again
as in a while statement or an if statement
and not just fail out and say we've got a
problem, then you have to understand how the
flags operate inside the if stream object.
When we try to open that file and the file
openings fails then a flag is set up inside
the stream object to tell us that something
has failed.
Now unfortunately with the ifstream object
even if we have a successful opening later,
the flag to tell us that a failure has occurred
will still be set.
So the solution to this is to do a clear inside
the stream object; there's a function called
Dot clear and when we before we attempt the
opening again we're going to call dot clear.
So to just walk you through the process, we'll
try to attempt to open the file once.
If it fails we'll enter into the While statement
to say that it has failed.
Then we can check to see that the file has
failed to open and then we can call clear
to clear the flags and open to open it again.
That way if the file succeeds in opening the
second time than the flags will now be clear
appropriately so.
So we have this multistep process towards
checking how to open a file, and then once
that process is complete we know for sure
that the file is actually open.