Now I'd like to show you how to do some input
from a file.
And so what I've done is create a couple of
sample files here; I'll just show you the
first input file.
And again it's very important these are text-based
files, so if you're creating these files on
a Mac you have to make sure that these are
created as regular text.
If you're creating them on a PC you might
just use notepad; notepad is really easy to
do to create these files and you can just
go and right-click inside the folder and choose
new text documents.
Don't choose word or anything like that because
if you look at a word file it actually contains
quite a bit more formatting information and
that sort of stuff.
We're not going to really care about any formatting;
we're just working with text.
So here I've created a text document with
just a number of integers and what I'd like
to do is create a program, which can read
in and maybe find the average of these integers.
So we'll keep it very, very simple to start
off with.
So the first thing is of course that account
include my fstream again.
I'm going to give you the open input file
function and open input file is going to have
to take into account the fact that the user
might type in the wrong file name.
So it's going to pass in the ifstream object
which an ifstream object we talked about is
a file coming in and when we pass streams
to functions, of course we always pass them
by reference.
So I'm going to pass in my in file, by reference,
to my open input file function and I'll just
create a string for the file name here and
ask the user the file name and I'll read in
its file name.
And then I'll go ahead and open that file
so I'll assume that the in file objects not
opened at this point which makes sense since
that's what we're asking this function to
do.
And we'll give it the file name I haven't
included string here so I can see that these
strings.
We hope that the file name opens but hope
is not enough we're gonna have to verify that
the file actually does open.
So I'm going to write a while loop to see
if the file is open and you ask why it's a
while loop, well because what happens if we
try again and it still fails to open a second
time and a third time and a fourth time.
In fact, you could ask the question how many
times is it necessary to try to open a file
before successful and the answer is we don't
know; we want to continue in this loop till
the file actually opens.
While in file is not open so while a file
is not successful while we have a failure
on any file it can say file fails to open
and then we can ask the user to do the same
process over again: read in in that file name,
and then we can try and open it again, but
before we open it we have to call clear because
what we're testing for is a flag that shows
failure.
And even if we have a success the previous
fail will cause that flag to remain, unless
we’ve called clear so before we open it
again before we attempt to open this file
again we're going to have to clear it that
failure flag and then you can try and open
it on the file.
So it's not exactly the same code as previous
because you have to clear the flags but we
do want to try opening it again and in order
to test it right after that.
We're going to have to make sure that it's
not in a failed state to begin with and then
we can try opening it and see if it's a failed
state.
This function almost becomes wrote because
you can use it over and over and over again
for different projects that you have to work
on, so I’d commit this to memory or at the
very least get used to knowing how this function
works.
And that way when we create an ifstring object
called in file we can use the open input file
function to open that in file and trust that
when it's done that that input file is open.
So now we know that in order to get out of
that function the input file must be open
and ready to read.
From that point we can read in maybe into
an array or a vector the elements of the file,
so I know that these are integers.
I'm going to go ahead and read these into
a vector of integers, so of course I'll pound
vector and then I can have a temporary one
so I want to make sure that I can't read in
into V there's no simple way to do that.
But what I can do is create a temporary object
and read in in a while loop from in file into
the temporary object; now, what this does
is reads in one integer into temp and then
we can process it.
Now if the input operation if the read in
operation is a temp doesn't succeed then we're
not going to continue in the while loop, that
would be a failure and we'd fall out of the
while loop.
So like when the file is done when we've read
in all the information from the file then
the read in operation will fail and we can
go on and do something else, but as long as
we're able to read in an integer then we can
store it in temp and then do something with
that.
And for this we're going to be real simple,
we'll just push that back the push temp back
out to V and then if we want let's say the
average we can take the sum using our for
loop, V sum plus equals the average of the
integers we can do some divided by dot size,
so that tells us a quick average of the items
in the file.
And I've called this input one dot txt very
important in Windows that you show the file
extensions, so if you don't show the file
extensions this is only going to show up as
input one but it's very important that you
recognize the file extensions do actually
exist.
So if all you're seeing is input one and it
says text document then in reality this is
input one dot txt.
I have it showing all the file extensions
for all my files because that's the way I
like it.
I'm going to compile this program I didn't
initialize it.
Yeah, that's right okay.
So I've got to initialize that and then when
I run the program txt.
The average of the integers in the file is
55 so that's an easy way to read in a whole
slew of integers there and you can work on
those integers using a vector or a dynamic
array of some sort.
I'll show you the code just one more time
main and finish the open it