So we understand that now we're going to do
this three step process of skipping leading
whitespace characters, reading invalid characters,
and stopping when we reach trailing whitespace
or an invalid character and the input operator
is going to do that for you automatically;
We just need to know and understand what's
happening internally inside that operator.
So what constitutes a valid character really
depends on the data type that we're trying
to read into.
Remember the operation is something like in
file our temp.
So what's the data type of temp and that really
defines what valid characters are.
Now temp is a string then anything goes any
characters a valid character and we're going
to read in a word at a time if you will, so
effectively if we had a somebodies name on
a line it would read in something like Daniel
and then stop at the space between the first
in the last name.
And then the second read in operation would
read the last name like Katz then that's my
name.
So we need two read in operations to read
that in; that's for strings.
Now what about integers; we can't read in
letters into an integer so a letter would
be constituting an invalid character for an
integer.
Integers can only accept whole numbers.
There's no period a period is an invalid character
if we're expecting to read in is an integer.
But for a double, a period is a valid character
but if we have two periods that second period
constitutes an invalid character.
And for a character, a char the first character
is valid but a second character is invalid.
So whatever the data type is C++, will process
the data type appropriately, will process
the input appropriate for that data type and
its skips over only the invalid characters
rather it's stops when it reads the invalid
characters.