So, we know how to read in one individual
item in the individual string, an individual
int or an individual double, but what happens
if you want to get a whole line of text and
process that whole line of text accordingly.
So, in my previous example of reading in a
name, what happens if the person…
Some people have a name like Daniel Katz and
some people have a name like John J. Jones
that would be two items to read in for one
person and three items to read in for another
person.
We can use the getLine function to get everything
up to the end of the line and that's a really
useful function.
It doesn't skip leading whitespace so this
doesn't work the way that input operator does;
it doesn't skip any leading whitespace.
It captures everything in the line so all
the characters in the line.
And so we reach the return character at the
end of that line and then it stops, and it
does not return the return character.
I know that's a little bit of a strange way
of saying it but the return character at the
end of the line is removed from the stream
and we don't return that into the string.
So the way to call this is just getLine and
we have inFile and myString and what will
happen is from the in files current pointers,
wherever the current position inside in file
is, will read in everything up to and in the
up to and not including the return character
at the end but the return character at the
end would be removed.
So if we put this in a loop, for example,
we could get an array of strings and each
of the strings would not contain a return
character and it would not really skip the
leading whitespace it would include everything
on the line.
So, we have a really nice way of reading entire
lines at a time and then processing them in
memory.
The only thing to take note of is that if
the file pointer is pointing to a return character
then getLine is going to return nothing because
its gonna read a no characters and then throw
away the return character also.
But this is a great way to get a large chunk
of data out of the file when you really don't
know how many whitespace characters there
are, you can just get the whole line or the
rest of the line and then you're set up to
read in on the very next line.