Alright, now I’d like to show what we can
do with something a little bit more complex;
maybe for an input file. We can take a look
at this input file and it has some student
IDs and test scores and names associated with
each other and tab characters in there. And,
let’s imagine that we were given this file
and you can imagine it’s a much bigger file
than it is, but we have guaranteed in column
one student IDs and in column two we have
student test scores and in column three we
have the students name. And what we’d like
to do maybe is order these by test score or
we like to find out all the students who had
a test score higher than 90. So, lets load
this data into a vector inside C++, and then
we can start to work on it. So just keep that
format in mind: student ID on the first column,
test score on the second column, and student
name on the third column. And what I’m gonna
do is create an object; so, now we have the
ability to create an object and I’ll do
this easily, I’ll just do it as a struct.
And here we go: Student and we’ll say that
the integer; we have an ID that’s an integer
we have test score and we have a string that’s
the students name.
So that’s the format of the file and I can
create a vector of students, call that VS.
S now I've got a vector of students and I’m
gonna create one student, again, so this is
going to be my temporary student. Now when
I go to read in, I’ve already opened the
input file using my open input file function
that you saw previously. And I’ll go ahead
and read in into the temp dot ID, and I know
that I’m going to have to do that inside
of a while loop because this is going to happen
over and over and over again. Now once I’ve
done that, I’ve guaranteed that I’ve got
a student. And I know that some of you might
ask the question of what happens if the file
is corrupt; my answer is that if the file
is corrupt you really can’t do anything.
So we’re assuming that the file is complete
and that on every line we have a student ID,
a test score, and a student’s name. So,
if we read in into the ID, we then still have
the additional problem of reading in the student’s
test score and then we have the problem of
the name.
So, now I’ve filled in the temp ID and I’ve
filled in the temp test score, but the problem
is going to be that this name contains multiple
breaks. Now we remember that in a read-in
operation, we read in valid characters and
we stop when we reach trailing white space,
like tab character, or we reach an invalid
character and we’re gonna say that we’re
not gonna reach any invalid characters anywhere
on this file. But how do we go about reading
in an entire name? So we’ve read in, let’s
say, the first student ID, and we’ve read
in the first test score. And the file pointer
is now sitting at this point because it stopped
when it reached trailing white space, and
what we’d like to do is read in this. And
that looks simple; it looks like two names.
The only problem is that if you look carefully
at some of these lines, it’s not two names,
its three or perhaps even more names. But
the problem is that we’re going to have
to read in basically the rest of the line.
So, what I want to do is go ahead and read
in the whole line, starting from the point
where we left of, which was the end of the
test score and going to the end of that line.
And I have a function for doing that; it’s
called getLine. And I can give it the in file
and I can give it temp dot name and it will
read in the rest of the line.
Now I know that getLine seems to describe
that it gets the entire line but in fact getLine
begins reading from the point where you left
off. And that might include that tab character
there; in fact, it probably will include that
tab character. So what we might do instead
is before we do that we can either get the
one character, which is the tab character,
or what we can do is that if we know they’re
tab characters, we can tell it to skip the
tab character by saying inFile dot ignore.
And inFile dot ignore needs first a number
of characters that we’re gonna skip and
we know this is just going to be one character,
but we’ll put in nine thousand nine hundred
and ninety-nine, just for the sake of putting
it in. And it’ll stop when it reaches that
first character that it should ignore. So,
it’ll stop either at ten thousand characters,
nine thousand nine hundred ninety-nine characters,
or it’ll stop when it reaches the first
tab character. And what that’ll do is that
it’ll skip over this tab character and then
getLine will read in the rest of the line.
Of course, I’ve only read into temp and
now it’s necessary to go in and push back
everything onto the vector.
So I’m gonna have push back temp onto the
vector, and when I finish with that I should
be able to write a simple for loop that gets
the student and we can test to see if S test
score, we said greater than 90, and if it
is then we can output the students name. I’m
gonna go ahead and put in a little description
here, and let’s go ahead and run that. Okay.
Looks good. Input two dot TXT. And you can
see that students with test scores over 90
are Daniel Katz, George Washington, and E.
F. Johnson. And if we take a look, that is
correct; it looks correct. We did not have
John H. Jones because John H. Jones was not
over 90, he was 90. But that’s perfect;
that’s exactly what we expected. So, what
we’re doing is we’re reading in the individual
items; so, we’re saying we’ve seen an
ID, once we’ve seen the id we know there
will be a test score, and we know that there
will be a tab character, and we know that
there will be a name. And we don’t know
how many items there are in the name but we’ll
go ahead and grab that and push it back onto
the vector and then once it’s in the vector
we can start working with it. So that’s
an easy way to start working with a lot of
files; files with a lot of data in them. If
you don’t need the getLine, you can just
read in straight into temp ID, temp dot test
score, and stuff like that. You can keep read
in operations, you can tie the read in operations
together. So, you might do something a little
bit more insightful like that; that would
work as well. Okay, you don’t have to but
you could; I like to do it just this way but
whatever works for you, works. So that’s
the way we can read in a large amount of input
information and begin processing it.