There's another function inside the stream
object which is useful, called seekG.
And seekG allows us to move the file pointer
around skipping over characters either forwards
or backwards.
We can also use seekG to move back to the
beginning of the file.
So, if we specify a positive number that moves
us that number of characters ahead in the
file.
If we specify a negative number that takes
us back that number of characters, but if
we specify as zero takes us back to the beginning
of the file.
Now one of the things to take care of here
it with seekG is that if we've reached the
E.O.F. marker, if we’ve reached the end
of file and the file is now what we consider
in a failed state because we read in the end
of file marker, using seekG to send it back
to zero doesn't clear those flags.
So if what your point is, is get once you're
at the end of the file is to move it back
to the beginning of the file, make sure you
call it clear because it's going to clear
those flags also.