One thing that we may want to do, which is
actually very common to do inside programming
and inside the file system, is adding data
to the end of a file.
So you might have seen a log file, you might
have a log file which keeps records of transactions
or you might just want to record a large amount
of information and you don't want to have
to read in the data and then add to the end
of it and write it, out as we've said we would
have to do.
So there is an option inside C++ called appending
and what appending does is leave the contents
of the file alone.
So in the original file, nothing will have
changed and what we do is add on to the end
of the file.
To do this we have a second parameter that's
passed to the open function so when we open
it, we're going to specify the file name first
and then we're going to specify this IOS double
colon APP.
And that's the way to tell C++ any ofstream
object that we don't know that we want to
append to the file and not overwrite it.
If the file doesn't exist, it’s going to
be created and then we’ll add on to the
end of this brand new blank file, so it's
effectively like writing.
If the file doesn't exist, then IOS APP really
has no impact on what happens internally in
the ofstream object.
However if the file does exist, it sort of
does seekG, if you will, to the very end of
the file and then any information that you
write into the file is going to be added on
the end of the file, rather than overwriting
what's existing there.
So, if what we're doing is taking in data
from the user and storing it on the file system;
we might take in some data in one run of the
program, write it out to a new file and then
the second run of the program, we don't want
to overwrite what the user already gave us,
so we'll just append on to the end of the
file.