Files all contain a name and we know that.
But what you might not realize is that files
also contain what's called an extension.
And the extension tells the operating system
whether it's Windows or MacOS or Linux or
you, what might be inside that file and what
program might be useful to look at the information
in that file.
So I'm sure your experience with Doc, DOC,
which is often opened in Microsoft Word, or
DocX which certainly is open in Microsoft
Word.
You might also be familiar with TXT which
is a plain text file that contains no formatting,
it contains no extra information; it's simply
text.
There might be an XLS file.
And all these file extensions serve the purpose
of telling us what program we want to use
to open that file.
So to open the file, you have to know its
complete name.
So we're not going to have a nice graphical
user interface for our programs, at least
not initially, that allows us to select the
file.
Instead we're going to ask you or the user
at the console, to specify the file name;
and the filename includes the extension.
So whereas in Windows you might look at the
files and see file without an extension, in
reality there's probably an extension that
Windows is hiding for you.
So the real filename would be something like
file dot TXT.
In addition we know that the file system is
organized in directories and you might know
these as folders on your operating system.
In reality it's simply a list of files that
are contained inside that directory.
And for simple purposes at least for now until
we get into complex operating systems concerns,
the file exists in just one directory.
And a directory can exist inside of another
directory and so on and so forth; we call
this a hierarchical database, which we'll
talk about later.
If you don't specify a directory when you're
opening a file, then the operating system
assumes that you mean the current directory.
Now the question then becomes what is the
current directory.
And if we're working in Visual Studio and
we try and open up a file then the current
directory is wherever we have stored our dot
CPP file.
If we're running an executable program then
the current directory is most likely where
that executable program is.
So this brings up a little bit of diversity.
If we run the program inside Visual Studio,
it's going to look in the current directory
for any files you want to open and that current
directory is the dot CPP file.
But if we then produce the EXE the executable
program and run it manually through windows
explorer,
it's going to be looking in a different directory
because the EXE and the CPP files are not
in the same place.
So you kind of have to keep track of where
you expect your programs to look for these
files and you have to put them in the right
place.
Now of course if you don't want to do that,
you can specify another directory at least
on Windows you can specify using a backslash.
So you can start at the top of your C drive
and do backslash users backslash your name
backslash so on and so forth and so on and
so forth and you can specify the entire full
path name for that file and then it will open
appropriately.
Most of the time we're not going to be worried
about doing that so we're going to be looking
at the current directory.
And this holds true for Windows it holds true
for MacOS, Linux whatever you're using.
Now the other problem about this is that files
can be locked.
So if a file is in use by one program, it
can't be used by another program at the same
time; and this is to protect the consistency
of the data inside that file.
Now the only exception to that rule is that
if both programs want to read the file as
input, both programs can have access to that
file.
So we have what's called a locking system:
there's a lock to prohibit reading of a file
that's being written to, and that's really
what it amounts to.