To get this to work, first you have to include
fstream.
So we put at the top of any program that we're
going to use files we're going to put pounding
include fstream as you have seen it here.
Once we've done that, we have the ability
to create those objects of type ifstream and
ofstream which is appropriate to the action
that we're going to perform.
And then we have to open the connection to
the file in the file system.
So it's not enough to just create the object,
we have to actually connect that object to
the file in the file system.
Now be very cautious, because opening a file
could fail.
There's a lot of situations which could cause
either an output or an input file to fail
so it's really important that we check that
with an if statement after we've made the
attempt to open the file.
Once the files open the object can be used
for import now put in really the same way
that we've been using the cin and the cout
variables.
We can use the output operator and the input
operator appropriately for whatever the data
type is we're working with, whether we're
doing input or output.
And in reality it works very much the same
way.