When we're going to pass an ifstream or an
ofstream an object to a function, or return
it from a function as we'll see later on.
Those have to be passed or returned by reference.
So the ampersand has to be there.
The reason for that is that the act of writing
to or reading from a file, actually changes
the object.
Specifically, we have inside the file object,
inside the representation, inside C++, we
have a pointer to how far into the file we've
been working with.
So that when we read in, we're always reading
in from where we left off on the last read
in operation.
Now obviously any read in or write out operation
is going to change that file pointer, and
that's an act of changing the object which
means it has to be passed in by reference
or returned by reference from a function.