So C++ makes output relatively easy and it's
not really very difficult.
All we have to do is create one of these ofstream
objects; that's the first step.
So we create the ofstream object and of course
we give it a variable name like out file is
descriptive enough to tell us what that file
is going to be, and then we have to open it.
And when we open it we tell it the full filename
that we want to open as you see here we've
got filename dot TXT.
Or you could also if you wanted to skip the
step of opening it, you could also just use
the constructor for the ofstream class and
pass the filename to the constructor.
Only in very rare instances will opening an
output file fail; but it still could.
For example, you might not have permissions
on the drive to create a file, or the drive
might simply be out of space.
If any of those things happen, we're going
to see how to detect that opening a file has
failed in just a few minutes.
But you should check for that every.
If it's important that the file is going to
open, you should check to make sure that the
file does open.
Now once the files open, you can write to
the output file exactly as you would write
to the screen.
So it's a simple output operation you can
say outfile arrow arrow, or output operator.
And then print out your string or print out
your variable or any capability that you would
have to write it to the screen output to see
out, you have the ability to write it to this
output file.
And it works again very much like printing
to the screen.