So if we do this, we’re going to consider
that we would either use a linked list again
or an array and we'll talk about the performance
differences between those in just a minute.
But what we'll do is we'll add to one end
of the data structure and we’ll remove from
the other end of the data structure.
So, let's say enqueue is going to add to the
end of the list or of the array, and dequeue
is going to remove from the front of the array.
Of course, we can do that backwards doesn't
matter which way we choose, it's a personal
preference thing.
But for the purposes of demonstration we're
going to say that enqueue adds the end and
dequeue removes from the front.
The supplemental functions, of course, we
need to write those and we need to provide
the big three.
And again we'll use whatever STL structures
are available either the vector of the list.
So we don't have to write all these functions
ourselves.