So again we have the breakdown of whether
we use a linked list or whether we use an
array to make the decision on what we should
use of the underlying data storage structure
for our queue.
so if we take a look at the list and we're
breaking it down by function here.
we take a look at the push function and of
course the push function on the list; it's
still going to be constant time.
Now we can say it's going to be constant time
because we're going to have pointers to both
the head in the tail of the list and we're
going to make sure that we can insert at either
the head or the tail for us, for our purposes,
we’ll be inserting a tail and will be popping
from the front but that's overly unimportant.
the array, again, for the push operation sometimes
it's going to be constant time and sometimes
it's going to be linear.
So the problem here is again if we run out
of space in the underlying data structure
of the array, We're going to have to expand
the array and that takes a linear amount of
time.
so we have that trouble still.
Now pop on a list, we've said it's constant
time and that's just removal of a node from
the list, so we're just going to have a simple
delete operation.
but Pop on an array is really problematic,
because we're going to be pushing out to the
end the bottom of the array; it means we have
to remove from the front from the top of the
array. and if we remove the zero element from
the arraign we're going to have to move all
the elements upwards by one.
So ultimately the pop operation is going to
take a linear time and that right there is
incredibly problematic.
We'll come back to that in just a minute.
the top operation on either of them is going
to take constant time, the clear operation
to get on the linked list is going to take
a linear time but the array is going to take
constant time and is empty in size are all
going to take constant time.
So if we come back, circle back to thinking
about that pop operation.
You can tell that on a range of a very large
size we can see that there's going to be a
very big problem because removing that top
element from the array Is going to cause us
to have to shift everything up by one element
inside the array. and that's a very very costly
endeavor so it's going to take us a long time
to do that.
there are mechanisms for dealing with it,
for instance we could record where the start
of the array is instead of assuming that it's
at the zero position but that runs the potential
of wasting space in creating a more circular
array.
so there are mechanisms to dealing with this
but ultimately what I think we're coming to
terms with is that it's easier and more efficient
to store this as a linked list.