So here we have the code for the queue class.
And again, you can see it looks very much
similar to the stack class.
We have the data storage as our private data
members, are only private data member.
It's a linked list of type T, so we have a
templated and we have the enqueue and the
dequeue functions, where we push on to the
back of the linked list and we pop from the
front of the linked list.
Ehe top element just returns again, the iterator,
the dereference of the iterator.
And then the isEmpty, int size and the clear
actually completely unchanged from the stack
versus the queue.
So the fundamental difference here is that
the enqueue function is going to push on to
the back, whereas the dequeue function is
going to pop from the front.
And by doing that we've changed the way that
we're inserting and removing into this list
and that means we go from having a stack to
having a queue.
First in, last out for the stack; first in,
first out for the queue, and that makes all
the difference in the world.