So here we have just a simple sample of how
we would use a queue.
We have a couple of calls to the enqueuer
function; we have values of twenty, fifty,
and thirty.
And when we insert twenty, or when we enqueue
twenty, it's going to be the only thing that's
on the list so it's pointers going to point
to null.
But when we insert fifty, the next pointer
of the twenty node is going to point to fifty,
meaning that twenty is still the head of the
list or the head pointer still points to the
node that stores the twenty.
But the next pointer inside the twenty node
is going to point to fifty, and so to the
same happens when we have the thirty.
When we start to dequeue these objects they
come out in the exact same order as they went
in, which is of course different from the
way that the stack works.
But that's because this is a first in, first
out buffer, instead of the first in, last
out buffer.