So our first data structure we're going to
talk about is a stack and the way that you
can best understand this is if you think about
going to like a buffet at a large restaurant
and at the beginning of the buffet there's
a stack of plates.
And the plates are nice and warm they're recessed
into the table so the only plate that you
can grab is the very top plate in the stack.
So here we have this stack of plates it's
recessed into the table and all you can grab
at is the very top of the stack.
And that's one of the purposes of a stack
you can't access arbitrary information in
the stack.
So once you put things into the stack you
can access only the last thing that's been
put into the stack and then on top of that
when it comes out of the stack you get the
last thing that was put in so this is what's
called a last in first out or first in last
out depending on who you talk to.
Which is abbreviated as either a FILO or a
LIFO or a buffer.
So the point here is that when we put things
into the stack the last item that we inserted
is the first one that's removed from the stack.
Now the functions that we use on a stack are
push and pop and top and those are the common
functions that we use.
Push to put something into the stack pop to
remove that top element from the stack.
We have a couple of supplemental functions
that do other purposes of course like clear
and is empty and size.
You've probably seen these before they're
pretty common clear throws away everything
that's on the stack so if you just want to
throw the whole stack away we can call clear.
is empty tells us if there's anything left
on the stack so it will return true if there
is something at least and size will tell us
how many things there are left on the stack.
So we're going to work with these stacks and
we're going to design how the stack works
in the next slide.