So now we've seen how long each of the functions
are going to take we can make a decision about
whether we would use a list or an array to
do the actual storage underlying stack.
And it's pretty obvious at this point I think
we would make the decision to do a linked
list because we're seeing that we're going
to do a lot of pop operations a lot more pushes
a lot more pop operations than we would the
clear operation.
So it's relatively unlikely to do a clear
as compared to a pop operation.
Remember that the clear just completely dumps
everything whereas the pop operation would
remove one element.
So to that end I think it makes considerably
more sense to choose to use a linked list
as the underlying storage mechanism for the
stack rather than to use the array.
And this is a great analysis that should be
done for most of the data structures or for
most of your programs that you're going to
do make the decision as to whether or not
you want to use A or B and play out the analysis.
So that's just one of the points that I want
to make is is it's not clear immediately whether
we should use an array or list but once we
flesh out what's actually going to happen
on the on the stack you're going to see that
the linked list actually plays out a lot better.
So for this purposes we're going to use the
STL list class we are not going to build it
ourselves.
So that's fine we know how to build a linked
list we did that in a previous module so you
don't have to worry about that.
And the STL list includes all of the big three
and includes all of the features of a linked
list class so we can deal with just the stack
portion.
For our purposes the push function is going
to call just simply push front on the STL
list the pop function will call pop front.
So we're going to push on to the front of
the list and when it comes time to remove
we're going to pop off the front to the list
so we're popping the most recently pushed
element.
The other functions we're just going to map
to the equivalent STL functions.
So there shouldn't be very much code as far
as we're concerned creating this.