So here's the code for the stack and you can
see it fits easily in a couple lines it really
doesn't take up a lot of space.
We have as a private data member we have this
data member called data which were storing
a linked list of T objects.
So we've included the STL list here and you
can see that we're just using that underlying
storage just as a mechanism to create the
stack.
The push function like we said it's just going
to do a push front the pop function is just
going to do a pop front.
So we can push items onto the front of the
linked list and we can remove items from the
from the linked list.
Top just returns the top elements of the linked
list.
Remember the data dot begin is actually an
iterator so we have to dereference it and
that's the first element on the list.
We can assume that there's something on the
list if somebody asked for the top element.
list already so we hope that this isn't going
to deref null or cause any problems there.
For is empty we're just telling C++ to return
the size whether the size is equal to zero
and for the size which return the size.
When it comes time to clear we just simply
call clear on the underlying data structure.
So you can see that the code doesn't really
have a lot of beef to it it's very relatively
easy.
All we're doing is inserting elements on to
the front of the list and we're removing elements
from the front of the list.
We know that both of those functions are constant
time function so insertions on to this stack
are only going to take constant time.
Of course accessing the top element of the
stack is only and it's a constant time in
fact if we take a look very carefully the
only one that's not going to be constant time
is that clear function which will be linear.
But we aren't too concerned about that because
we know that that's not going to happen terribly
often.
So the code is relatively easy to understand
relatively easy to go through.
Take your time taking a look at it and if
we wanted to use this we would understand
that we just have to create a stack and call
push and pop as we see fit.