So now that we've seen how to create the stack.
How do we use the stack or what do we use
the stack for?
Well one of the most fundamental components
of computer science of course as we see is
the compiler and we're using the compiler
extensively for all of our C++ work and there's
a lot of other programming languages that
use compilers.
Compilers have a lot of places where they
use the stack but one of the most fundamental
places is pattern matching.
So that when we have a piece of source code
we want to make sure that for example all
the opening parentheses correspond with all
the closing parentheses and all the opening
curly braces correspond with all the closing
curly braces.
And all the opening square brackets correspond
with all the closing square brackets and it's
not just a matter of counting how many openings
we have and matching it to the equal number
of closings.
It has to be precise so that when we have
an opening it matches with the closing both
in number and in order so that's a really
important factor.
If we have an opening curly brace followed
by an opening parentheses and then we have
a closing curly brace before we have the closing
parentheses we have an invalid syntax there
because we haven't closed the parentheses
before we close the curly brace.
And the easiest way to deal with this is to
create a stack and when we encounter an opening
we can push on the opening symbol on to the
stack.
It's going to be stored there and remember
that because this is the first in last out
buffer what we're looking at on the top of
the stack is the last thing that we inserted.
So if we have an opening parentheses and then
immediately a closing parentheses.
We're going to see that the opening parentheses
matches the closing parentheses.
And it doesn't matter what came before it
or what comes after it.
We have to have that matching opening with
that matching closing.
So what we do is when we find an opening we
push onto the stack and when we find a closing
we compare it to the top of the stack and
if it's a match then we can pop the top of
the stack we can remove that opening element
and say let's go to the next element and see
that the next element matches.
And the next element might be an opening or
might be a closing.
So the stack is used to do the pushes and
the pops to make sure that the last thing
that we see is the first thing that we see
in the in the closing.
There's also a couple more examples of where
we would use stacks for and that is in math
operations it's very difficult to deal with
infix operations using using a programming
language like C++.
So if we have even a simple task like two
plus three times four we recognize from a
math perspective that the three times four
portion has to be done before the two plus
three portion because that's order of operations.
But the computer has a little difficult time
because we're going to be scanning that from
left to right.
So there's a different type of notation that's
called postfix notation and what we can do
is take the operators the plus and the multiply
and we can push them on the stack and there's
a number of different rules about what you
can push on top of something else you can't
push a lower precedence operator on top of
a higher precedence operator.
And then we can order this so that two plus
three times four actually turns out to be
two three four times plus which makes it very
easy for the next thing that we use stacks
for and that's for converting a postfix notation
into an actual value.
We take the two the three and the four and
we push those on to the stack and then when
it comes time to do the multiplication we
pop the last two elements off of the stack
so we have the three times four so that makes
it very easy to do order of operations without
having to worry about infix notation.
We've converted it's postfix notation.
Both of those examples we use stacks in the
conversion we would use the stack to store
operators and in the evaluation we'd use the
stack to store operands would use to store
numbers and when we get done we can push the
number back onto the stack and when we're
completely done with the evaluation the top
number on the stack which should be the only
number on the stack is the actual value.
So we can see that in the examples in later
on in the course but you'll see the infix
to postfix conversion and you'll see postfix
the value of valuation and it's done with
stacks.