So here's a piece of C++ code and I just wanted
to show you how this works when we use a stack.
So we're going to take the code we're going
to parse it character by character.
And what we're doing is we're saying if we
see any parentheses or curly braces or square
brackets we're going to push those onto the
stack of their opening.
And if they're closing we're going to compare
them to the top of the stack make sure it
matches.
So we can see of course is this actually is
an acceptable piece of code of course, we're
going to take first the characters int main
we're just throw them away because they're
not relevant to our discussion.
And we're going to take the parentheses we're
going to push it onto the stack and when we
see the close parentheses, you're going to
discover that on the top of the stack there
is an open parentheses and so that matches
and the open parentheses would then be removed
in the stack would be empty.
We then encounter the opening curly brace
and we'll push that onto the stack.
Some more characters that we just completely
throw away.
And then we have an opening square bracket
which will push on top of the opening curly
brace.
And then we have a closing square brackets
so we throw away the openings square bracket;
more characters that we throw away.
There's an opening curly brace, and we have
two opening curly braces on the stack some
characters that we throw away, and then we
have a closing curly brace.
So we match it with the opening curly brace
that's already on the stack and throw both
of those away.
We throw away all the other characters leading
up to the opening square bracket, and the
opening square brackets pushed on top of the
opening curly brace that's already on the
stack and then we have an opening parentheses,
which gets pushed on top of the stack.
And you'll seen at that point in the compiler
there's an opening curly brace and opening
square bracket and an opening parentheses.
And then we have the closing parentheses so
the opening parentheses comes off the stack.
We have the closing square brackets so the
opening square bracket comes off the stack;
we throw some characters away.
We have the closing curly brace and we throw
away the opening curly brace.
We’re done with the input; the stack Is
empty.
This code is great.
If anything doesn't match up, we can throw
an error and we can actually tell the user
tell the programmer roughly where the error
is.
For example, missing square bracket at line
blah blah blah, and I'm sure you've seen that
in your experience, this is the exact way
that your compiler has generated that error.