As you can see from the images, what we have
here on the top is a spinning hard drive and
you can see that magnetic disk that I was
talking about there.
The head is the component that looks like
a straight line and that one is in what's
known as a parking location right now once
the disk spins up.
It would come off that parking location and
move to different radii along the disk and
that this would just continue spinning along
until the read operation was complete or until
the drive was shut down completely.
So one of the issues that come up with a hard
disk drive is that it does waste a lot of
energy to move that disk physically, so there
is quite a bit of energy savings in in going
with the solid state disk drive, which is
along the bottom, and there's a performance
benefit also for solid state disks.
Unfortunately the downside is with a solid
state disk you get significantly less storage
than with a hard disk drive.