When the desires of the CPU create the instructions
what they're doing is creating what's called
a set of instructions or an instruction set
and these are the set of instructions that
the CPU can perform.
And it's usually a very small set just about
one hundred instructions or so each one represented
by a numeric value and when the CPU receives
a particular instruction it performs that
task that's associated with the instruction.
Now one instruction might actually have multiple
codes associated with it if there are different
variables that are associated with that instruction
but fundamentally we only have a very small
set of instructions and they do limited operations.
And we have to work with the higher level
languages to bring the higher level languages
code down into the machine language code so
that it can actually run on the CPU.