So the brain of the computer is what's known
as the central processing unit or the CPU
and this is where all of the processing, all
of the data processing, all the commands that
we're going to run inside of a computer.
This is where all that is done.
It is a single piece of silicon in the form
of a chip designed and manufactured by a company
like Intel or AMD. or there's a few others
that produce these chips, and this is the
only location in the entire system where code
can actually be run.
Now the code that's going to run here is not
the code that we're going to write, at least
not in the first parts of this course.
The code that we're going to write in the
first part of this course is what's known
as a high level language and the CPU only
runs machine language code.
Machine language code is not easy to write
and we will do something a little bit like
it but it will then convert to machine language
code.
In short machine language codes for machines
and human code is for… higher level code
is for humans.
The CPU operates on a fetch, decode, execute
cycle which we'll talk about in just a little
bit, but it runs this cycle very very quickly
and when it's running this cycle each CPU
has its own set of instructions which it understands.
So the CPU has a language for itself if you
will.
Each CPU really only has a small amount of
memory, there's not a lot of memory inside
the CPU and those are called registers.
And the registers are where we store information
temporarily, in order to do the immediate
processing.
But we only have a few of these registers
so we have to be…
When we're writing machine language code,
we have to be very careful to use them without
wasting the memory.
And the CPU may have a cache memory which
can perform more quickly than main memory,
but it's not really much of a concern for
us because as programmers we don't have a
lot of capability for working with cache memory,
in terms of what's inside the CPU.