So all computers every computer will have
at least one central processing unit and the
central processing unit is the brain of the
computer.
That's where all the real work is done.
Main memory – main memory is where the code
and the data are stored, but main memory has
got to be temporary storage because once we
turn the computer off all of that is lost.
And then because we're going to need some
sort of a permanent storage system, there's
got to be a secondary storage system where
the information is stored permanently.
Of course all computers are going to have
something that relates all those, so that
they can communicate.
Most computers are also going to have a video
graphics controller where images can be rendered
and we can put them on display on a screen.
They'll also probably have a network interface
so that we can communicate on the Internet
or in the local area network.
And then of course they're probably going
to have a peripheral interface which is a
USB or a Thunderbolt, or a Firewire, or a
SCSI.
And all of these components meet the requirements
so that we can bring data into the computer,
we can process that data, and then we can
produce output.
And if you look back at each one of these
individual items that I've mentioned you're
going to see that they either do one thing
or two things: input processing or output
and that's the basic idea.
Most devices inside the computer are either
IO devices or they're processing.