The instructions and all the data has to come
from somewhere.
And in order for the code to be executed it
has to be in a register built into the CPU,
that one that we spoke about called the instruction
register.
So why don't we just load all of the code
directly into the CPU and then run it directly
from there.
The unfortunate fact is that the amount of
memory inside of a CPU is really measured
in bytes.
It's a very small amount of memory.
So it doesn't fit a lot of code in fact we
really only want to store one instruction
directly inside the CPU and the reason that
is because each additional byte of memory
costs a really significant amount of money
to add to each CPU and the manufacturers of
these CPU's like Intel and A.M.D. want to
keep the costs down as much as possible so
we can store everything in registers because
it's just too expensive so what we do is we
create a memory hierarchy whereby each layer
of the hierarchy adds a little bit more space
and costs a little bit less but in addition
it runs a little bit slower.
And we'll see that.