So there's a lot of different ways that computers
can be connected physically.
And we want to take a look at a few of those
in the most popular ones that have come up
with are copper, fiber, and wireless.
The copper is your standard Ethernet cable
or any sort of physical cable that involves
a metallic connection, and that's usually
called copper because it's usually made up
of copper.
Very commonly inside of a copper cable there
might be eight wires, four pairs of cables
and they're twisted together in a form of
an unshielded twisted pair or you might have
heard UTP cable so that's the idea behind
a copper physical connection.
Fiber is an Advent that's come out in the
past thirty years and it's actually where
we transmit information via light on a piece
of glass.
That's a cable but it can transmit with a
lot less attenuation, so we lose a lot less
information in that data transfer via light
and it can go a lot farther distances.
So fiber cables go faster and they travel
longer distances, unfortunately they cost
a lot more too because it's glass.
And then the latest one is wireless, we've
had wireless only for about the past twenty
years and it's certainly taken off.
We see wireless virtually everywhere usually
in the form of a wifi connection which we'll
talk about.
But wifi is only one type of wireless and
we have to understand that there's quite a
few types of wireless including microwave
and a lot of others.
Protocols are in use for a lot of situations,
for example we want to know when we need to
start sending data, we want to know who it's
coming from, we want to know who it's going
to.
In terms of physical connections, the idea
of a protocol is very important because it's
a language, it's a language that two computers
are going to be talking and each of them have
to understand the complete language.
So we need to know, we need to have a very
well defined protocol and thankfully we do.
As far as physical connections are concerned
we can talk about ethernet and ethernet physical
connection would define both the protocol
and the type of connection so we might have
for example one hundred base T, which is a
fast ether net connection better known as
Fast ethernet, that's one hundred megabit
connection of ethernet over copper and it
defines how we would communicate; it defines
when we start sending data, it defines when
we stop sending data, and it defines the format
for information that's being passed over that
network.
So we have a lot of these different protocols
including wifi which you've heard of as the
802.11 group, the 802.11 group is defined
by the IEEE and it has a lot of different
sub working groups for example 802.11B was
the original one that produced eleven megabit
wifi and we've 802.11N, and AC, and there's
a lot of different letters that go associated
with that and then we have ATM which is asynchronous
transfer mode which is used in a lot of backbone
networks for transmission of high capacity
links.
So all of these are our physical types of
connections that we would have to physically
connect to multiple computers to a network.