We have a lot of different types of computers
in use in the environments today as well as
and past history.
So we have this concept of a mainframe which
is a very, very large computer which used
to act for lack of a better term, used to
act as a central point for all the computing
done on a campus.
So for example, one university might have
just one mainframe for each campus in the
entire university and that's where all the
processing was done.
Imagine only having one computer for the entire
university.
It gets very very busy and the time on that
computer is very much in demand.
And then we move to a more common definition
today which is that of a server, and a server
would be something that probably exists in
a data center or in a room dedicated with
air conditioning and power controls.
This would not be used by most people, so
it would have a lot of capability a lot of
RAM a lot of CPU (we will talk about these
definitions later) but the server serves one
purpose.
And a desktop would be used by an end user
at one physical location (obviously) because
you don't want to carry a desktop around too
much.
A laptop we know we just carry it around and
use it just as a regular computer.
A tablet is pretty much the same as a regular
laptop except without a keyboard, and that's
basically what we've come to these days.
And then we could also add that a portable
phone is by definition a computer because
it does take input, do some processing on
that input (your voice), and then encoding
your voice, and then it produces output in
the form of a signal it gets transmitted to
your cell provider.
So all of these are types of computers and
we're going to explore the commonalities between
these computers in just a minute.