So all the communications inside of the machine
the communications between the individual
components are done via a bus.
And a bus is, actually the way that I usually
think about it is a big yellow school bus
moving from one component to the next and
carrying, not children in this case, but information
and the information can move either from one
component to the other or vice versa.
So it's a bidirectional communications pathway
in which we can send information and the bus
is actually something that exists physically
in the system.
So if we put the system under a microscope,
we could see the little copper lines that
go on the mainboard or on the component to
act as the physical bus.
So this is something that we can see physically
on the system if we probably put it under
a microscope because it's rather small, but
the system bus is the main pathway between
the CPU and main memory.
Now IO devices often have access to the system
bus as well for communications both to main
memory and to the CPU but the system bus is
primarily used priority for CPU and main memory
communications back and forth, and that's
what has to be done very very quickly inside
the system.