So the secondary storage can be broken down
into two types, and this is kind of representing
a change in the industry as we are today we're
moving from hard disk drives to solid state
disk drives for a lot of computers.
Now hardest drives are not going away by any
means.
Hard disk drives are also known as spinning
drives and the reason for that is that they
contain magnetic material which is in the
form of a disk and the disk rotates at a constant
velocity, and it's measured in a number of
revolutions per minute.
And that's published by the manufacturer usually
is fifty four hundred RPM or seventy two hundred
RPM or possibly even ten thousand RPM.
The disk rotates and we have a head that moves
in and out along the disk for different radii
on the disk and this allows us to define,
by polar coordinates, a particular radius
with a particular rotation angle and a height
(the head) to indicate a specific point on
the disk where we want to either read or write.
So we can access the entire magnetic material
which is where the real storage happens.
Unfortunately with this system if we move
the head, which has some time that it takes
to move, if we move the head to the innermost
radius and then do a read operation and then
try and move the head to the outermost radius,
it really takes a significant amount of time
in comparison to move in the head to an adjacent
radius.
So what we call the each radius is known as
a track, and it looks like a track if you
were running around in a in a gym.
Each track can hold a certain amount of information
and the tracks are all adjacent to one another
but moving from one track to the next adjacent
track takes a very insignificant amount of
time, I shouldn’t say insignificant, it
still takes an amount of time, but moving
from an inner most track to a very far distant
track will take quite a significant amount
of time.
In addition to that we have this rotation
that happens and on a drive with, for example
a fifty four hundred RPM, we can recognize
that it takes eleven milliseconds to do one
full rotation of the disc.
So if we move the head to the appropriate
location and happen to notice that the sector
that we want to read, the location where we
wanted to read just went past, it's going
to take eleven milliseconds for that to come
around again.
So that could take some significant time,
also.
The benefit to having a hard disk drive is
that the size can be enormous, sizes of four
terabytes six terabytes are not usual today.
So these sizes are really significant amount
of storage space.
The unfortunate downside is that accessing
that storage does take a little bit of extra
time with a solid state disk drive, which
is where a lot of the industry is moving to
for most end user machines.
This solid state destroy don't have anything
that moves, hence the term solid state.
They contain a number of chips which look
just like your USB flash drives, if you ever
happen to accidentally crack one of those
open.
All the data is stored electrically in the
chips and it looks very much like RAM chips,
but the chips are in a very different design,
the chips are designed very differently.
These are store data permanently, so that
even if the power is removed from the chip
the data is still stored which is a great
thing because this is secondary storage and
we don't want to lose the data if the power
is removed.
Thankfully with solid state disk drives, all
the data can be accessed in random time and
they can all be accessed in the same amount
of time.
So accessing the first byte on the drive and
then accessing the last byte on the drive
doesn't take any additional amount of time
other than the first or the second bite.
Unfortunately due to the cost and design of
these drives they're much smaller, so solid
state drive are significantly smaller, they're
a little bit more expensive but hard drives
are larger, and they're cheaper but they perform
slower.
So again we have the memory hierarchy working
here just inside of the term of secondary
storage.
So even inside secondary storage we still
have this concept of a memory hierarchy working.