When we used to make a call on the telephone,
we'd have a physical connection.
A physical connection between your telephone
and the destination telephone and you can
go back to the very, very old days, your parents
and grandparents days, of making telephone
calls.
They used to call the local operator and ask
for a connection to the national operator
and the national operator would connect to
another local operator another local operator
would connect to the destination.
Along this line they would create a physical
channel so one wire that went from the source
phone, your phone, to the destination phone.
That's absolutely not what happens at all
today.
Now we're sending packets.
So today we send small amounts of information,
very, very small amounts of information usually
of around a thousand bytes or fifteen hundred
bytes and the data gets sent from one program
running on a machine to another program but
unfortunately it can't be sent directly, it
has to be sent via protocols which each one
will add a small amount of information to
this packet.
So the way that we send it is buying capsulated
the packet and it's given to the lower level
protocols, so we take the data and we give
it to the next lower level, and then the next
lower level gives it to another lower level,
and the next lower level gives it's another
lower level, so we have a higher key that's
created whereby the data stands at the top.
And then we have a small amount of information
for application protocols added to the front
of that data, and then a network, for example,
layer will add a small amount of data to the
front of that.
Now the purpose of all of this is so that
when it's received on the destination the
destination can decide which for example application
is supposed to receive this information so
we might have for just to use a good example
we might have two tabs of chrome open, or
even we might have chrome and Internet Explorer
open and if we have chrome an Internet Explorer
open and both are browsing the exact same
website at the exact same time when we receive
data back, it's really important for the computer
to be able to route appropriately the response
from the website either to chrome or to Internet
Explorer and we do that via quite a few protocols
which will talk about in just a minute, but
it's important to know that path back.
When the packet moves to the logical protocol
we add a header and so on and so forth until
the data is actually sent on the physical
network.