So at the top of the memory hierarchy you
can see that we have registers and registers
a built regularly into the CPU; there's only
a few of them, the size is measured in bytes.
But the time to access each of those bytes
is measured in nanoseconds and registers are
the only place that instructions can be executed.
So we need to use the registers very sparingly.
We need to be very cautious about how we use
the registers, and in fact in the higher level
languages we're not going to concern ourselves
with how to use the registers.
But when we get down to machine level instructions
we have to be cautious about that.
The next level of the hierarchy is cache,
and in cache we can measure.
There's actually two layers of cache but we
can measure the total in megabytes.
And each of them have nanosecond access times.
Although it is slower than a register it can
help speed up the processing and the CPU does
this automatically in terms of things like
pipelining and bringing in instructions before
they're really needed.
The processor designers take care of the cache
and it's not terribly useful for programmers
there's not a lot that we can do inside the
cache of a CPU.
The next level is probably one of the most
important ones that we have to take care of
and that's RAM.
RAM is measured, of course, in gigabytes,
but it does have a lot slower access time;
this is over ten nanoseconds access time.
So it's a factor of ten slower than the registers.
But it's the only place where we can really
store code and store our data.
We do have to take into account, as I said
before, that RAM is volatile memory.
So once the computer is shut down all the
contents of RAM are erased completely and
that's automatic, it's just by design - the
way the RAM is designed.
But RAM is incredibly useful because that's
where the data is going to come from that's
where the code is going to come from to load
the code into the registers one by one.
Of course if we have temporary storage, we're
going to need some permanent storage because
we don't lose everything every time the computers
shut down.
So the secondary storage devices which have
sizes that may be measured in terabytes have
much slower access times on the order of ten
milliseconds, which if you remember we talked
about RAM is ten nanoseconds that's one times
ten to the negative nine, ten milliseconds
is one times ten to the negative third, so
secondary storage is about a million times
slower than RAM but it's the only permanent
storage device that we have inside the system.
So if we want to save something so that it's
not erased when the power is lost on the computer,
the secondary storage is where we have to
store.
Secondary storage is usually in the form of
a hard drive or a more modern solid state
disk drive, but we use it for the permanent
storage of the system.
Thankfully this is where the operating system
comes from this is where your code comes from
when it starts off and then it's loaded into
RAM, of course so that it can execute.
But this is where we store just about everything
on the system.
Tertiary storage is a term that we use for
offline storage and these are things like
your USB, flash drives, a CD-ROM drives, if
anybody still uses those, possibly even tape
drives, if we're talking about a server.
These have sizes that can be left to your
imagination and we can talk about offline
storage in the form of petabytes and possibly
even exabytes.
This is used for backup and it's used for
information that doesn't need to be immediately
accessible.
You can imagine that the time it takes to
load a tape would certainly be significant
if we were talking about it in comparison
to in ten millisecond access time but that's
the idea behind the memory hierarchy as we're
working at the top things are faster but significantly
smaller and much more costly as we're working
at the bottom things are much much slower
but more larger and much less cost much cheaper.