The next cache associativity we will discuss
is full associativity.
In a fully-associative cache, a D RAM block
can go into any cache block that is unoccupied.
In the figure, the blue D RAM block can go
to any cache block that currently doesn’t
have data or instruction.
So the fully-associative cache is the opposite
of direct map.
It tries to keep the content in the cache
for as long as possible by allowing it to
be put anywhere that is free.
Therefore, fully-associative cache has very
good temporal locality.
However, since the data or instruction can
be anywhere in the cache, we may have to look
to the whole cache to find it.
If we look at the cache as an array of blocks,
it may take several cycles to get the data
or instructions, leading to more access delay.