So we see how the two extremes of cache associativity
work.
What we want to do is to get the best from
both extremes.
This is where set associativity comes in.
In a set associative cache, the cache is broken
down into sets of N equal blocks.
In the figure we have here, the cache is broken
down into sets of 2 blocks.
The idea is to make the cache direct-mapped
with respect to the sets, but fully associative
within a given set.
Here is what we mean; each DRAM block can
only go to a specific cache set.
For example, the D RAM blocks in blue can
only go the set 0 of the cache, and all D
RAM blocks in yellow can only go cache set
1.
In this respect, the cache is direct-mapped
with respect to which set the D RAM blocks
can go to.
However, within a set, a D RAM block can go
to any free cache block of that set.
For example, with 2 blocks in each set, a
blue D RAM block can go to any block that
is free in set 0.
Similarly, a yellow D RAM block can go to
any block in set 1.
So with this hybrid design, the set associativity
principle attempts to find the middle ground
between direct mapped and fully-associative.
Though we use 2 blocks per set in our example,
this number can be different.
Usually, a set-associative cache in modern
processors has 4 or 8 blocks per set.
The general label for a set associative cache
is N-way set associative, where N is the number
of blocks per set.