The next aspect of cache design we will look
at is the write policy.
Though cache policy has some impact on temporal
locality, it is primarily done to synchronize
the data in the cache with that in main memory.
For example, when we have a store instruction,
do we write the data in the cache only, in
the D RAM only, or in both?
The decision on which to select depends on
the bandwidth limitations of the memory, the
amount of energy it takes to write to memory,
and who else needs the data.
For example, if we have a processor for a
low-power device like a smartphone.
Its memory is likely to have limited bandwidth,
so it may take a lot of time and energy to
always write to the D RAM for every store
instruction.
However, if the data that we are writing needs
to be used by a co-processor like a graphics
processor, then it is best to have it in D
RAM where the co-processor can access it.
There are two common write policies: write-through
and write-back.
The basic idea of write-through is to write
the data both to cache and the D RAM on a
store instruction.
This keeps both the cache and D RAM synchronized
but consumes more energy.
In write-back cache, the data is written to
the cache only on a store instruction.
The data is not written into the D RAM until
the cache block has to be evicted according
to its replacement policy.