If it worth emphasizing the write-back policy
of a cache and the write-back stage of a CPU
pipeline.
The write-back policy of a cache deals with
synchronizing data between the cache and the
D RAM.
Whereas, the write-back stage of a CPU is
for writing registers at the end of instruction
execution.
So how is the data in the write-back cache
synchronized with the DRAM?
The Write-Back policy synchronizes the DRAM
when it has to evict the cache block that
a store instruction was performed on.
Let us take a look at an example.
Assume we have 2-way set associative LRU cache
with the write-back policy.
Each block of a write-back cache has what
we call a dirty bit.
The role of the dirty bit is to indicate that
a store instruction has been performed on
the block.
So on a store instruction, the data is written
into the cache block only and the dirty bit
for that cache block is set to one.
In addition, the age bits of the block are
updated to reflect the current time.
So in our example, the last block of the cache
is being written to on the store instruction.
Later in the execution, a new D RAM block
needs to be brought into the cache.
Since the cache uses a 2-way set associative
policy, we go to the set only set that the
new DR AM block can be moved to.
The new D RAM block is yellow, so it can only
go to set 1 in the cache.
The cache controller realizes that all blocks
in the set are occupied, so one of them must
be evicted.
Since the cache replacement policy is LRU,
the cache controller looks at the age bits
of the two blocks in set 1.
The last block is the oldest and thus must
be evicted.
Before evicting it, the cache controller checks
its dirty bit.
If the dirty bit is one, this means that a
store instruction was performed on that block
and the DRAM doesn’t have the new data.
So the cache controller writes the data of
that block in the DRAM to updated the DRAM
and clears the dirty bit.
Then, the new block can be brought in that
cache.
In this example here, the content of the dirty
cache block is written to the D RAM to synchronize
it and the dirty bit for that cache is clear.
At this point, the D RAM has the must up to
date information for the block.
Then the new DRAM block is brought in the
recently evicted cache block and its age bits
are updated to reflect the current time.