So far, we have assumed that every memory
access that the CPU makes takes one clock
cycle.
That is, each time an instruction is fetched,
or a data is written to or read from memory,
it only requires one cycle.
However, in reality, each memory access takes
several cycles.
This is because of two reasons.
The first and most important reason is that
main memory is generally implemented as DRAM,
which stands for dynamic random access memory.
In this instance, dynamic means that the data
needs to be refreshed from time to time, in
order to keep it available in memory.
This refreshing delays the access time of
data because it may need to be refreshed before
it is brought to the CPU.
The second reason is that the main memory
is so large, usually in the gigabyte range,
that it has to be put off the CPU chip, causing
it to run at a lower frequency than the CPU
itself.
Therefore, the main memory is running at a
slower speed than the CPU, causing additional
delays.
In many cases, access to main memory can take
as many as 100 cycles for each access.
Therefore, if we consider a simple pipelined
CPU, each instruction fetch stage requires
100 cycles.
Similarly, each memory stage where the instruction
reads from memory or writes to memory also
requires 100 cycles.
In this small example, we can see how the
execution time goes from 7 to at least 700
cycles when we consider the real access delay
of memory.