So this is a generalized view of the memory
hierarchy that incorporates the cache.
This memory hierarchy is representative of
the hierarchy found in a typical laptop.
So the idea is the following: starting from
the bottom of the triangle, the higher you
go, the less is the access delay, but the
smaller the memory gets.
Therefore, we get a trade-off between speed
and size of the memory.
At the lowest level, we have the hard disk,
which is nowadays in the range of terabytes
and takes millions of cycles to access.
To put it in perspective, if we have a standard
laptop, it takes 0.5 milliseconds to access
the disk, which is pretty slow by processor
performance standards.
At the next level, we have the main memory,
which can up to 8 gigabyte of DRAM nowadays.
A typical access to DRAM takes several thousands
of cycles.
Next we have the caches, which are divided
as levels.
Typically, the processor of a laptop has two
levels of caches: Level 2 or L2 is usually
in the range of 128 kilobyte to 2 megabyte,
can be implemented on the CPU chip or off,
and can take up to 12 cycles to access.
Level 1 cache or L1 cache is on the same chip
as the CPU.
An L1 cache can range between 2 kilobyte and
32 kilobytes can take between 1 and 4 cycles
to access.
In most processors, there are two level one
caches, and instruction level 1 cache that
is used for the instruction fetches of the
CPU pipeline, and a data level 1 cache that
is for the memory stage of the pipeline.
The upmost level of the memory hierarchy is
the general-purpose registers, which are part
of the CPU and take one cycle to access
So with this illustration, we can imagine
how instructions are moved across the different
levels of the memory hierarchy.
When we start an application, its binary and
its static data are copied from the hard disk
to the main memory.
When the application starts executing, code
and data are copied from the main memory to
the caches.
But since the caches are significantly smaller
than the main memory, data and instructions
have to be moved back and forth between the
caches and main memory in order get the correct
ones in the cache for execution