So now let us look at how caches are organized
and how data and instructions are moved from
the main memory to the cache.
Let us first go over some basics.
First, the main memory is organized into blocks,
each block being of the same size.
The CPU designer can configure the memory
blocks to be 16, 32, or 64 bytes.
Each cache in the CPU is also organized into
blocks that are the same sizes as the main
memory blocks.
But since the size of a cache is much smaller
than that of the main memory, there are significantly
less cache blocks than there are main memory
blocks.
For example, if we have a memory hierarchy
with 16-byte blocks, a 2 gigabyte main memory
will have over 1 million blocks, whereas a
32 kilobyte cache has a little bit more than
2 thousand blocks.
So the key question is how does the CPU move
data and instructions between the caches and
the main memory?