So let us discuss cache associativity.
Cache associativity dictates where in the
cache can a DRAM block be copied into.
Associativity is the main factor that determines
the trade-off between temporal locality and
access time of the data in the cache.
There are generally three associativity methods:
one is direct mapped, the other is fully associative,
and the last one is set associative
In a direct map cache, there is a one-to-one
mapping between the cache blocks and the D
RAM blocks.
In other words, a D RAM block can be moved
to only one specific cache block.
We use this color coding to indicate direct
mapping.
Blue blocks in the D RAM can only go the one
blue block in the cache.
Yellow blocks in the D RAM can only go the
yellow block in the cache, so on and so forth.
The main benefit of the direct map cache is
it is easier and faster to search the cache.
This is because, since a D RAM block can be
moved to only one specific cache block, we
can directly go to the exact cache block to
look for the data.
Usually, the way that is done is by using
the index number of the cache block.
In this example we have here, when searching
for the instruction or data in a D RAM block
0 or 4, the cache controller simply goes to
cache block 0 to get the instruction or data
because that is the only place in the cache
that D RAM blue blocks can go to in the cache.
However, direct map doesn’t provide good
temporal locality.
This is because the blue cache block may have
to be evicted several times if another blue
D RAM block needs to be brought onto the cache.
When we say eviction we essentially mean that
cache block has to overwritten or replaced
with new content coming from the D RAM.
Since direct map only allows one location
to put all the blue D RAM blocks, if the blue
cache block is busy, then we have to kick
the current content of the blue cache block
out.
If we end up needing it again, we have to
go back to the D RAM to get, causing more
delay.
In summary, direct mapping provides very good
access speed because it is easy to search,
but has bad temporal locality.