So now that we've got the idea of a process
down, let's make it a little bit more complex.
Because while a simple program might be running
one cohesive execution cycle, or execution
unit, the idea of having a large program run
as only one execution thread just doesn't
make sense anymore.
So, it was invented and we now use this concept
known as a thread.
Now we recognize that there are still going
to be processes in the system, but the idea,
the definition of a process, will doubt change
to mean a unit of resource ownership.
The idea of a process now no longer means
an execution path, we're now talking about
a unit of resource ownership.
So, all the files that are open inside the
process, all the memory that's owned by the
process, all the IO devices for the process,
all of that that can be owned is owned by
the process.
But there's no real execution happening in
the process, and what I mean by that is the
execution is offloaded to a concept known
as a thread.
So, the process becomes the unit of resource
ownership but the thread becomes the unit
of execution.
And we might have multiple threads that run
inside a single process and each thread has
its own code.
Although the code is memory and the memory
is owned by the process.
So, there might be multiple threads that are
running the same code, or the threads might
be running different code.
All the threads inside a process share all
the resources of the process and that includes
all the memory, so threads can share the same
memory unlike processes; processes can't share
memory they're restricted because they're
in user mode.
But threads all exist inside of a process
and the operating system is going to recognize
that multiple threads are running inside a
process, and it's going to be able to execute
any one of the individual threads inside the
process.