So, if we now modify the definition of a process,
we need to change where things are stored
inside that process.
So if we take a look, the PCB still has most
of the stuff that we would recognize: the
memory allocation, all the memory and IO tables,
all the files all the linkages, all that stuff.
But the thread now needs to keep track of
some of the thread specific things like the
context, the stack, the variables that are
specific to that thread.
All of that needs to be offloaded outside
of the PCB and inside maybe a TCB, a thread
control block, to keep track of each of the
individual threads.
Now the fun part about threads is that they
all have access to the resources, the memory
and all the rest of the stuff, from the process,
and that means that we have a great level
of communication between all the threads inside
of a process.
But the process needs to recognize, or the
threads really need to recognize that they
exist inside of a process and there are some
concurrency issues that come up in relation
to that.
Now what about your old programs, like your
‘Hello World’ programs that you've written
for previous modules, do they have threads?
Well they did; they had one thread, the main
thread and that main thread could have, although
it didn't create other threads to do other
tasks each individual task inside the system
can be or inside the process rather, can be
handled by one thread and each of the threads
do their own sort of work.
But they all work together on one project
one process and they all share the materials
of that process.