I'd like to take a look at some reasons why
we would use multithreading, and some of these
are rather obvious and you're to see them
in in your regular day to day use of your
computer.
Sometimes you might have foreground and background
activity; the perfect example I love to use
is Microsoft Word, because it's one that we've
all used a million times.
And Microsoft Word is broken down into a really
large number of threads, but just the few
that we might pay attention to are that we
might have a thread that's taking in input
from the keyboard, and it takes in whatever
the user types and it stores it in main memory
in what we would call a document.
And there's another thread that takes the
that main memory from the document and puts
it onto the screen; print it in the appropriate
way, formats it, makes it look nice based
on the font.
And then there might be another thread that
goes through and checks the document and underlines
everything in green or red according to whether
or not it's spelled correctly.
And then another thread that goes through
and checks the grammar.
And then we might have another thread that
sits in the background and waits for ten minutes,
and when that ten minute timer is up that
thread will save the document in some temporary
location just in case your computer loses
power.
So, there's a lot of foreground and background
activity that's happening inside something
like Microsoft Word.
We might also look at Microsoft Excel, because
it's another one that we've used quite frequently.
And the act of changing one cell inside Microsoft
Excel can cause a cascading change throughout
the entire spreadsheet when that one cell
changes there's threads that go out and change
all the other threads that are related to,
all the other cells, that are related to that
one cell.
So, then again there's a lot of foreground
background activity.
There's asynchronous in synchronous processing.
So, if processing has to be done or if processing
can be done synchronously we can create multiple
threads to deal with the synchronous processing.
So, if we have a very large data set and we'd
like to process portions of it separately,
we can process those portions separately using
multiple threads.
And a block that happens in one thread will
not obscure the other thread from running.
We might also have asynchronous processing,
where the threads need to do some sort of
work cohesively so that when one thread ends
the next thread begins.
We might have infrequent tasks, where one
thread doesn't run very often; as my example
of Microsoft Word and the saving every ten
minutes is an example of infrequent tasks.
Speed reading, here we have a problem where
each thread that does a read operation on
the file system is going to be blocked because
that's going to take a very long time, so
the operating system is going to block that
thread.
Now the interesting part about threads is
that blocking one thread, doesn't block the
rest of the threads in the same process.
So, we can have one thread whose responsibility
it is to read all the data from the file system
and bring it into main memory, and another
thread whose responsibility it is to process
that data, and this is called Speed Reading.
So, we're pausing only to deal with the IO
operation but at the same time when the IO
operation is causing us to pause, we're continuing
to process data that's already been brought
in.
And then it also creates a more modular program
structure where we can break down a larger
program into smaller portions and we can deal
with each of the portions independently, as
if they were basically their own program.
But they're still working on one goal which
is to deal with this memory or to deal with
this process as a whole.