Here we have an example of a file server.
and the file server does some sort of an IO
operation for eighty percent of its time.
So, what this is we’ll take in a request
for some file, and then we’ll process that
request, whatever that means, and then we’ll
go off and receive the file, recover the file
from them from the secondary storage device,
and return it to the requester.
So, you might think of this is like an old
1990’s style HTTP web server so we take
the request, we process the request; that's
going to take let's say about two milliseconds.
And then we'll deal with the IO operation
of actually recovering the file from a secondary
storage device and returning it to the to
the requester, which maybe takes eight milliseconds.
So, in total the processing time takes ten
milliseconds.
And that's just a perfect example; we've got
an IO operation that takes eighty percent.
If we do this without threats, we do this
with just one process that means we've peaked
out, we've maximized, our utilization at one
hundred transactions per second; each transaction
is going to take us ten milliseconds and of
course there's a thousand milliseconds in
a second, so thousand divided by ten means
we can get one hundred of these transactions
in a single second.
But let's take a look if we add in the idea
of threads, and let's create a thread for
each transaction.
When we do that, we can now synchronously
process the CPU and the IO operation.
In other words, if we created two threads,
then the first thread’s CPU could be done
while the second thread was doing an IO operation.
And then the second thread could do its CPU
time while the first thread is doing the IO
operation.
So, we can sort of go back and forth using
the CPU as much as we can and using the IO
completely.
Now if we do this, we recognize that the IO
can't be done synchronously; we have to we
have to do that asynchronously.
We have to do that so that one IO operation
is completed and then the next IO operation
can start.
The IO device can run multiple requests at
the same time, so we can service multiple
requests at the same time, that means we have
to do it asynchronously.
Well what that means is that we have these
little eight second eight millisecond blocks
that were chopping up this one thousand millisecond
second into these eight millisecond blocks,
and that means we can use only one hundred
twenty-five transactions per second.
Now that doesn't mean we're not doing the
CPU time, of course we're still doing that
two milliseconds of CPU time, but it means
that we're doing it while the IO operation
is happening for one of the other threads
for the other thread.
So, ultimately we've increased our capability
by twenty-five percent, because what we've
effectively done is hidden the CPU time behind
the IO delay, and that works out great.
But we can actually do better because in this
example of a web server, it's pretty obvious
that a lot of the requests are going to come
in to the exact same file; they're going to
be for the exact same file.
And if we're dealing with each request independently,
then the CPU time and the IO delay don't result
in any cache; they don't result in anything
being retained for the next request.
But if we can keep track of each of the requests
and when we bring in a file, we store that
file in main memory, then in the next request
we don't have to do the IO operation; we can
avoid doing that eight milliseconds, that
expensive IO operation, we can completely
avoid that by recovering the file directly
from the cache.
So, this is one of the benefits of threads
that were exploiting by having a shared memory
space, which you can't do with processes;
a shared memory space where we can store these
files temporarily.
Now at some point if we don't ever need the
file, we have to throw it out of the cache
and if we use up too much memory, we may have
to throw away some of the files that aren't
being used very often.
So, there's an extra bit of processing, but
even if we increase the processing time by
twenty-five percent and increase it then say,
do two and a half milliseconds of CPU time,
the benefit here is that we're decreasing
the amount of IO delay.
Now, let's say for example we get seventy-five
percent hit rate on the cache; now that's
abnormally high granted, but it's possible,
if we have a web server that's popularly serving
one web page.
When that happens, we recognize that the IO
delay drops to zero for those seventy-five
percent of the operations of the transactions,
the IO delay will drop to zero.
Now the twenty five percent that remains we're
still going to have to do that eight milliseconds
of IO delay, and unfortunately now we've wasted
an additional half a millisecond for the CPU
time to sort of look into the cache and realize
that it's not even there.
So, this extends that, but it reduces the
overall time because now on average we're
going to have two and a half milliseconds
of IO delay for every transaction but then,
correction two and a half milliseconds of
CPU delay for every transaction, but the IO
delay is reduced to only two milliseconds
for every transaction.
And it's not really two milliseconds for every
transaction, it's eight milliseconds for those
transactions that we have to do the IO delay,
but that's only seventy-five percent of the
time.
So, we can say that on average each transaction
uses two milliseconds of IO delay, so with
two and a half milliseconds of CPU and two
milliseconds of IO delay, we have four and
a half milliseconds total and that means that
we can get four hundred transactions in a
single second.
So, we've gone from one hundred transactions
in a second to now four hundred transactions
in a second just by implementing threads and
creating a cache and getting a pretty good
cache hit rate, but it's possible.
If we want to put some money into the problem,
maybe we can add a second processor and set
up symmetric multiprocessing so that that
CPU delay can be done concurrently, in which
case the only slowdown here is the IO operation.
We’re IO bound, meaning that we still have
those two milliseconds of IO delay that we
can't get rid of, and that two milliseconds
means that we're kind of limited at five hundred
transactions per second.
But with a very small investment, we can go
from one hundred transactions per second to
five hundred transactions per second, and
with no investment at all we can go from one
hundred to four hundred transactions per second
just by implementing threads.