So, if we take a look at the concept of a
thread now, we recognize that the thread really
only has three states.
It has ready, it has running, and it has blocked,
and all of those makes sense in the same concept
that we talked about them in the process level
notion.
A thread can be ready, meaning it has everything
it needs to in order to run it's just waiting
for a processor.
It has running, meaning it's actually on the
processor and doing some work, and it has
block, meaning it's waiting for something
to happen.
Threads don't really have a new and an exit
state, because we don't need to load code.
For example, our old example of loading the
code and that was why we needed the new state,
we don't have that anymore because the thread
already has all of its code loaded in main
memory.
We're just creating a new thread and how does
a new thread get created?
Well the operating system creates a TCB to
recognize this thread, initializes the linkages
initializes the TCB, and then it starts to
run.
So, it's really an atomic element creating
a new thread can be done atomically, and the
thread just begins running inside the context
of the process.
So, we don't need a new state and likewise,
we don't even exit state because when a thread
completes there's nothing returned back to
the running process; the thread just records
that it's done.
Now obviously, if it's the last thread or
the main thread, if you would, then that needs
to be returned back so we still have the concept
of new and exit state in the idea of a process,
but in the idea of a thread the new and the
exit state aren't really there anymore.
Likewise, the idea of suspension is really
a process level concept; if we've removed
all of the main memory the none of the threads
are able to run.
So in suspension, we have to recognize that
all of the threads have been blocked or all
the threads have been stopped altogether.
But at the same time, there's no real recognition
of the suspended state inside of a thread;
that's more of a process level concept.