So we've talked about the upsides of threads
and we certainly understand how threads can
be great, but of course there's got to be
some sort of a downside.
And what's the downside?
Well the biggest one is that all the threads
have access to the same memory of the process;
well that was an upside too, wasn’t it?
The biggest issue here is that we have concurrency
problems; that if all the threads are trying
to access the same memory that of the process,
then it is possible that the threads could
interfere with one another, unintentionally.
And there's a lot of examples of this and
we’ll go over some of the concurrency examples
in the next module, but ultimately what we're
looking at is that whenever a thread is accessing
memory or it really any resource that's common
to the process, it needs to do so very carefully
and it needs to keep track of where it is
inside the execution cycle.
Usually what we do with this is some sort
of a mutual exclusion lock, or a some or for
to indicate the thread is in execution and
maybe has been stopped.
Now why was it stopped?
Well could be any of the reasons that we talked
about for a context switch.
So, any time we could switch a process, we
could also switch a thread; so, from one running
thread to the other.
And unfortunately, if the thread is making
some changes to the memory, it might not be
complete with all of the changes; it might
do only half of the changes leaving that memory
in a really inconsistent state, and that's
one of the concepts that we know of as concurrency.
This is what we call concurrency.
The other problem of course is deadlock, but
deadlock can happen as well in processes and
we will talk about deadlocks in a later module.
The other problem that we have with threads
is that programmers really like them, so they
create a lot of threads.
And if we create too many threads we lose
track, or it's very easy to lose track I should
say, of what each thread is doing and that
causes a lot of confusion.
And two threads might interact with each other
in a way that we didn't really intend because
we're not being careful with how many threads
we're creating.