So, the process is made up of the code, data
and context.
And we're talking about the process being
a running program in a system state, and we're
gonna talk about what system states mean,
in detail, in the next topic.
But for now, we'll simply say that when the
program starts, it has to have all the information
that it needs in order to run; specifically,
the code as well as any data it may need initially.
And then the operating system needs to keep
track of a lot of information about the running
program, and that's what we're gonna call
that the context.
The code all has to be run in sequential memory;
you know this, you've done some programming.
You've done quite a bit of programming and
you're gonna have to recognize that the code
starts from point one and proceeds sequentially
through the entire program.
And so that code needs to be loaded into sequential
memory.
The process is a way for the operating system
to keep track of the state of the running
program, and the resources assigned to that
running program.