So, the operating system is going to need
to record quite a bit of information about
the process and in total the process is going
to be stored in what we know as a process
image.
The operating system will keep a table known
as the process table with pointers to the
various process images for those processes
that are running inside the system.
And one of the components that are in the
process image is what's known as the PCB,
or in some cases you might consider the PCB
to be the actual process image.
It includes all the information that the operating
system needs in order to run and manage the
process.
So, the PCB is a really critical component
of the operating system; it's usually implemented
as a simple struct with quite a bit of information.
So, what's in there?
Well we've got memory tables; we've got what's
allocated to the process.
We've got what secondary storage is allocated
to the process.
We've got IO tables, which are what devices
the process has access to and where it is
inside those devices.
We've got file tables with all the file handles,
so anytime we opened a file in our previous
programs that we create an entry in the file
table and that was stored inside the PCB in
the process image.
And then we've got stack pointers, and all
of these components make up the process image,
which includes all the code data and of course
this is the context.