One of the other components that the operating
system needs to keep track of is what mode
a process might be in.
And what we're really talking about here is
what processor mode the process could be using.
For the most part processes are going to use
user mode, and that's normal, but in certain
instances a process may have to be created
that has more permissions, to access more
parts of the system then a user mode would
be allowed to access.
User mode has a lot of restrictions; it's
not allowed to directly access system hardware,
it's not allowed to access main memory outside
of its own bounds.
So, the operating system keeps track of what
processes are in user mode, and what processes
are in kernel mode and there are very few
that are in kernel mode.
Now let's be clear kernel mode has absolutely
no restrictions; you can do absolutely anything
that the system can do when in kernel mode
and kernel mode should really be restricted
to only those processes that need kernel mode.
In years past kernel mode was allowed for
almost any process that was running on the
system, and if you survived or use computers
through the late 90's and early 2000’s you
know how dangerous that was.
The era of Windows 98 and Windows ME constantly
crashing and blue screening and the power
switch solution to that was partly a result
of having every process access to kernel mode.
Now we have a much better solution: we use
user mode only for those for those processes
that are going to not need kernel mode.
And the processor knows the difference between
user mode in kernel mode as a result of one
register.
In the Intel architecture, we call this the
program status word register the PSW, and
that one register has one bit to indicate
whether it's in user mode or in kernel mode.
Switching between the modes is easy if you're
going from kernel mode to user mode because
you simply modify the register for the program
status word and it changes into user mode
from kernel mode.
But switching back from user mode to kernel
mode is a bit more difficult.
For this the processor, itself needs to recognize
when the operating system is going to run
and it needs to move back into kernel mode
automatically, by itself.
And we’ll talk about when this happens there
are certain events that occur that cause the
processor to move back into kernel mode and
when that happens, of course, the processor
is going to switch to running the operating
system.