Hi there, hoping you're having a great day.
Today we're going to talk about position and
number systems, and we're all used to working
with the decimal number system.
We're going to see some other number systems
today and see how we can generalize the way
we work with a decimal number system to work
with some other kinds of number systems.
But before we do that, let's talk, let's say
a few words about a memory of a presentation.
So we know that our memory basically is made
out of bits that are grouped into a bytes,
each one of these bits physically is made
with electricity flow or a magnetic field.
But we like to think of it abstractly as zero
and one because it only has two states.
We would need to figure out how to represent
a lot of data using only this kind of a primitive
unit.
So we can think that for example numbers can
be represented using the binary number system,
we'll talk about it in much more detail soon.
But the idea is to represent not only numbers,
but other kinds of data is as well.
For example text, if we write a document or
an email.
How is that represented using zeros and ones
and not symbols as the alphabet symbols?
Images; how do were present images with all
the colors and details with the zeros and
ones?
How do we represent videos, or how do we represent
audio?
All of that should be represented using only
zeros and ones.
So the key idea here is that everything would
be represented as a number, and in a few minutes
we see how we represent numbers, but first
let's see that all kinds of data can be transformed
into numbers, for example text.
We have a mapping for each letter, for each
symbol in our alphabet into a number.
So if we want to take the text, for example
“Hello world!” we can use this mapping.
For example, the upper case “H” would
be 72.
So we start with 72 and then the lowercase,
“e” is 101, so we have 101, and then lowercase
“l” is 108.
So we have two 108’s and so on.
Every character has its own mapped number,
and we have a sequence of numbers to represent
basically a text or a sentence.
Not only letters, but also a symbol, such
as space or a question mark.
Every symbol has its own a number that its
mapped to, so text also is mapped into numbers.
Images are a bit more tricky.
Let's say we have a beautiful image that we
want to represent with numbers.
So you know that images is a very dense matrix
of pixels: each small pixel has its own unique
color and then a color can also be represented
using numbers.
To represent a color, a common way to do that
is using an R.G.B., a representation basically
the amount of red, green, and blue.
Each one ranges 0 to 255.
So for example, this purple here is 120 red,
100 green, and 200 blue.
The Pink has other values of R G. and B. and
so on.
So basically, each pixel has three numbers
that represent its color and then the entire
picture would be a very, very long sequence
of numbers that represent the level of each
color.
Videos are basically a sequence of images,
so if we know how to represent images with
numbers, obviously we can represent videos
with numbers.
Audio also can be represented with numbers.
If we sample the audio wave at a very high
rate of times, we can see the voltage level
in each point of time that is also a number.
So basically, all our data is first transformed
into numbers.
Numbers can be represented with the zeros
and ones, we see that in a few minutes.
And therefore, all our data in our memory
is then represented with the zeros and ones.
Let's go ahead and see how we can represent
numbers with zeros and ones.