We’ll talk about the binary number system
in much more detail in a few minutes. But
let's take a look at another very important
number system: the hexadecimal number system.
which is also called the base sixteen. Let's
start counting in base sixteen this time.
So zero, one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, after nine. So now we
have a problem, because we are still not supposed
to group the ones to a ten at this stage,
right we are grouping only sixteen ones to
hexadecimal ten but we don't have any more
digits anymore symbols to use for a single
digit number. So, when we worked with the
number systems that are less than ten, I don't
know, the octave, the binary, we just used
a subset of the digits zero to nine. For the
octal, we use zero to seven. For binary, we
use zero to nine. But, now that we have a
bigger number system, in this case base sixteen,
we need additional symbols.
So, the common symbols for basics in common
digits for basic things is zero to nine, which
are the first ten digits we use anyway. And
then we need five more, that would be the
first five letters in the English alphabet
A.B.C. D. E. and F.. So after nine, instead
of grouping together and moving to the next
position, we still have a single digit number
represents the quantity of ten. That is A
and then we have B. C. D. E. and F. which
represents the amount of fifteen object, see
still a single digit number, and then the
sixteenth object would be grouped into a single
ten and the next position , a decimal ten
so we have one and zero additional ones. And
then we have eleven, twelve, thirteen, nineteen,
after nineteen comes. I hope you didn't say
twenty, it's 1a right? Because after one hexadecimal
ten and nine ones we have one hexadecimal
tens and ten ones that are still not grouped,
that is written 1a, after that we have 1b,
1c, up to 1f. After 1f, now comes the twenty,
because we are grouping sixteen ones into
a single hexadecimal ten. In this case, we
would have two tens and no additional ones.
Twenty one, twenty two, twenty three, up to
2f, then would come for thirty and so on.
Can you think what comes before one hundred?
Hope you said f.f. because it represents fifteen
tens and fifteen ones. The next one would
be grouped into another ten then we would
have sixteen ten, grouped into one hundred
and so on.