Okay, so now we know how to translate a number
in an arbitrary number system to decimal,
enough to take a decimal number and turn it
into a binary. You could generalize it and
turn it into any other number system as well.
I want to show you, and basically this is
enough to convert from one number system to
any other number system. If you do these two
things as a two step process, but I want to
show you another kind of translation and that
is to convert a binary number to its equivalent
hexadecimal number. It's going to be a direct
way, where a direct process that does this
translation is going to be a very fast and
simple one, I hope. And the question that
we ask ourselves is why do we care about the
hexadecimal number system? I think I have
a better, or I have a good answer for that
in one of our future models but for now, let's
just see how we can convert a binary to hexadecimal
number back and forth.
So, for example, let's take a 3b9, a hexadecimal
number, and try to figure out its binary representation.
So, first I'll show you the technique, how
technically you take a hexadecimal number
and turn to binary and binary to hexadecimal.
I’ll just show you, without explaining why
it works just how to do that, and after that,
I’ll try to justify it in some sense.
So, for example, when you get this number
3b9 hexadecimal and you want to convert it
into binary. What do you do is actually, with
time you memorize it, but for now let's have
a table. That one side would be the hexadecimal
digits and the other would be the 4 bit binary
representation of these digits, so that the
hexadecimal digits are 0, 1, 2, 3, up to F,
right? And their 4 bit binary representation
goes like that. So 0 would be four 0s, 0.
1 would be 0001, 2 would be 0010, 3 would
be a 0011, and so on. If you keep on going,
you'll see that basically this 4 bit binary
representation gives us all the combinations,
all the possible values or options of four
bits, and it's not a coincidence. It's part
of the reason why this method kind of works.
So, assuming we have this table, on a piece
of paper or we just memorize it, again with
time you memorize it. The process of converting
hexadecimal number to a binary one works like
that, we work digit by digit individually,
independently, and write its 4 bit extension
instead of the digit.
So, for example 9 is 1001, and that what will
have instead of the 9. b is 1011, that's what
we'll have instead of the b. 3 is 0011, that's
what would have instead of the 3. So, we have
3b9, each one extended to 4 bits. All of these
together gives us the binary equivalent of
that number. So, it's kind of simple if we
memorize this table, and it's kind of surprising
because we are actually translating the hexadecimal
number digit by digit, individually and independently.
We didn't do that when we wanted to convert
75 decimal to its binary presentation; we
didn't convert 7 on its own and 5 on its own
and together it was 75, we had to do something
that is much more global in order to convert
a decimal number into a binary one. But hexadecimal,
maybe because it's 2 to the 4, it’s a power
of two, allows us to have a much easier process
to make these conversions.
By the way, the other way around taking a
binary number and convert it into hexadecimal,
would be very similar. We'll have split the
numbers into groups of four and each one to
match to its hexadecimal digit. Just one thing
to note when we group the numbers by fours:
we need to start from right to left, because
if one of the groups or if the number of digits
doesn't divide evenly by four, it is good
to add a 0 to its left without changing the
value of the number. And then we would get
like a whole number of groups of fours. In
this case, the first group is a 3, the second
group is a d, the third group is a 6, and
all together we get 6d3.