Let's try to do the same.
Now let's try counting in base five.
So it would start zero, one, two, three, four,
and now in base five, we are grouping five
objects together.
In base ten, ten objects (ten ones) were grouped
into a ten, ten tens were grouped into a hundred,
and so on in base five were grouping more
often.
We're grouping five objects together so five
ones would be grouped into a base five-ten,
and five tens would be grouped to one hundred
and so on.
So now that we are counting the fifth object,
instead of having the single symbol a single
digit to represent five objects, we are using
one group of five objects and base five-ten
and zero additional ones.
After that, we have eleven, twelve, thirteen,
and fourteen, and the next object would give
us, again, five ones, that would group to
another group of ten.
So, we would have two groups of base five-ten
and zero additional ones.
And so on: twenty one, twenty two, up to one
hundred.
Can you think what comes before hundred?
I hope you said forty four, because after
forty four the next object would be five ones
that would be grouped to another ten, and
then we would have five tens that would be
Group to one base five-hundred.
No tens, no ones, and hundred and one, hundred
two, and so on.
In this case, the digits we needed to use
are only zero to four, because we don't need
any other symbols to represent numbers in
this kind of representation.
We are grouping the five objects together
so we only need to represent quantities of
zero, one, two, three, and four, as a single
object.