Okay, so now we know that we can represent
numbers using the binary number system, basically
base two, so numbers can be represented using
zeros and ones.
But then, let's see how we can represent not
only positive numbers but also negative numbers.
So for example, 26.
The decimal 26 is equivalent to 11010 binary,
right?
Because if we add up the weights, 16 plus
8 plus 2, it would add up to 26.
Check it yourself.
How can we represent negative 26 decimal in
binary?
So obviously, we can write negative 11010
but then inside a computer, we don't have,
we only have zeros and ones.
We don't have the negative sign, we can’t
have that represented.
So, we would need to figure out a different
way to represent negative numbers, signed
numbers, using only zeros and ones.
The first approach I want to show you is called
“Sign and Magnitude.”
It's a very intuitive approach and it says
it's a slight variation of a binary number
system, the formal binary number system.
It said that not all of the bits have their
weight depending on their position; the left
most bit is used only to say what the sign
of the number is, the rest of the bits would
have their weighted value depending on the
position.
So, for example, a positive number is 0, a
negative number is 1 for the sign bit and
twenty six would be whatever 26 looks like.
000 and then 11010 so negative 26 in the sign
magnitude representation, would start with
the 1 as the sign and the rest of the bits
would just represent 26.
This way using only zeros and ones, we can
represent negative numbers as well.
Just know that the one in the signs bit position
doesn't have a power of two as its weight,
it represents something else, its represents
the sign of the number whether it's positive
or negative.
So, that's a very intuitive way to represent
signed numbers.
But then, that's not the way computers typically
represent signed integers.
The typical way that computers represent signed
integers is called “Two’s Complement”
and I'm going to explain this representation
method right away.