Okay, let's do another example working with
Two’s Complement.
So let's take this number here, 00101101,
represented in a 2-bit Two’s Complement,
that's the representation method for this
number, and try to figure out what's its decimal
equivalent, what this number basically represents.
So, since it a starts with a zero, we know
that it is a positive number.
Then, this representation method says that
the first (k minus 1), seven bits, basically
represent its value.
So if we add 32 and 8 and 4 and 1, we get
45 and this number is basically the decimal
45.
Let's take a look at this number here, 11101010,
again in an 8-bit Two’s Complement representation
and try to figure out what its decimal representation.
In this case, since it starts with the one,
it's not a positive number.
But this a presentation method is not ‘Sign
and Magnitude’ that we can just figure out
the value of the lower seven bits and say
that it is negative of this value.
Since it's a Two’s Complement representation
method, we should figure out the absolute
value of this number in a different way.
So let's use the second property that the
sum of a number and its additive value, additive
inverse, is 2 to the power of 8.
In this case, we know that, we don't know
what these values are but we know that this
number here is some kind of a negative something.
Let’s say negative X.
So 11101010 is some negative X. and we’ll
try to find what positive X. is, so we can
know what the absolute value of this number.
So once again, we're trying to figure out
what number is missing there, to be the additive
inverse of the number that we have no idea
what it is.
But since the additive inverse would be positive
and positive numbers are much easier to figure
out their value, we can then figure out what
the value of the negative number.
So once again, let's try to find what's the
additive inverse of our input of this 11101010.
So 0 plus what, would give us a zero?
0 plus 0.
1 plus what, would give us a zero?
Plus 1 with a carry over.
1 plus 0 plus 1, and then another carry over.
1 plus 1 plus 0 with the carry over.
1 plus 0 plus 1, and 1 plus 1 plus 0.
And 1 plus 0 plus 0, and 1 plus 1 plus 0.
So, basically we got that our number is 11101010
but its additive inverse, its absolute value,
it's positive corresponding value is 00010110.
And this number is very easy to figure out
its value because we just have to add the
weights of each digit.
So we have a 2 plus a 4 plus 16, and that
adds up to 22.
So this number here is positive 22, which
implies that the negative number we had before
is negative 22.
So this number 11101010 in an 8-bit Two’s
Complement representation, it represents the
number negative 22 decimal.