Okay, now that we know how to add numbers
in different number systems, let's see how
we can subtract numbers in a different number
system.
Again, let's start with decimal for practice,
and then try to generalize it to other number
systems as well.
So, let's try to subtract 427 minus 192 decimal.
So, we start with the ones right.
7 minus 2 that would give us a 5, then we
try to subtract 2 minus 9 and that's a problem
because we can’t subtract 9 from 2, so we
would need to borrow an additional 10 tens,
actually in this case.
So, instead of having 2 tens, we'll have 12
tens, and that by splitting the hundred, the
4 hundreds into 3 hundred and 10 tens.
That would leave us with 3 hundred and 10
tens additional 2 tens that would give a 312
ten.
So, instead of saying 42 tens or 420, we say
312 tens.
Then we have these 12 tens minus 9 that would
give us a 3 and 300 minus 1, that would give
us a 2.
So 427 minus 192 is 235.
Let's try doing the same for the octal number
system.
Let’s try to subtract 351 from 536.
Same thing, we first subtract 1 from the 6
that would give us a 5, then when we try to
subtract 5 from 3, that is not possible.
So, we need to split one of the hundreds,
one of the 5 hundred into tens.
So, instead of having 530, we would have 4
hundred and 13 ten.
So therefore, we have 13 tens that we need
to take 5 out of them.
So, let's count back out of thirteen, so it's
twelve, eleven, ten, seven, six.
So, we have 6 there, and 4 minus 3 is 1.
So, 536 minus 351 is 165 octal.