Okay, now that we know how to count in different
number systems, we can see that we can represent
the same value in different ways, depending
on the number system we're working. Let's
take a look at the number 13. So, when I think
13, I have to be more specific because 13
can be a decimal number, can be an octal number,
can be a base five number. They all use the
digits one and three. So, I have to say what
kind of a 13 I'm referring to. Now that we
have a lot of number systems, the way to do
that is to subscript the number system we're
referring this number with the number thirteen.
We enclose it in parenthesis and say subscript
ten, basically meaning the decimal number
system.
Let's try to figure out what's the equivalent
value for the decimal thirteen in the octal
number system. So, let's try counting up to
thirteen. So one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, octal would after seven would
group the ones into a ten, so we would have
ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen.
So a decimal thirteen is equivalent to a one
five, fifteen, octal. Let's try to figure
out what's the equivalent value in the base
five number system. One, two, three, four,
after four would come ten, eleven, twelve,
thirteen, fourteen, after fourteen, we have
another group so it would be twenty, twenty
one, twenty two, twenty three. So thirteen
decimal is equivalent to fifteen octal, and
to twenty three base five. Let's try to see
what this number is equivalent in the binary
number system. Again, let’s count: one,
ten, eleven, one, hundred, one, 101, 110,
111, 1000, 1001, 1010, 1011, 1100, 1101. So
the decimal thirteen is equivalent to 1101
binary. Let's do the same for the hexadecimal:
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, then would come A. B. C. D., so it would
be a D. hexadecimal.
So, a 13 decimal is equivalent to 15 octal
to 23 base five to 1101 binary and D. hexadecimal.
Once again, you see that a lower number system,
a binary number system, is a longer number
and groups more often. So, we get a longer
number. And a bigger number system, sixteen
for example, is a shorter number, it's one
digit in this case. It would be very interesting
to have a method to be able to convert a number
of presentations in one number system to its
equivalent in a number of another number system,
to translate N. in base b1 to N., the same
amount representing the same value, but in
base b2 and that's what we're going to do
next.