So, for that let's start with the decimal
number system itself; understand exactly what
the positions of each digit mean, and then
try to generalize it to other number systems
as well.
So, for example, number 375, decimal 375.
So, we have three digits here: the ones, tens,
and hundreds.
So, the one basically stands for the five,
that is in the one's position.
Each value here, represents a single object,
right?
Each value in the tens position represents
a group of ten objects, and each value in
the hundreds position represents a group of
one hundred objects.
We like to write it as powers of ten, so one
hundred is ten to the power of two, ten is
ten to the power of one, and one is ten to
the power of zero.
So, now we can look at 375 as a weighted sum
of these weights of the digits in their position.
So, we have five times one object: ten to
the power of zero.
Plus seven tens: seven times ten to the power
of one.
Plus three hundred, which is three times ten
to the power of two.
If you add that, you get to 375, not surprising
at all, but that what we mean when we say
375 decimal.
Now, let's look at 125 octal, for example.
Once again, each digit here has its own weight,
its own amount of objects that it represents.
So, the ones digits represent a single object
here as well.
The ten digits represent a group of eight,
right?
And the hundredth digits represent eight eighths
or eight octal tens, which means 64 objects.
Once again, let's write it as powers of eight.
So, sixty four is eight to the power of two,
eight is eight to the power of one, and one
is eight to the power of zero.
So, 125 octal, we can look at it as the sum
of: 5 times 1 times 8 to the power of 0, plus
2 times 8 to the power of 1, plus 1 times
8 to the power of 2.
If you add them all up, you get 85.
Basically, 125 octal represents an amount
of 85 objects, decimal eighty five by the
way.
Same thing would work with the binary number
system.
So, again each digit has its own weight, right?
The ones digit is 1, the tens digit is 2,
the hundreds digit is 4 and the fourth digit,
the thousandth digit, represents an amount
of eight.
Again, as powers of 2 to the 0, 2 to the 1,
2 to the 2, and 2 to the 3.
And the sum would then be 1 times 2 to the
zero, plus 1 times 2 to the 1, plus 0 times
2 squared, and 1 times 2 to the three.
You add them, you'll get eleven.
So, 1011 binary is equivalent, represents,
11 objects, 11 decimal, right?
Same thing for hexadecimal 3b2.
Each digit has its own weight: 16 to the 0,
16 to the 1, 16 to the 2, and then when you
add it up, you get 2 times 16 to the 0, 11
times 16 to the 1, right?
B. is one after the A: A is ten, B. is eleven.
So, 11 times 6 into the 1 to 3 times 16 squared.
All together it adds up to 946.
If you look in a general form, you look at
the number An to a 0, like you have n. plus
1 digits here.
In the number system, base B., each digit
would have its own weight: b. to the 0, b.
to the power of 1, b. to the power of 2, up
to b. to the power of N. And this number,
if you add the digits with their corresponding
weight, you'll have the formula: A0 times
B. to the power of 0, plus A1 times b to the
power of 1, and so on up to An times B. to
the power of N.
If you use this technique, you'll be able
to figure out what’s the decimal value that
is represented, in this case a base B. number.