Okay, let's see how we can convert a number
in one number system representation into the
equivalent number but in a different number
systems representation.
Actually, I'm not going to show you the general
form of taking a number in base b1 and converting
it into an equivalent N in b2, I’m going
to show you two techniques to do some other
kind of a translation.
So, first one would be taking a number “N”
and in an arbitrary base B. and converting
it into decimal that would be a very important
thing to be able to do.
Cause a lot of times you'll get numbers in
binary hexadecimal and you want to understand
what they mean, basically, so you convert
it into decimal.
And the other way around is also something
important to be able to do.
Taking a number in decimal, your natural number
system, and converting it into, I don't know,
the computer's number system, the binary,
or the hexadecimal, or whatever.
If you think of it a bit deeper, you see that
these two translations actually allow you
to convert from any number system to any other
number system.
Just compose them pmrafter one of the others:
start with N and b1, convert it into a decimal,
and then take the decimal and convert it into
b2.
So, basically going from b1 to b2, stepping
in the decimal somewhere in the two-step process.
But I'll describe each of them separately.
Let's start with how to take a number in an
arbitrary number system and convert it into
decimal.