In order to get used to working in other number
systems, let's start with the most trivial
thing we can do.
Let’s start counting, and in order to be
able to count in different number systems,
let's take a deeper look at the decimal number
system in base ten.
How we and what we're doing in that number
system and then we'll try to generalize it
for other number systems as well.
So let's start counting in the decimal number
system in base ten kind of going back to second
grade, but let's do that.
So, zero after that would come one, after
one would come two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine.
Then, when we get to the tenth object, instead
of having a single symbol to represent the
amount (the quantity of ten), we grouped ten
ones into a single ten.
We have this ten in the second position in
our number and then we have zero additional
ones.
So one zero basically means one group of ten
and zero additional ones.
Then we have eleven, which is one group of
ten and a single addition of one, twelve,
thirteen, fourteen, up to nineteen.
After that, when comes the next object having
a group of ten and ten ones, these ten ones
would be grouped into another group of ten,
so together we would have two groups of ten
and zero ones.
And so it continues twenty one, twenty two,
and so on, up to, for example ninety nine.
And after ninety nine, the next object would
have ten ones that would be grouped into another
ten, therefore, would have ten tens and these
ten tens would be grouped into a single one
hundred that is represented in the next position.
So we have one of one hundred group, zero
of the tens groups, zero of the one.
And so on, it continues.
So this is what we do when we are counting
in base ten; how we look at the positions
of the digits in a decimal representation.
The digits we use in order to represent the
numbers are zero to nine, to represent all
the different values we can have in each position.
After nine, we're just not using this position
anymore we're grouping it and moving to the
next position.