Let's go over the func2 formula that calculates
the target addresses for branch instructions.
Since branches use relative address calculation,
the formula uses the program counter of the
branch instruction.
In addition, the formula uses a 16-bit immediate
parameter that we label as do immediate.
Here is a little bit more detail on the formula
for func2.
It first takes the program counter and increments
it by 4.
Recall that in this situation, the value of
the program counter is the address of the
branch instruction.
It then takes the 16-bit immediate value and
sign-extend it to 32 bits.
In the third step, the formula takes the sign
extended immediate value and shift it left
by two.
This has the same effect as multiplying it
by 4.
The final step adds the results from step
1 and 3 to get a 32-bit target address.
Here is an example to illustrate how func2
works.
We have a branch if equal instruction with
the program counter and the do immediate parameter
given.
The first step adds 4 to the program counter
and the second step sign extends the do immediate
value.
Since the Do Immediate is a positive value,
the sign extension simply pads zeroes to make
it 32 bits.
The third step takes the sign-extended Do
Immediate and multiplies it by four, and the
last step adds the results of step 1 and step
3 to get the target address highlighted