To set the correct value of the Rs in the
jump register instruction, we need to first
understand the interaction between the jump
and link instruction the and jump register
instruction. Consider this use case of the
absolute value function. We have a header
file Lib dot H that holds the declaration
of the absolute value function and a c file
Lib dot C that holds its implementation. In
the main file, we call the absolute value
function. Recall that the jump and link instruction
is responsible for function calls. Jump and
Link does two things. It first sets the address
to return to after the function call in R31,
and then it jumps to the function. So in this
respect, the return address is in the R31
register and the jump register instruction
must use R31 to return from the call. Hence
Rs in the jump register instruction is equal
to R31.