There is one more factor to consider.
As we see in the high-level code, the absolute
value function call must return the result
to the main code.
In our current MIPS mnemonic code, we have
the result of the absolute value in the R4
register.
If we recall, R4 is a register used to pass
parameters to function calls.
It thus cannot be used to return data from
function calls.
For that, we need to use either R2 or R3.
So in the final version of the code, we need
to initialize R2 to X in order to keep the
value in R2 in case X is already positive.
We also need to make sure that the result
of the subtraction that turns the negative
value into a positive is also put into R2.
This way, when the function call returns,
the absolute value is in the R2 register and
it can be used as the result variable in main
code.