Now let's take a look at an example of how
jump and branch instructions are used for
loops.
Consider the following example.
We have two integer variables X and Y, both
greater than zero.
The goal is to perform X times Y, without
using the multiplication instruction.
One way to implement this function in a high-level
C or C++ code is as follows.
We have a while loop that uses a decrementing
counter initialized at Y.
Inside the loop, we add X to an accumulator
as long as the counter is not zero.
Note that for this approach, it doesn't matter
if C and Y are always greater than 0.
Another approach is to leverage the fact that
X and yYare both greater than zero.
In that case, we know that the loop will be
executed at least once.
So we can use a do while loop for the code.
We will use that second approach to implement
the MIPS mnemonic code.