So let's detail the MIPS mnemonic code for
our X times Y. Let us assume that X and Y
are in R4 and R5 respectively and that the
code segment starts at address 4D0.
If we look at the high-level code, we see
that the first two operations initialize the
counter to Y and set the accumulator R E S
to zero. We can do the same for our MIPS code
by initializing the register R8 to zero and
the register R9 to the value of Y. In our
MIPS code, we will thus use R8 for the accumulator
and R9 for the loop counter. Since we have
a do while loop, we know that we are going
to add to the accumulator and decrement the
loop counter at least once. To add to the
accumulator, we simply use the doubleword
ADD, or D ADD, R8, R8, R4 instruction to keep
adding X to itself. To decrement the counter,
we use the immediate add instruction D ADD
I, where the immediate value is negative 1.
The next part of the code is to check if the
counter is zero in order to determine if we
need to get out of the loop or not. There
are several ways to do this. We can use a
branch if not equal to zero instruction, a
branch if equal to zero, a branch if not equal,
and probably other approaches. We choose to
use branch if not equal. Since we need to
compare the loop counter to zero, we use R9,
which holds the loop counter, and R0, which
is always zero, as the registers of our BNE
instruction. If the counter is not yet zero,
the branch is taken, and we need to go back
to the two instructions that add the accumulator
and decremental loop counter. This allows
us to iterate through the loop one more time.
As we discussed before, the sequential instruction
after a branch instruction must handle the
case when the branch is not taken. For our
code, the branch is not taken when the counter
is equal to zero and we need to return from
the function call. But instead of simply handling
the return, we first need to store the final
result of the accumulator in R2 or R3 register
so that it can be available as a return value
from the function call. So here we use the
R2 register to return the value of the accumulator.
This is similar to what we did before for
the absolute value function. The last instruction
handles the return from the function call
and for that we use the jump register instruction.
Assuming that the function would be called
using jump and link, we know the return address
will be in R31 register.