Here we have the MIPS mnemonic code for the
other high-level code that works whether X
or Y is zero.
In this code, we also initiate registers R8
and R9 to hold the accumulator and the loop
counter.
The next stage is to implement the while loop.
For that we use a branch if not equal instruction.
If the branch condition is true, we go inside
the loop to decrement the counter and to add
to the accumulator.
If the loop condition is false, then we need
to quit to loop.
The way we do that in this case is by using
the Jump instruction.
This allows us to skip the instructions that
are within the loop.
We also see that there is a jump instruction
after the instructions within the loop.
This second jump instruction targets the branch
if not equal instruction so we can go back
and check the condition of the loop before
we quit the function.
The last two instructions are similar to the
other code as they are responsible for copying
the value of the accumulator in the R2 register
and for returning from the function call.