So now that we've got data that we can store
inside the function inside the object and
we can get data out of the object, then perhaps
we should have some other useful functions.
It's really common here in the U.S. that we
might print a date in the term, in the form
of day slash month slash year.
So we could add a function inside our object
inside our class where we can display the
date in the form of day slash month slash
year.
So you can take a look at the code for that;
it would be a very simple function to write.
Again it's const-ified because it's not changing
any of the data.
We might also write a function to validate,
to check to see if the date is valid, and
it will return true or false.
For example, if somebody puts in February
thirty first of two thousand and sixteen,
that shouldn't be valid because there really
is no February thirty first; so that might
return false if we were to have a validate
function on that.
We could also check to make sure that the
leap year is valid and if we need a leap year
calculation; we need to check which years
are leap years and which years are not leap
years that may require another function.
And in that case the calculation of a leap
year may not be a function that we want to
have allowed access to from the outside, which
would make that function a private member
function.
Really what I'm getting at here is the possibilities
are endless.
What you decide to do with a date class might
be very different from what somebody else
decides to do with a date class, but you can
do literally anything you want with it inside
C++.