One of the problems that we're going to run
into is that if we just construct an object
like we did before and it's a Date object;
what are the values of day month in year immediately
after the construction of the Date object,
they’re garbage, they’re garbage values.
We don't know what their values are and they
may not even be valid so it's very possible
that we may have a large number for the day,
like negative eight hundred thousand and it's
now here are stored inside, what we would
classify as an acceptable date object, because
we created it.
So what C++ allows us to do is make sure that
we always know that valid values, even if
we just created that object, that there are
valid values in it.
So C++ creates thing called a constructor,
and we can create the constructor where it
runs code that we want so that we can set
the values appropriately for whatever the
default date is.
So the default constructor is a function which
is given a name which is exactly the same
and it is case sensitive, it’s exactly the
same as the name of the class.
There’s no return type, so it’s not void
or anything like that, it’s just literally
no return type, we don't list anything and
it doesn't have any parameters.
So we can see from the code that what we've
done here is create a constructor where we're
setting the values of day, month, and year,
to the appropriate to what we classify as
an appropriate value, without any interaction
by the user.
All the user has to do is create one of these
Date objects, by default, and it will set
those values to what we consider the default
values.