So we can also have constructors that take,
for example three integers.
We might have one that takes a day month in
year, sets those values.
We can also have a constructor that takes
just one of the values and constructs it based
on the Unix epoch, in case you're interested
in constructing it based on that.
But what we can do now is inside main, we
can now create a date with those three variables
so that our code is a little bit easier.
So if you remember back couple slides ago,
the previous code, we set the date to August
sixth one thousand nine hundred one.
We had to create the date first and then set
each of the three individual values.
Now we can take those four lines of code and
compact them down into one/ where we create
the date and set the values all at the same
time.
You can create as many constructors as you
like; each has to have a unique set of parameters.
And you have to remember that even though
we have a default constructor, only one constructor
will ever be called.
So whichever constructor is chosen to be called,
that's the only one that will ever be called;
it's not like one is going to call the default
constructor and then go further on to do some
extra work.
Construction only happens once and we only
call one constructor.