C++ allows us to do something that most of
the languages have eliminated; they don't
like this anymore. Java has gotten rid of
it, Python never had it to begin with, actually
Java never had to begin with, to be honest.
What we can do with C++ is what we call operator
overloading, and operator overloading allows
us to take two objects, and for example add
them together. We can operate on two objects
or on an object, using what we would consider
a normal operator.
So there's three different types of operators:
we have unary operators which only work on
one object one operand. A unary operator would
be like plus plus, we would say A plus plus;
there is no other object that we're working
with. A binary operator works on to operate
operands, so two objects, A plus B, for example.
And the majority of the operators that we're
going to work with are in fact binary operators.
So we have all the regular math operators,
plus, minus, multiplication, division, module,
zero. We have the compound operators, which
are things like the plus equals, and the minus
equals, and so on and so forth. We have the
comparison operators, which are the less than,
the greater than, the output, the input operators,
and then we also have things like the square
brackets operator or what we call the array
index of operator.
There's also a category of operators called
the ternary operators, and in fact C++ only
has one of these. It's called the conditional
operator and if you haven't come across it,
it's horribly confusing and we don't often
like to use it; but it is there and some people
like it. So you can have the turnaround operator.
Really when boils down to it operators are
nothing more than functions, and they're just
a strange way to use functions. What C++ actually
does is it takes that A plus B and it says,
I don't know how to do A plus B, but I know
how to make function calls. And it converts
the function; it converts the operation, into
a function call. What it converts the function
call to depends on how we as the programmer
decide to overload that operator. If we overload
the operator as a nonmember, we’ll talk
about this, the operator the function call
would look like operator plus A B. So the
A plus B function call would be operator plus
A B; it would take two parameters. It's a
binary operator, it's overloaded as a nonmember,
it takes two parameters. However if it's overloaded
as a member, then the this object becomes
one of the operands and so we only need one
parameter. So, the equivalent function call
if we're a member, is A dot operator plus
B. Here we only have one parameter because
the this object, the calling object, is the
second, is actually the first operand. Operator
functions can be either member or nonmember
and we're going to talk of a lot about how
to choose which to use. And some operators
change the data inside the objects; some return
a new object, so it's important to look at
what the operator is supposed to do. A compound
operator like the plus equals operator should
actually change the calling object. Whereas
the plus operator A plus B, doesn't change
A or B, it in fact return something entirely
different. So you have to take into account
what the operator is supposed to do, and then
you've got to figure out how to write it.