C++ has some restrictions; it's not open.
There are some operators that can't be overloaded.
For example the dot operator; you can't change
what it does, it's known as the struct member
union select operator and you simply cannot
change anything about it.
The scope resolution operator, the one that
goes between the name of the class and the
name of the function when we're defining it
outside the class, you can't change that there's
nothing you can do with that.
There's a couple more that you would probably
never try to change; the Star dot which is
the de-reference and member select.
The size of which is very rarely changed;
very rarely even considered, very rarely used.
And the ternary operator, you can't change
what the ternary operator does.
So those are some that are just completely
off limits.
You can't change anything about them; they
are what they are.
There are some that are restricted that you
can overload them but you have to be a member
in as an to overload this this operator and
that's because the operator has so much involved
in what it's going to do inside the class,
that C++ says you have to be a member of this
class in order to overload it.
So these are functions that can only be overloaded
operators that can only be overloaded as member
functions.
So the assignment operator and the array index
of operator can only be overloaded as members
of the class; you have no choice in that.
There's also some that can almost, not be
overloaded as a member: the input and the
output operators, or technically they're known
as the bit shift the left and bit shift right
operators, but we all call them the output
in the input operators.
These operators can be overloaded as a member
of the class because if you look at the equivalent
function call, if we said something like C
out arrow arrow A then the problem is that
this would be C out dot operator arrow arrow
A. So you wouldn't be making this a member
of your class, you would be making this a
member of the class which has the object C
out, and that's called an O stream.
And you're not going to overload override
the entire Ostream class; you're going to
recreate the entire Ostream class, and create
a new C out object just to overload this member.
So while C++ doesn't technically say that
you can't overload this members, overload
this operator is a member, it's almost universally
accepted that you're going to make this a
non-member of the class.
So those are the only restrictions; any other
operator that you can think of, you can't
create your own you can't change the precedence
of any operator, but any other operator which
C++ has you can overload.