Now that we understand how we can overload
these operators.
we have to take a look into what the operator
returns, so what's it going to do when it's
done the value that's returned really depends
on what the operator is going to do.
So the plus operator for example is going
to return back the sum of the two operands;
it doesn't change either operand we said that
before, we're not going to change A or B.
If we do A plus B, but instead we're going
to return back a new value which is the sum
of A and B, whatever that means because we
haven't defined what data types A and B are.
Here we have a little bit of a rule in that
we the return data type, really depends on
what's being returned of course.
If the item that's being returned was created
inside the function, then the return has to
be by value.
So in the plus operator we add together two
operands A and B. In order to do that we have
to in the plus function, in the operator plus
function, we're going to have to create a
temporary object, store the value that's in
A and add the value that's in B, and then
return that temporary object.
So we've created an item; we've created something
inside the function and now we want to return
it.
The only choice we have is to return by value.
But if we're returning something that was
passed in as a parameter.
So for example, we have the plus equal operator;
the plus equal operator instead of returning
the just the sum of the two items, now we're
expecting that we're returning the left hand
side item.
So A plus equal B would return A, and that's
something that existed prior to the function
call.
We didn't create it; it existed prior to the
function call.
So the return line is probably going to look
something like return star this, there’s
another use for this.
And in doing so we recognize that we could
create another copy of this object, but the
time it takes to create the other copy and
the duplications of the data uses more memory
is a waste of time and memory.
So what we'd rather do is return by reference,
because now we don't have to do the copy and
do use up the extra memory instead we can
just return by reference.
Returning by reference is really the preferred
mechanism.
But in order to do that the object that we
are returning has to have existed prior otherwise
or returning a reference to something that
will no longer exist at the end of the function
because it was created inside the function.
So if we created it, returned by value; if
it was passed into us or existed before, return
by reference.
And that's what to return.