One interesting thing about C++ is it has
both the pre and the post increment operator;
of course we've used these before.
But we need a special case to differentiate
between the pre and the post increment operators
because they're both unary operators.
So since, if they’re members it's not going
to have any parameters; how do we differentiate
between the pre increment and the post increment
operators.
Well C++ resolves this by passing an int to
the post increment operator; the pre increment
operator is just going to change the value
and then it's going to return a reference
to the existing operator, it’s going to
return star this.
So the format for that looks exactly like
you see on the screen: it's just date ampersand
operator plus plus with nothing in the parameter
list, returned by reference because we are
returning star this.
But the posting current operators going to
create a copy of the object, it's creating
something inside the function, and then is
going to change the value of the object, not
of the copy, and then it's going to return
a copy.
So we're returning the original value, or
a copy of the original value, and we're changing
the value at the same time.
Since we're returning by value, we have to
make sure that that return is by value.
So we’re returning a copy; we’re returning
something that we created inside our function
so we have to return by value.
So you're going to see it as date with no
ampersand operator plus plus, and because
this is the posting current operator, we need
to pass in that integer; so it's date operator
plus plus integer.
The integer really has no bearing on what
happens inside.
It's really just a way to differentiate between
the pre-increment in the post increment operator
and that's the only way that C++ can solve
it.
So don’t look at the value of the integer;
the value of the integers completely irrelevant.
Just the fact there is an integer there tells
us that it's suppose increment operator.