Now we have a good basis for how to create
classes and when to create classes, there's
something else that we can do in C++ which
is really great; and that's called inheritance.
Inheritance allows us to create really, really
complex classes out of simpler ones; not just
with composition, not just with adding elements
into a class, but what we can really do here
is create what we call the is a situation
or the is a solution.
I'll give you a couple of very simple examples:
a car is a vehicle, or a circle is an object
or, for example, a student is a person.
What we're saying is that the car class should
contain everything that the vehicle class
can contain.
So anything you can do with a vehicle, you
could do with a car.
The person is the same sort of thing, any
information we'd like to store about a person,
we'd also like to store about a student.
So for storing things like name, and height
and age and that sort of stuff for a person,
we'd like to store that same information as
a student but we also like to store additional
information in a student that's not in a person.
So what we're creating here is a larger more
complex derived class from an existing base
class.
So using the base class as just a form so
that we can add things and not have to reimplement
all the work that was done to create the base
class.
Now the great part about inheritance is that
all the items all the functions, all the data,
everything that was in the base class is automatically
going to be in the derived class.
Unfortunately, we don't copy over the constructors,
so the constructors for the base class don't
come over to the derived class; we have to
recreate any constructors that we might want.
But we also have the ability to call those
base class constructors so it's not as difficult
as it might seem.
The derived class, of course, can add any
new material that it wants to add; anything
that we want to put into the derived class
that doesn't exist in the base class can obviously
be put in.
The derived class can create new versions
of existing functions and then it's called
overriding.
We can override a function that exists in
the base class by creating a new function
in the derived class which does similar things
which has the same parameter list which has
the same name.
One thing that we're going to come into play
with, that's going to come into play here,
is that we are not changing any of the accessors;
so public is still public and private and
is still private.
And if you remember I said that inside the
only member functions of a class can access
private data; does that mean that member functions
of a derived class can access private data?
The answer is no: member functions of a derived
class cannot access private data of a base
class.
Obviously, member functions of a derived class
can access its own private data, but not that
of the base class.
So we have to take that into account when
we look at accessing private information.
The derived classes member functions can’t
access the base class’ private data.