Here we've got quite a bit of code and I just
want to go over it quite simply.
We've got a base class called Pet. and the
base class pet, what we're doing is we're
creating a cat and a pet combination here.
So the base class pet has functions like get
name and set name and it asked the pet to
speak and figure out what the pet speaking
does later.
But we also have a cat class, which is based
on the pet class.
If take a look that colon public pet indicates
that a cat is a pet, and that's the derivation;
that's inheritance right there.
The cat doesn't redefine name and pet ID that
were created inside the pet class, but it
does add a double, which is the whisker length
of the cat.
The constructor for the cat class tells the
pet class to set its pet ID to ten thousand.
So here we have an explicit call to the base
constructor and if you look, that form of
it looks very much like the member initialization
list that we saw so many slides ago.
Now we call it the base initialization list
and it can only be done this way; you can't
put anything inside those curly braces in
order to initialize the pet.
Now keep in mind if you take a look at pet,
the cat will not have access to the pet ID
because it's a private data member inside
the base class.
So the only way to set the pet ID is to use
that base initialization list.
We also have a function speak, which just
prints out meow and set length and get length,
which are accessors and mutators for the whisker
length.
And we have another function called set name
which coincidentally looks very much like
the set name function inside pet.
We’re going to look at that in just a minute.