The idea that we want to employ here is one
of encapsulation: we don't want anybody outside
the class, outside the class creation, to
be able to access data inside the class.
So the idea is that code written as part of
the class has a greater access than code which
is not part of the class.
For example main, main shouldn't have access
to some of the private information inside
the class.
And the idea of encapsulation allows us to
set levels of protection so that programmers
that aren't involved in the creation of the
class are not going to have access to certain
items.
We can give them controlled access to items
that we want them to be allowed access to,
and then we can strip their access so they
can't have access to the items that they shouldn't
have access to.
So, for example going back to our house and
blueprint model.
The architect should be able to change anything
on the blueprints of the house, the designer
of the class should be able to change anything
inside the class, but the plumber who's installing
the toilet shouldn't be able to change where
the location of the toilet is or else the
bathroom door might not close, for example.
So we want to create a model where we can
protect certain parts of the class and allow
public access to other parts of the class.