Let's get down to the syntax of how we can
create a class.
First off the class is an abstract data type,
so we're creating a new data type for C++
to know about.
We can create this class as a data type which
is a more complex data type made up of simpler
data types.
And we're going to get into this a lot because
we can make them very, very complex.
Of course we’ll use the C++ keyword class,
which means incidentally that you can never
use the word class as an identifier for anything
inside your programs.
You can't create a variable named class.
Here's a quick view of what a date class might
look at, and we know that a date is actually
just three integers; it's a day, a month,
and a year.
So here we’re creating a new data type for
the storage of three integers, atomically,
so that they go together.
The year and the month and the day are all
associated, so that for example, your birthday
is actually three different numbers associated
with them one another: the day, the month,
and the year.
And we need to have all three contain together;
hence the idea of encapsulation.