Let us discuss how instructions are encoded
and formatted in MIPS64.
First, let’s go through basic characteristics
of the layout of an instruction.
Recall that each instruction in MIPS64 is
32 bits.
Each instruction has an opcode.
The opcode is 6 bits long and it is the most
significant bits of the instruction.
The role of the opcode is to indicate what
operation the instruction performs.
For example, the load double instruction has
its own opcode and the store double instruction
has its own opcode.
Some instructions have the same opcode for
formatting purposes.
In such cases, the instructions have second
opcodes also known as functions.
These second opcodes play the role of indicating
the operations of the instructions.
In addition to an opcode, each instruction
has one or many operands.
The goal of the operands is to indicate where
the data needed by the instruction is located.
An operand can be a register number or an
immediate value that is hardcoded in the instruction.
MIPS64 defines three formats for its instructions:
register format, or R-format, Immediate format
or I-format, and Jump format or J-format.
The purpose of instruction formatting is to
allow the processor to understand the role
of the instruction and what operands it needs.
This provides a compact method to design the
processor.
If each instruction was allowed to have its
own format, then the CPU would have to be
very complicated to handle any formatting
approach.