R-format instructions have only registers
as operands.
An R-format can have between one and three
registers and one of the registers can be
a destination register.
Another interesting aspect of R-format instructions
is that that they all have the same opcode
of 0.
Therefore, each R-format instruction needs
a second opcode, or a function, to detail
its unique operation
The figure illustrates the layout of R-format
instructions.
The opcode for each R-format is the same.
The instruction has three 5-bit fields for
at most three registers, Rs, Rt, and Rd respectively.
Another field of R-format instructions is
the shift amount field.
This field is only valid when the instruction
is shift left logical or shift right logical.
Otherwise, the shift mount field is zero.
The last field of the instruction is the 6-bit
second opcode or function.
As we see, when we add the size of each field,
we get 32 bits.
Let us illustrate how the processor determines
what to do when it fetches an R-format instruction.
Consider the example of this figure.
The processor first reads the opcode and it
sees it is all zeroes, meaning it is an R-format.
The processor then reads the function field,
which is the least significant 6 bits, to
determine the operation of that R-format instruction.
The function 101100 is for the D ADD instruction.
The MIPS64 manual details the function field
for each R-format instruction.
Once the CPU knows the instruction is a doubleword
ADD, it knows that it needs the operands Rs,
Rt and Rd.
Moreover, since it is not a shift instruction,
the shift amount field is not used.
The processor then converts the register numbers
for the operands of the instruction and can
form the complete instruction.