A J-format instruction only has one operand:
a 26-bit immediate value.
J-format instructions are used for jump instructions.
Therefore, the 26-bit immediate value is used
as an address parameter to use to calculate
the target address of the jump instruction.
Just like I-format, each J-format instruction
has its own opcode and does not need a 2nd
opcode.
Just like all instructions, the CPU first
read the opcode to determine the format.
In the case of this example, the opcode matches
to the Jump instruction.
Since the jump instruction is a J-format,
the CPU just reads the next 26 bits to determine
the value of the address field.