Let us now look at the memory step.
This step is only used by load and store double
instructions in our CPU.
For the load double instruction, the CPU sends
the memory address to the memory controller
in order to obtain the read the data.
Since the address of the data was already
calculated during the execute step, the CPU
can simply make the memory request using the
address stored in ALUOut1.
When the data is returned from memory, the
CPU puts it in the load memory double or LMD
register.
LMD is a special purpose register that temporarily
holds the value of data obtained from memory
loads.
For the store double instruction, the CPU
must write the data from the register Rt to
the memory using the address calculated in
the execute step.
Since Rt is put in the B temporary register
during decode stage, the memory step is fairly
straightforward for this instruction.
The WriteBack step is only useful for the
Load double and the R-format arithmetic and
logic operations.
This is because only these instructions of
our CPU need to write to general-purpose registers.
For load double, the CPU takes the content
of LMD and writes it into the Rt register.
For the R-format instructions, the CPU needs
to write the result of the ALU operation in
the Rd register.
Since the result of the ALU operation was
put in ALUOut2 during execute step, the CPU
can simply use the content of ALUOut2 to put
in Rd.