Let us discuss each execution step in detail.
In the instruction fetch step, the processor
uses the program counter to access the memory
and get the instruction to execute.
The syntax M and PC in brackets indicates
a memory access where PC is the address is
used for the access.
When the memory returns the instruction, the
CPU puts it in a special register known as
the instruction register, or IR.
This register always holds the 32 bits of
the instruction being executed.
The last part of the instruction fetch is
to update the program counter to point to
the next instruction.
This is done by adding four to the current
program counter.
The value four is used to increment the program
counter because each instruction is 32 bits
or four bytes.
Therefore, the CPU has to jump four bytes
of address space to go point to the next instruction.