During the decode step, the CPU determines
the operation that the instruction needs to
perform, obtains the register values that
may be needed, and allocates the functional
resources that the instruction needs for its
operation.
For the purposes of our CPU, we only need
one functional unit: an ALU.
This is because our CPU does not have complex
instructions.
The same ALU is used for all operations that
the CPU needs to perform.
This ALU has two outputs ALUOut1 and ALUOut2.
Here is a little bit mor e detail on the decode
step for our CPU.
During that step, our CPU automatically accesses
the registers for the Rs and Rt operands and
sign-extends the 16-bit immediate value, regardless
of the instruction type.
The CPU then puts the value of Rs in a special
register called A, It puts the value of Rt
into a special register called B, and it puts
the sign-extended value into a special register
called I MM, or immediate.
Note that A, B, and I MM, are special registers
like PC and IR and cannot be accessed by the
code.
They are only used to store temporary parameters
that the CPU needs to complete the instruction.