Regardless of the instruction, the processor
goes through the same procedures for fetch
and decodes steps.
Things begin to change when we get to the
execute step.
This is because each instruction has a different
role.
As a result, we have to look at the execute
step for each instruction.
Let us first look at the load double and store
double instructions.
During the execute step, the CPU calculates
the memory address that either the load or
the store instruction needs.
Recall that both load and store use the Rs
register to hold the base address of the data
segment, and use the 16-bit do immediate as
the offset within the data segment.
Also, remember that to calculate the address,
the CPU needs to first sign extend the do
immediate, then add it to the base address
of the data segment.
During the decode step, the CPU had already
moved the value of Rs to A and had already
sign-extended the do immediate and had put
into I MM.
Therefore, during the execute step for load
double or store double instruction, the CPU
just adds A and I MM to get the address of
the memory access.
The result of the addition is stored in ALUOut1.