Let us now discuss the performance of this
CPU.
First, let's go over the concept of CPU clock
rate.
Usually, when we buy a computer, one of the
factors that we look at is the CPU frequency.
The frequency essentially is representative
of the clock rate, which defines how fast
each operation can be performed.
The metric of the clock rate is the clock
cycle.
To determine out how many seconds a clock
cycle last, we simply take the inverse of
the CPU frequency.
For example, if we have a 1 gigahertz CPU,
one clock cycle takes 1 divided by 1 gigahertz
which equals 1 Nano second.
What this means is that each operation of
the CPU takes 1 nano second to perform.
In this respect, an operation can be thought
of as the work of one state in our CPU high-level
diagram.