Let us discuss pipelining in more detail.
When a CPU is pipelined, it breaks down each
execution step into a stage, where each can
be used independently by an instruction.
In addition, each stage uses buffers, commonly
known as latches, to obtain information about
what the instruction did in the previous stage.
So let's use this example to illustrate the
benefits of pipelining.
When one instruction starts executing, it
first goes in the execution, instruction fetch
stage in the pipeline.
Just like the states in the high-level diagram
of the CPU, each pipeline stage takes one
clock cycle to complete.
When the instruction completes the fetch stage,
it goes to the decode stage of the pipeline
in cycle 2.
This means the fetch stage is free at that
cycle because no instruction is currently
using it.
The pipelined CPU can thus send another instruction
in the fetch stage to begin its execution.
At this clock cycle 2, there are multiple
instructions being executed at the same time.
Hence we have what is called instruction level
parallelism or ILP.
At clock cycle 3, the CPU sends the first
instruction to the execute stage, the second
instruction to the decode stage, and the third
instruction to the fetch stage.
Using this approach, the CPU can have one
instruction being executed in each stage at
all times.
However, note that we cannot have multiple
instructions in the same stage at the same
time.
This is done only by Superscalar CPUs.
Right now, we only have a pipelined CPU.
Using pipelining method, our code can take
7 cycles instead of 18 cycles, doubling its
performance.
One interesting note about pipelining is that
some instructions may need to go to pipeline
stages that they don’t use.
For example, the double word instruction doesn’t
need the memory stage, because it doesn’t
read or write data.
But since, it must go to the writeback stage
to write the result in the register, it has
to go through the
Memory.
This is because in the pipelined design, the
CPU simply moves an instruction from one stage
of the pipeline to the next stage until it
completes.