Let us take a look at structural hazards in
more detail.
Consider the code here.
Remember that in our CPU, there is only one
ALU.
That same ALU is used by the fetch stage of
the pipeline to increment the program counter
by four and is used by the execute stage for
operations.
In this example, at clock cycle 3, the first
instruction is in the execute stage and the
third instruction is in the fetch stage.
Therefore, both instructions need to use the
ALU at the same cycle.
Here is another example of structural hazard.
Let us assume our CPU has only one memory
port.
The same port is used by the instruction fetch
stage and by the memory stage.
In this example, the first instruction needs
to use the memory port at cycle 4 in order
to load the data from memory and the fourth
instruction needs to use the port at cycle
4 to fetch the instruction.
The main way to mitigate structural hazards
is by replicating resources.
Therefore, we can add two ALUs in our CPU,
one for the instruction fetch stage to increment
the counter, the program counter.
And another in the execute stage to perform
the functionalities of the instructions.
Note that structural hazards rarely occur
in modern processors because they have several
replications of resources for different stages.