Branch hazards occur when there is a branch
instruction the CPU needs to fetch the next
instruction in the pipeline.
Since the result of the branch condition and
the target address of the branch will not
be available until the execute stage, the
CPU does not what to fetch.
Consider the example here.
At cycle 4, the CPU fetches the instruction
at address E0.
In the next cycle, that instruction moves
to the decode stage.
To keep the pipeline busy, the CPU needs to
fetch a new instruction at that same cycle.
However, the CPU does not yet know if the
branch is taken or what that target address
is in that case.
Although we have described the branch hazards
for conditional branches, the same issue occurs
for unconditional jump instructions because
the target address is calculated at the execute
stage of the pipeline.
There are several ways to overcome branch
hazards.
The most naïve way is to simply stall the
CPU execution until the branch instruction
goes to the execute stage to calculate the
target address.
This is known as a pipeline bubble.
In fact, pipeline bubble can be used to mitigate
just about every hazard.
The issue with pipeline bubble is that it
does not optimize the use of the pipeline.
If we have to always stall due to hazards,
then the benefits of pipelining are limited.
Another approach to mitigate branch hazards
is for the compiler to add a branch delay
slot after each branch instruction.
A branch delay slot is essentially an instruction
within the program code that can be executed
whether the branch is taken or not.
This is similar to the instruction reordering
approach.
The most common approach to mitigate branch
hazards, however, is by using branch prediction.
The basic idea here is to predict if the branch
is taken or not based on past history.
The CPU has a table to keep the history of
each branch instruction.
For example, for each branch instruction,
the table holds its last target address and
whether the branch was taken the last few
times it was executed.
The CPU then uses that pattern of the last
few times the branch was executed to predict
if it will be taken and to provide the CPU
the target address at the fetch stage.
Branch predictors are over 99% accurate in
modern processors.
Branch hazards occur when there is a branch
instruction the CPU needs to fetch the next
instruction in the pipeline.
Since the result of the branch condition and
the target address of the branch will not
be available until the execute stage, the
CPU does not what to fetch.
Consider the example here.
At cycle 4, the CPU fetches the instruction
at address E0.
In the next cycle, that instruction moves
to the decode stage.
To keep the pipeline busy, the CPU needs to
fetch a new instruction at that same cycle.
However, the CPU does not yet know if the
branch is taken or what that target address
is in that case.
Although we have described the branch hazards
for conditional branches, the same issue occurs
for unconditional jump instructions because
the target address is calculated at the execute
stage of the pipeline.
There are several ways to overcome branch
hazards.
The most naïve way is to simply stall the
CPU execution until the branch instruction
goes to the execute stage to calculate the
target address.
This is known as a pipeline bubble.
In fact, pipeline bubble can be used to mitigate
just about every hazard.
The issue with pipeline bubble is that it
does not optimize the use of the pipeline.
If we have to always stall due to hazards,
then the benefits of pipelining are limited.
Another approach to mitigate branch hazards
is for the compiler to add a branch delay
slot after each branch instruction.
A branch delay slot is essentially an instruction
within the program code that can be executed
whether the branch is taken or not.
This is similar to the instruction reordering
approach.
The most common approach to mitigate branch
hazards, however, is by using branch prediction.
The basic idea here is to predict if the branch
is taken or not based on past history.
The CPU has a table to keep the history of
each branch instruction.
For example, for each branch instruction,
the table holds its last target address and
whether the branch was taken the last few
times it was executed.
The CPU then uses that pattern of the last
few times the branch was executed to predict
if it will be taken and to provide the CPU
the target address at the fetch stage.
Branch predictors are over 99% accurate in
modern processors.