Ok so let’s try to use all the syntax we
talked about integers to implement a simple
problem.
We name it weeks and days problem.
So let’s write a program that reads from
the user number of days they traveled.
And then the program would print what’s
the travelling time in the format of how many
full weeks they traveled and how many additional
days are there.
For example if we executed this program the
program would ask the user please enter the
number of days you traveled.
The user would say for example 19 and then
the program would respond 19 days or two weeks
and five days.
Because 19 days are two full weeks and extra
five days.