Let’s stop for a minute and roll back to
I don’t know second grade.
And recall what our math teacher used to say
when we divide 13 by 5.
So when we divide 13 by 5 we get something
like 2 with a remainder of 3.
Basically means 5 fits into 13 two full times
and there is still a remainder after these
two full times of 3.
There are two designated operators that give
us these 2 and 3 they are called div and mod.
For example if we do 13 div 5 we get 2.
Which basically div means how many full times
times 5 fits in 13.
So 13 div 5 results to 2.
And 13 mod 5 results to 3.
Basically meaning what’s the remainder when
we are dividing 13 by 5.
In C++ we don’t use div and mod in the textual
writing there are specific symbols to do div
and mod.
For div we have the slash operator so if we
have int slash int that would do a div operator
in this case that would be 2.
And for mod we will use the percent symbol
so 13 percent 5 would be 3 for the remainder
when we divide 13 by 5.