Let’s implement this program so first let’s
ask the user to enter the number of days they
travel so cout. And then please enter number
of days you traveled. Let’s break the line
end line. And then let’s read whatever the
user enters into a variable. Since it is number
of days int is the type we want to use here.
We first have to declare this variable so
int. And then we have to decide what the name
of this variable would be. In my previous
examples I just used x y z whatever because
they had no meaning just to show you the syntax
of integers. But here in this program this
variable would be used to store some significant
kind of data. It is going to store the days
user traveled. So let’s give it meaningful
name in this case I would name it days traveled.
But then I can’t have a variable name days
traveled made of two words. So I need to somehow
create a single word that would be made of
more than one word in it. So there are a few
common conventions on how to do that. One
way is to separate the word something like
underscore symbol something like that into
days traveled. Another convention could be
something like to capitalize the beginning
of each word days traveled and then easily
you can see what this long sequence of characters
basically mean. Third convention is to start
capitalizing only from the second word so
the first d is lower case then the t for the
travel is uppercase. For variable names the
common C++ convention is something like that.
Capitalizing each word starting with the second
word so int days traveled this is the variable
name we will choose here. And then cin days
traveled that’s the variable we are going
to read into. Now that we have the input from
the user so we ask the user to enter the number
of days they traveled. We read these days
into this variable now we should calculate
how many full weeks and what’s the remaining
days. So just as I spoke it the variable names
should be probably full weeks and remaining
days. So let’s declare two additional variables
one I would name full weeks. Note that I am
using this convention lower case f upper case
w. And remaining days once again lower case
r upper case d. You can also note that when
you declare more than one variable of the
same type you can do it in a single line of
code and separate the variables with a comma.
In this case I declared two variables in this
line both of them are of type int. One named
full weeks and the other remaining days. So
right here after we have the number of days
traveled in order to figure out the number
of full weeks we said we should div it by
7. So we do full weeks equals days traveled
div 7 right. That’s the number of full weeks
and the remaining days would be numbers of
days traveled mod 7. So remaining days equals
day traveled mod 7. So I am using the percent
sign here. So I have these values so now that
I have calculated the amount of full days
and how many days are remaining I can output
the message to the user cout. And I want it
to be in the format of in the case of the
input of 19 19 days or two weeks and five
days. So let’s start with days traveled
which would be our 19 and then days are which
would be full weeks as a string. And then
the remaining days days. After that we want
to break the line something like that. So
we have in the case of the input of 19 19
days are two weeks and five days. This should
be fine let’s execute it and see if we need
to make some minor changes. So I am compiling
it I am just pressing the play button here.
And please enter the number of days you traveled.
I entered 19 and then it says 19 days are
two weeks and five days. There is a spacing
issue here and actually it makes sense because
we printed days traveled and then the text
days are with no spaces. So if we want to
space 19 and days we have to add a space over
here. We should also add a space here before
the two so there would be 19 space days space
are space and then two and then again we need
to add a space here and a space here and also
space here. Now it should look better let’s
execute it. Once again let’s enter the input
19 and then it would say 19 days are two weeks
and five days. Seems to work perfectly fine.
One last thing that I want to update here
is the use of 7 here. So as you can see we
have the variables days traveled full weeks
remaining days. They are all variables with
type int they are all data of type int they
are all integers. And then we use 7 here and
7 here are also integers because they are
C++ literals but this 7 is not an arbitrary
numbers. We use 7 because 7 is the number
of days in a week. A lot of times we prefer
to define our own constant to represent this
value. To make our code more clear. We typically
define constants above the main. We can define
it just next to the variables as well. Maybe
later on we will discuss what’s the difference
of the location where we define our variables
and constants. But for now let’s define
constants before the main. So up here I will
do constant int and now I want to define a
constant that the value would be 7. I am trying
to think what I should name this integer constant
and typically I choose the name by what it
represents by describe what it represents.
So 7 represents the number of days in a week.
For constants the common convention for constant
name is using all upper case and separating
t he words with underscore. So it would be
days in a week and then I would set it to
7. So not like variables where we define the
variable all lower case and separate the words
starting with the second one with upper case.
In constants we have a different naming convention
where we type the entire text as uppercase
and separates the words with underscore. So
days in a week equals 7 and then instead of
just typing 7 here I would just divide it
by days in a week and I would mod it by days
in a week. So when someone reads our code
now they can see that full weeks are basically
days traveled div the numbers of days in a
week. And the remaining days are days traveled
mod the number of days in a week. There is
no supposed to be any effect on the execution
just instead of writing the literal 7 we define
our own constant with the value of 7. So here
when we type 19 we just get once again two
weeks then five days.