Let’s talk about some more stuff regarding
integers.
For example what are the literals that are
built in inside C++ for integers.
Maybe let’s take a step aside here and understand
what do we mean when we say C++ literals.
So when we are talking about data basically
data can come into two major forms either
variables or constants.
Variables are as we can understand by their
name can change their values where constants
are values that are constants cannot be changed.
So if we look at these lines of code here
we see that we have x and y which are variables
we can see that we can set their values x
equals 6 and then set it to 7 or to 8 or whatever
they are variables their value can change.
And then there are also some constants here
in this program.
As we said every data in C++ is has a type
of its own C++ is a strongly typed language.
So 6 -6 even 0 way down there are all of some
type in this case they would be of type integers.
So we can see that they are variables we can
declare them let’s say int x later on we
can define double y or whatever type we want
to see for each variable.
And then there are also contants and then
for constants we talk about two kinds of constants
one that are built in inside our language
when we name C++ literals.
Basically we don’t need to define 6 or -6
or 7.3 or abc we don’t need to define what
these values are the compiler already recognizes
them they are built in inside programming
language.
But we can also define our own constants we
can create a program and define contants.
The syntax for that goes something like cons
int max = 5 and in this case we are creating
a constant of type integer its name is max
and the value is set to 5.
We will talk more about it later on but the
major idea here is once we set max with 5
this value cannot change cannot set max to
7 after a few lines of code.
Once we created a constant that value is there
to stay.
So let’s get back to literals of type int
what kind of built in data the compiler recognizes
as integers.
So as we can expect writing numbers in their
decimal representation just like 3 4 -6 3954
or whatever number you want the compiler would
recognize them as integers.
So we can use them and we know that they are
considered to be integers.