Ok so let’s get into the details of int
of the data type for integers.
So integers as we said are used to store integer
numbers so every time we want an integer number
we use the type int.
Let’s see how this int data is represented
inside the memory of our computer.
What is the inner representation of an int.
So there are basically two options here.
Either each data would be of a different size
for example smaller numbers would take less
space less bits in order to represent them.
And larger number would take more space in
order to represent them.
That would make integers be of a different
sizes.
Another option would be that every int data
would have a fixed amount of bytes in its
representation.
There are advantages and disadvantages for
each one of these options and C++ the data
types the int datas are all of the same size.
Each int data is four bytes long which is
32 bits each byte is 8 bits so four bytes
is 32 bits.
So each integer is 32 bits long.
For example if we have an integer x then inside
our memory there would be four bytes for this
x.
Let’s say starting at address 100 until
104.
If we have an integer y after x would come
this four bytes for the y from 104 to 108.
So each int data uses four bytes.
So I think the greatest disadvantage of a
fixed size variables or fixed size data is
that we can say that 32 bits is quite a lot
we can represent two to the power of 32 different
values in 32 bits.
Two to the power of 32 by the way is around
four billion different numbers so there are
a lot of numbers we can represent in an int
variable.
But then if we were thinking about that integer
number domain it is an infinite domain and
if our program would like to represent a number
that are very big for example astronomical
distances then 32 bits won’t be enough for
that kind of data.
So that’s the biggest disadvantage of using
a fixed size data but then there are also
a lot of advantages of using fixed size data
and we will talk more about them in more detail
when we speak about arrays later on in this
course.
Ok so inside the memory each integer takes
four bytes let’s think how the integer is
represented inside these four bytes.
What bits what zeroes and ones would be used
in order to represent an integer data.
So when we talked in one of our previous modules
about number systems we saw that we can represent
numbers using zeroes and ones using the binary
number system base two.
And then since integer can also be negative
numbers we talked about the 2’s complement
representation method and that’s how integers
are represented in C++ the numbers are basically
represented in 32 bit 2’s complement representation
method.
So for example if we set x to 6 obviously
6 decimal is 110 in base 2 but if we are thinking
about the 2’s complement representation
of 6 basically we are padding it with zeroes
so 6 then is this representation in a 32 bit
2’s complement.
So these 4 bytes these 32 bits are then placed
inside the 4 bytes of x.
If we set y to -6 then again -6 as a decimal
are represented like in a 32 bit 2’s complement
representation method and these 4 bytes are
then taken inside the y’s location in the
memory.
So the numbers are represented in four bytes
and using the 2’s complement representation
method that’s a very important thing to
know about integers.