So, there's a lot of ways to implement threads
and a lot of these are leftovers from an older
era where the operating systems didn't actually
support the threads, but programmers wanted
to use threaded concepts inside their programs.
So, the first way to implement a thread is
what we know as a kernel level thread.
Now this is very different from a kernel thread,
and this is very different from kernel mode.
This is the concept where the operating system
recognizes that a thread has been created
and the operating system will create a TCB
for that thread and the operating system can
choose to run that thread or can choose to
block that thread and all the states that
go along with that thread.
The other main way of doing this is what we
know is user level thread, and this is really
a leftover of a bygone era although that still
very much in use today.
The biggest downside of a user level thread,
actually the way that a user level thread
works is that the operating system doesn't
recognize that the threads are in use.
So, it sees this thread as a process, let's
say, so let's take for example an operating
system that doesn't support threads.
Well how can we run threads?
We can have a library of code inside of our
program, which creates or simulates creating
of threads and switching between these threads.
So, what would be required would be some scheduling
algorithms and some ability to create new
threads and destroy threads, inside a user's
program.
But all of this is a simulation and the operating
system doesn't really know that multiple threads,
if you want to call them that, are being created
here.
Instead what it does is recognize that one
process is being created.
And the biggest downside to that is that if
any of those threads, and I use quotations,
those threads cause a blocking system call
then all of those threads are going to be
blocked because the OP running system just
sees it as a single process.
So, that's the idea behind a user level thread.
The advantage of a user level thread is that
you can choose to do whatever scheduling algorithm
you want; you're not at the behest of the
operating system.
in a kernel level thread the operating system
decides when your threads are going to run,
but in a user level thread you, the programmer,
decide when that thread is going to run and
how often it's going to be run.
So, you could have three threads and give
priority to one of the three threads to run
more frequently than the other two, and you
can't do that with kernel level threads easily.
The hybrid approach takes benefits from each.
So, the hybrid approach, which was first implemented
by an operating system known as Solaris or
best implemented by an operating system the
Solaris, what they did was they created both
kernel level threads and they created a user
level thread.
And they tied the two together by means of
what was known as a lightweight process, and
the lightweight process is simply a container.
So, we can put a number of user level threads
inside of a lightweight process and we can
choose to run that lightweight process on
one kernel level thread, so when a kernel
of a thread becomes available the lightweight
process runs.
And all of the user level threads in that
process are run according to the scheduling
library of that lightweight process.
So, you as the programmer would create a lightweight
process; you’d creates a number of user
level threads.
You’d assign the user level threads that
you wanted to run to the lightweight process,
but you can create any combination of user
level threads and lightweight processes.
So, if you had a very important user level
thread, you would create one lightweight process
for that one user level thread and any time
that lightweight process ran that one user
level thread would be the only one running.
Then you could take three other user level
threads, that are not critical, and put them
on one lightweight process.
So that when that lightweight process runs
any of the user level threads inside could
run.
Of course, the same downside occurs as with
user level threads, if one of the user level
threads in the lightweight process blocks;
all of the threads in the lightweight process
will be blocked.
As far as thread scheduling is concerned,
there's both a global scheduling algorithm
that chooses to run the kernel level threads
and then there's a local scheduling algorithm,
which you can implement you can manage yourself
as the programmer, that would choose which
of the user level threads associated with
that lightweight process would be chosen to
run.