We'd like to talk about the five state process
model, and we're going to be talking about
each individual state.
Now what is a state?
Well a state is one condition that a program
might be in and the process is going to spend
quite a significant amount of time in each
state.
So each state has to be recognized and has
to be recorded by the operating system.
So let's go through the five different states
that a process could be in, and you'll have
a better understanding of why the process
is in each of these states.
So, the first state is the new state and all
processes start out in a new state.
Now we have to recognize that the process
is going to spend quite a significant amount
of time in each of these states.
So, why would a process spend a significant
amount of time in the new state.
We have to think about the process being created
and the procedure that we would go through
to create a process inside the operating system.
And the new state is when that process is
being executed by the operating system.
Now one thing that we need to recognize is
that a state is an atomic element.
And if the operating system can complete everything
atomically, then there's really no reason
to have a state.
So, the new state happens because the process
is being created and the code for that process,
one of the reasons is the code for that process
will have to be loaded from a secondary storage
device into main memory.
And that's an IO operation and I operate generally
take an enormous amount of time, and we'll
see this in a later model, but for now we
just say that an IO operation takes a really
long time.
And the operating system doesn't want to sit
in wait for the IO operation to complete;
it wants to go on to do other things.
But it needs to keep track of where this process
is in the act of creation and the way to do
that is the new state.
So all processes in the new state are in the
act of being created and their code being
loaded into main memory.
Once the process finishes loading and can
be run, then the process moves not to the
running state, unfortunately, but to the ready
state.
And the ready state is that point where the
operating system has all the processes which
actually have all their parts ready to go.
These are only waiting for a processor to
become available so that we can load the process
onto the processor and actually let it run.
Remember from our hardware discussion, that
the processor is the only location where code
can actually be run in the system.
So, the processes that are on the ready state
have everything that they need in order to
run but they're not quite running yet because
there's no processor available.
Once the processor becomes available, the
process is going to move from the ready state
into the running state and then it will actually
be running on the processor and doing some
real work.
This is called a dispatch operation.
Once the processor either times out, or the
process makes a blocking system call, or the
process ends altogether, the process is going
to stay in the running state until one of
those three things happens and then it's going
to move to the ready state, the block state,
or the exit state accordingly.
Now we already understand what the ready state
is we've seen that just a second ago.
But what's the block state?
Well what happens if the process makes some
sort of request which is going to take a really
significant amount of time.
The operating system doesn't want to stand
and wait, waiting for that process to do what
it's asking to do.
And so it moves the process into the block
state to indicate that this process is no
longer ready to run; it is not running but
it's not quite done yet.
And the process is going to wait in the block
state until whatever action it's requested
finishes, and then it's going to move from
the block state instead back into the ready
state.
And then eventually from the ready state to
the running state and from the running state
back to the ready state when it times out.
And this process will happen from ready to
running to blocked, ready to running, to ready
to running, and so on and so forth until the
process finally finishes.
And when it's done the process moves to the
exit state.
And in the exit state the process is just
waiting to be cleaned up and terminated.
And there's one key element that has to be
returned back to the parent process, which
we'll talk about later and linkages, and that
is the return value.
Remember return zero from int main, well that
has to be given back to the parent process.
And a process that in the exit state has not
yet returned back its element, its return
value, to the parent process and that's why
we have the five states that we have.