We also add to the concept of the states with
the idea that the process may be suspended.
Now suspension is a bit of an odd notion in
that the process is sort of still ready to
run but it isn't actually running or runnable
yet.
In suspension, the process will be completely
removed from main memory; so, obviously its
code can't run because this code isn't loaded
in main memory.
So, in suspension we completely take the process
out of main memory and move it to a secondary
storage device or even maybe a tertiary storage
device, if we really don't have any memory.
Why would we have this?
Well one of the biggest reasons for having
a concept of suspension is that we can free
up main memory.
If we get to the point where main memory is
starting to fill up, with so many processes
or with such large processes, that we no longer
have a lot of processes that are ready to
run we might get into a condition where the
process list has nothing on the ready state;
everything is in the block state and there's
no more memory available to allocate to new
processes.
So, we aim to free up that memory by suspending
one or more processes and this is done by
what's known as the medium term scheduling
algorithm.
And the medium term scheduling algorithm will
choose which process to suspend, and then
it will take that process and put it on the
secondary storage device.
Now, this doesn't mean that the process is
terminated because we can certainly reload
all the code data and context from the secondary
storage device back into main memory at a
later time and then run that process, just
as if nothing ever happened.
So it's very possible for any of your programs
your ‘Hello World’ style programs from
previous modules, that could have been suspended
at some point.
We might have suspended the process just simply
for debugging purposes; we might have suspended
the proper process at the request of the user
doing a control Z on a Unix system.
But the point is that we need to add States
to our five state process model to recognize
the possibility that the process is suspended.
And we actually need to add two different
suspended states, because we need to recognize
if a process is suspended and ready to run
or if it's suspended and blocked for some
reason.
And the movement into and out of the suspended
states is relatively easy.
If the process was in the block state than
during suspension it would be moved to the
block suspended state, and if it was in the
ready state during suspension it would be
moved to the ready suspended state.
If it some point in time in the block suspended
state, the event that we were waiting for
occurs then the process would be moved from
the block suspended state to the ready suspended
state.
So, we evolve our concept of the process model
from a five state process model into a seven
state process model, where we add these two
suspended states.