So, if we take a deeper look into the contents
of the PCB, what we're going to see is a lot
of the context information for the process.
We're going to see things like the numeric
identifiers.
The numeric identifiers that we have just
a few examples of, are the process identifier.
Now that's one process identifier is assigned
to each process in the system and this is
a simple word, it's only sixteen bytes, sorry…
sixteen bits large and the PID has to be unique
for all the processes.
So, you're starting to come to the idea that
the maximum number of processes in the system
is 65,535 because that's the maximum number
of process identifiers that we have.
We're also going to keep track of the parent
process identifier.
Now each process is going to be created by
a parent, and the parent has certain responsibilities
and rights over that child process.
The parent can terminate the child.
The parent can receive the child's information
when the child finishes; the return zero value
so to speak.
So, the parent process identifier needs to
be recorded as part of the information that
we're going to use to manage that process.
We're going to record the user identifier,
of the person who started that process.
The UID is important because it leads to the
security perimeter restrictions that are placed
onto that program.
What can this program do is based on who activated
this process.
And we're going to talk about registers, inside
the PCB; we have a number of registers, now
those are for when the process is either in
the blocked or the ready state.
When it's in the running state remember the
process is actually running, so the registers
are constantly changing.
But those registers have to be recorded every
time we pull the process out of the running
state and they need to be reloaded back into
the CPU whenever we restore the process to
the running state.
We're going to have the stack pointers.
So, any stack pointers that this process might
have in this case is probably only going to
be one stack pointer later on, we're going
to see where there's a possibility of having
more.
Scheduling: so how long has this process been
on the CPU, how much time has it spent, how
long has it been waiting, when should reschedule
it to wait, and so on and so forth.
Any linkages: if this process is linked to
another process in terms of a pipe, so that
the output of this process goes to the input
of another process, this has to be managed
via the PCB.
Any into process communication systems that
might be enabled inside this process, so any
communications that the process is having
with other processes in the system.
And the resources in use, so IO devices or
files and how much memory is being used.
That makes up the contents of the entire PCB.
and that's what the operating system really
uses to manage the process.
The PCB. might be moved from state to state,
or the PCB. might coincide with the process
image, but either way we're going to keep
all this information about the process in
order to manage it.