So, a process that's in the running state
will stay in the running state until something
happens, and we need to understand what happens
to cause the process to come out of the running
state, and how that might affect user mode
and kernel mode.
Well first off, a process switch is going
to occur during one of the events either an
interrupt a trap or a blocking system call.
During an interrupt, some piece of hardware
has indicated that it needs immediate servicing,
and so the operating system must be invoked
in order to take care of that hardware.
Now the hardware could be any piece, we can
think of a wireless device; a wireless access
card where it has a small amount of memory
and the buffer is starting to fill up.
If the buffer actually gets full then any
new data that's coming in through the wireless
card is going to be lost, because the buffer
is full.
So, the solution to this is for the network
card to send an interrupt to the CPU.
And what happens in an interrupt is the CPU
will finish executing the instruction that
it's running, and then it will switch to running
the operating system.
And the operating system has a specific point
that it uses, it's called the Interrupt Service
Routine, the ISR.
The ISR runs whenever an interrupt occurs;
the processor knows to switch to the operating
system’s ISR, and of course since it's switching
from a running program to the kernel; it switches
from user mode to kernel mode and it runs
the ISR.
We could also have a trap; now this is a situation
where the process has done something that
causes it to need the operating system, even
though it doesn't know it needs the operating
system.
And we can also have a blocking system call;
these are obvious like the program is trying
to open up a file.
If the program is trying to open up a file,
it's going to need to invoke components of
the operating system and so the responsibility
switches.
The process will switch to running the operating
system and when it does that the operating
system will take care of opening up the file
and reading in the data.
Now a process which involves quite a lot of
steps, most importantly, we need to save the
context of that process.
We’re gonna save that in the PCB.
And then we need to move that PCB into the
appropriate queue whether it's the blocked
queue or the ready queue to indicate what
we're going to next do with this process,
and then we need to service whatever was requested;
deal with the interrupt, deal with the blocking
system call or deal with the trap.
And then choose another process that's ready
to run so we're going to look to the ready
queue and choose one of the processes on the
ready queue to move into the running state.
And then we're going to actually run that
new process by restoring its context.
This gets a little bit more complex if we
talk about multi processors, and the idea
of multiprocessor we might have more than
one process on the running state at any given
time. and so that's going to have some effect
on performance.