Okay. So, let's take a look at another search
algorithm; basically it's a variation of the
general searching problems algorithms, named
the sorted search problem. in this case we’ll
implement the function, a sorted search, where
we’re given a sorted array, sorted A R R,
that's the name of our array. Which means
that the elements are ordered in this array
in an increasing order, so we get the sorted
array and its logical size and again a val
to search for. And same thing, so if val appears
in the sorted array, let's just return one
of the indexes where it appears. We’re not
really interested in finding the first appearance
of value in a sorted array, so let's just
return an index where val appears. And once
again, if val is not one of A R R elements,
we’ll just return a negative one. For example,
if our sorted array is five, seven, eight,
eight, ten, and twelve, again notice that
the elements are ordered in increasing order,
then when we call this sorted search function
for this array of size six searching for eight,
we'll just return an index where eight appears;
in this case eight appears in index two and
three, we could arbitrarily return three.