Let's implement the sorted search function.
So I have here a main program that I created,
a sorted array. Notice that the elements in
this array are increasing order, one, three,
five, seven, nine, and so on. And I've made
it call to the sorted search function, that
is given the array, sorted array and its logical
size of ten. and for example we're searching
for thirteen here, and thirteen does appear
over here so we're expecting to get the index
of thirteen, which is zero, one, two, three,
four, five, six; so, we're expecting to get
a six out in this print statement. And let's
just implement the sorted search function
so this program can execute. I have this prototype
up here; let’s copy it and do our implementation,
so something like that. And okay. So, let's
get started.
So, we have our sorted array, something like
that, and each time we are limiting half of
the range. So, let's have two indexes to indicate
the valid range we're searching initially;
let's name the low and high. So, initially
they are set to the entire range of the array,
so let's create two variables low and high
and set them initially low to zero and high
to the last index of the array, which is the
sorted array size minus one. And then, we
should start iterating each time eliminating
half of the valid range. For that we would
use a while loop, right. We don't know exactly
how many iterations we're going to have so
let's use a while loop here. And I'll keep
the Boolean condition here empty for now,
till we figure out exactly what's the body
of the loop it would be easier for us to state
that really in condition.
Okay. Another thing I think it's good to set
from the beginning would be a Boolean flag
that indicates if we found the value val we
are searching for or still haven't done that.
So, let's have Boolean variable name found,
that would be set initially found to false
and when we find our value we'll update it
to true, but initially it would be false.
And then let's start iterating, so each iteration
we are searching the range from low to high;
and we said we're not searching it linearly,
we are taking the middle point and comparing
the value we have in here, to the value we're
searching for. So, for example if our value
were searching is as we had before seventy
nine, let's take the middle point and compare
it to seventy nine. So let's have a mid index;
so we have mid. And let's set mid to the middle
between a low and high. So mid would be…
how can we figure out what mid should be?
So mid, in order to be the middle between
low and high is basically the average between
low and high. So low plus high over two; that's
the value of mid, so let's set mid to low
plus high over two. Notice that since low
and high are both integers, obviously, low
plus high is also an integer and since two
is an integer literal then these two operands
of the dividing slash here are integers basically
saying that C++ would interpret this slash
as a div not as a real division. Which is
very good for us because we don't really want
mid to be the real average between low and
high; it should be a valid index, an integer
value.
So, div basically takes it floored down which
is an estimation of the point; it could be
offsetted one index to the left. So, we have
the middle position and now we should compare
val to the array in the middle position. So
let's see if, and in here there could be a
few values, so for example if we're lucky
the value in sorted array at the middle position
is val, exactly the value we're looking for,
in this case we should raise the flag basically
say that found is true. Right? So if in here
we have, for example seventy nine, then basically
we're done. We should just say that val, that
found is true, and break out of the function
return the index we’re at. Actually, I don't
want to break the while loop by a return statement
so I'll just save the position that val is
found so I'll create another integer named
ind where I’ll store this index and I'll
set ind to be the mid point basically where
value is right that is at the mid index. So
if we found val, we are storing the index
and setting found to true. Hopefully that
would help us breakout of the while loop;
we’ll take care of it in a few minutes when
we state the Boolean condition.
But most likely we won't be so lucky and we
won't get seventy nine right here in the beginning.
So, let's see, else if we’re as we said
not so lucky and value isn't exactly as sorted
array mid, we should compare it and see how
what relational order they have. So, for example
if we have say ninety six, or in other words
if our val is less then sorted A R R at the
middle position, right; like we have here
where seventy nine is less than ninety six.
In this case, as we said, we can eliminate
all of that range right. In order to do that,
we should then just said high over here right;
so, we can basically create that as our valid
range. To do that let's say that high in this
case should equal to mid minus one right.
We ruled out all the elements there are to
the left, to the right, actually of ninety
six. Okay, so that takes care of that.
But another case could be if we have here
a value instead of ninety six that is a value
that is less than seventy nine. So if we have
instead of ninety six, let's say fifty one;
so we're in an else right. So sorted A R R
mid is not seventy nine, sorted A R R mid
is not greater than seventy nine, not greater
than val. In this case, that mid … maybe
comment and say that we are in the case where
val is greater, seventy nine is greater, than
the sorted array in the middle position.
In this case, we can eliminate all of these
elements and to do that we just set low to
here, right. So we should just say low equals
mid plus one, right; setting the valid range
to this half of our searching range. Let's
take a look at the body we have for the while
loop so each iteration we’re figuring out
where the middle index is and then we’re
checking whether the middle element is exactly
the value we're searching for, in this case
where saving this position and hopefully raising
the flag that would lead us to break out of
the while. Otherwise if we are not so lucky
we are comparing val to the element that is
in the middle position; if val is less than
we are eliminating all the right values, the
values that are greater than the middle position
basically setting high to mid minus one. Otherwise,
we're eliminating all the values to the left
of the middle position, basically saying that
low is mid plus one and we do that over and
over. While, so obviously, while found is
still false right. We initially set found
to false, so we want to keep on iterating
while found is still false. But there are
cases where found would never become true,
right. So, if the value val appears in sorted
A R, eventually we'll close on it and find
its position, but in case value doesn't appear
in sorted A R R at all found would never become
true, and we want to be able to break out
of this while loop in that case as well.
So, in order to figure out what we need to
do here. Let's take a closer look; I’ll
maybe try to demonstrate it on a small numerical
example. So let's take a new array of three
elements, let’s have, I don't know, two,
five, seven; these are our elements. There
are indexes: zero, one, two. So, initially
we have low and high over here, right. And
let's try to execute this code and see what
happens if we are searching for a value that
is not in this array, let's search for four,
right. Obviously, we should figure out that
it doesn't appear there. Let's try to execute
the code. So, initially mid would be low plus
high div two, basically zero plus two. That's
two div two, two div two that’s one. So
mid would be here, right. And then we’re
trying to compare if in index one element
equals val, equals four, that's not true right.
Our value here, five, does not equal four.
In this case, we should then continue on.
So if val four is less then what we have in
the middle position which is five, so four
is less than five which is true, then we should
set high to be mid
minus one, which makes a lot of sense right.
If four would appear here, it wouldn't be
in the right half, it would be in the left
half.
So, let's set high to being mid minus one;
so high would then be right here. So high
would be zero as well. Okay. So we have both
low and high at zero position; another iteration
mid would be low plus high div two, zero plus
zero div two that would be zero as well. So,
our mid would also be here. Once again we’re
checking whether the element we’re searching
in, which is basically the only element in
our valid range, the one and only element
in our range. So, two is it equal to val,
to four? It is not, so or we should check
whether val four is less than the element
we have in the middle; is four less than two,
that's not true as well. So it means that
the val is greater than our middle element,
which is true four is greater than two, in
this case we said that we should make low
mid plus one.
So our low would go over here. Okay. So as
you can see, basically, low crossed over high;
always we have low to the left of high, right.
Initially low is to the left of high then
we change high to that half and again, low
is to the left of high and low would go over
here and it would be to the left of high and
high would go over here and a low would be
to the left high. But if we have one single
element here and it's not that element, low
would go over high and that basically means
that our element is not found.
So, in addition to looking whether the flag
is turned out to true or false. We should
always check whether our range is valid, basically
if low is less or equal to high. So, if both
we still haven't found our element, found
is still false, and our range is a still valid
range, low is still to the left of high, low
is less or equal to high, we want to keep
on iterating.
But if found becomes true, we want to break
out. If low crosses over high and low is not
less or equal to high, that means our val
doesn't appear, we want to break out. Okay.
So after this while loop, we should basically
check what's the reason we broke out; if we
found this element? So if found equals true
that means that val appears in sorted array
so we should just return the index we saved
earlier, this index here. But if found is
false, basically that means that we broke
out of the loop not because we found the element
but because our range is invalid, low is not
less or equal to high, in this case we should
just return negative one.
Okay, yeah. That seems to be the implementation
for this function. Let's try to execute it
and see if we get a six if we’re searching
for thirteen in this sorted array. Okay. We've
got a six here. Let's try to call it one more
time with an element that does not appear.
For example, it's fourteen and see that we
get a negative one here. Yeah. For fourteen
we got the negative one which seems to be
right. Yeah. So, just you know maybe it would
be a good idea if you try on your own, to
take an array with values and to trace it
on your own, but the idea here is just as
we've talked earlier. Let's try to analyze
the running time of this algorithm, right
now.