Okay.
So we've seen two searching algorithms: the
general search algorithm, which was linear
time, and sorted search, the binary search
algorithm which was a log of N time.
Now obviously a theta of log N is significantly
better than a theta of N, but I want to show
you or give you a better intuition what's
the meaning of this difference of log time
versus linear time.
So, you would really appreciate these kinds
of algorithms: the logarithmic time algorithms.
Let's try to compare the value of N versus
the value of log base two of N for several
values.
So, for example for N equals two, log two
of N would be log two of two which is one,
slightly better than N, one is obviously smaller
than two but doesn't seem such a big difference
not something to be too happy about.
Let's go on, for N equals four, I'm skipping
three by the way just because I want the log
of N to be integer values.
So, any value between two and four, in this
case three, would be somewhere in that range
and you see that later on as well.
So, for N equals four, log two of N is log
two of two squared which is four, that equals
two.
So again log two of four is less than four.
But again doesn't seem such a big difference;
let's go on.
Let's keep two eight two to the power of three;
let's take a look at log two of eight.
That would be log two of two to the power
three, that is three again better than eight
not something to get too crazy about.
Let's go to a larger value: two to the power
of ten, around one thousand right.
So one thousand on the N but log two of two
to the power of N, is only ten that starts
to be a greater difference here; a thousand
versus ten.
And let's go on, two to the power of thirty
two; to the power of thirty two, that's around
four point three billion.
When we're taking the log two of N that would
be a log two of two to the power of thirty
two, that it would be thirty two.
That already is quite a big difference: four
point three billion versus only thirty two.
So an algorithm that had to do four point
three operations versus an algorithm that
has to do only thirty two operations, the
thirty to one would run much faster.
But let's even go further; let's talk about
N equals two to the power of one thousand.
Now that is a huge number, it represents like
the quantity of two the power of one thousand
is greater than the number of the total number
of practicals in the universe.
So that's a huge number, obviously it would
take practically infinite time for an algorithm
to run, to execute two to the power of one
thousand instructions.
But a logarithmic algorithm, on the other
end, which has two log two of two to the power
of one thousand, would basically need to execute
only one thousand instructions and that is
less than the second.
So a logarithmic algorithm is much faster;
obviously as N grows but it's much faster
than the linear one.
And that's the thing to take into account
where we are implementing an algorithm, if
we can create a logarithmic algorithm that
we would give us a much better performance
than a linear one.
Just you can see that a linear function, if
we look at the graph of F of N equals N versus
a function equals to log of N, you can see
that they are both kind of growing.
I don't know if you can see that log of N
also grows to infinity very slow, but it also
grows to infinity.
If we zoom out this difference would even
be more visual.
Again, you can see that F of N equals N, the
linear function, grows very fast where the
logarithmic function actually seems very much
like a constant, almost doesn't grow at all.
It's kind of fascinating but it would grow
to infinity eventually but very very slowly.
So a logarithmic algorithm is it's a very
good resource, is very good algorithm.