So the mutual exclusion rules are real simple.
No two threads may be in a critical section
at the same time; it just means that we can
have two threads that are in the critical
section at the same time.
I know we said before that that is possible
if we're talking about two threads that are
working in critical sections on completely
different resources, and that's fine we're
not talking about that.
What we're talking about is when we have a
shared resource, we have to protect that shared
resource by not allowing any threads that
have that are in their critical section to
access that resource.
So, when no thread is in a critical section,
any thread that requests entry has to be allowed
in without delay.
And that means that we can't as the operating
system to act as a traffic cop; we can't say
to the operating system every time we want
to access a critical section: are we allowed
to access the critical section?
Because that would be a call to the operating
system and then the operating system is going
to have to stop and check and then run the
thread again, which requires context switching
in we talked about how expensive that is.
So, we'd rather have is the way for the thread
to check itself to see if it can go into its
critical section, to see if it's allowed to
go into its critical section, and if it is
to just go straight in and not stop.
If the thread is not allowed into its critical
section, of course, we're going to have to
have the thread pause, we’re gonna have
to have block and of course that's going to
involve the operating system because the thread
is going to move from the running state into
the block state and that means the operating
system has to be invoked.
But really we want to avoid any unnecessary
delay from the thread if it has to enter its
critical section; let it in as long as nobody
else is.
The other part about this is that the thread
can really only remain in its critical section
for a very small amount of time; we don't
want to have large sets of functions very
large functions with a lot of work in a critical
section, or in considered to be a critical
section, when all we need is a couple of lines
of code to be in that critical section.
So, we want to have that is minimal as possible;
we want to allow the thread to enter into
its critical section, do its work and then
get out as quickly as possible.