So, we need to look at the internals of the
semaphore and we need to have an understanding
of how the semaphore works internally.
So, what we're going to do is kind of piece
together what happens inside a semaphore,
without actually going through the nitty-gritty
of how the operating system creates a semaphore
and maintains a semaphore.
But what we do is we create a counter inside
the semaphore object, and the semaphore is
going to indicate how many signals, or the
counter is going to indicate how many signals
have been sent.
Each weight causes the counter to decrement
and if the counter ever becomes negative then
the thread that causes it to go negative,
and of course all subsequent threads, are
going to be blocked and then they're placed
on a queue.
Now the operating system maintains the queue,
and it's a queue of blocked threads waiting
for a signal on that semaphore.
So, that's going to be our indication that
we can release a thread, but they all go into
the blocked queue; all those threads that
come in and call wait, that cause the counter
to go negative, when the counter is negative
those threads are all blocked and the only
thread that's allowed to run is the one thread
that consumed the one and only signal.
Now when that thread is finished, it has to
send a signal, and if there are any threads
on the queue then the signal will cause the
counter to increment; first signal always
causes the counter to increment.
But it also releases the next thread in the
queue, if the counter actually goes positive
that means that there's nobody in the queue
waiting for a signal so there's nothing to
be done there, but we recognize that the signal
in the wait function allow us to create this
mutual exclusion environment.
Unfortunately, internally to the semaphore,
there exists the critical section; the act
of looking at the counter and then changing
the counter is itself a critical section.
So, here we have a mechanism that we're trying
to use to protect against critical sections,
and we created a critical section.
So, that's a real problem so we have to use
a hardware solution to prevent asynchrony
when the semaphore has to both check the counter
and set the counter.
So, this is where the semaphore is going to
use someone of the hardware options, either
disable interrupts or test and set, probably
exchange, and it's going to take care of it
internally.
So, we have to recognize that semaphore itself
has a critical section and it has that in
order to solve our critical section.