In this model we're going to continue our
discussion of threads and we're going to talk
about some of the features of having threads
work together with one another.
So we're going to talk just simply a quick
reminder about what threads are we're going
to talk about some features of having multiple
threads accessing multiple resources.
We're going to have a discussion on ways that
we can end up with a synchrony and what a
synchrony is.
We're going to talk about the idea of critical
sections.
We're going to talk about concurrency issues.
We're going to explain mutual exclusion and
talk about some software and hardware options
or solutions for mutual exclusion.
We're going to describe the operating system
semaphores and how they work.
We're going to describe deadlocks and how
we can resolve deadlocks and then we're going
to talk about the dining philosophers problem
as a wrap up problem.
So there's a lot to go through in this module
and we'll get started immediately.