I like this picture because it really shows
traffic inside a normal city environment.
And what we have here is that each of the
cars that would enter the intersection sort
of went a little bit over and are now blocking
a portion of the intersection.
And what you can see is that each car is waiting
for another car to move and the last car is
waiting for the first car to move, and ultimately
as you can tell, nothing is going to get done
here.
There is no way that any of these cars are
going to move until someone decides to take
action, and just completely change the scenario;
maybe one of the cars could make a turn and
get out of there and then free up the intersection.
But ultimately what's happening is we are
controlling one quadrant of the intersection,
each car controls one quadrant of the intersection,
and needs one more quadrant in order to complete
its task of moving through the intersection
and we recognize that that can never occur.