We talked about a lot during this module.
We talked about what threads are; we gave
a little reminder about the threads.
We talked about features of having multiple
threads accessing multiple resources and we
said that there was the possibility, of course,
that we could have asynchrony.
And if we do have the possibility of a synchrony,
we said that we need to identify critical
sections so that we can protect those critical
sections using concurrency control mechanisms.
And those concurrency control mechanisms that
we talked about are software and hardware
based.
We talked about the idea of mutual exclusion
using semaphores.
We talked about the design of the semaphores,
and how they work internally we also went
into how deadlocks occur and how we can prevent
deadlocks. and then we talked about the dining
philosophers problem.
So, we really covered a lot during this module.