So one of the nice features of having multiple
threads of course is that they can communicate
with one another.
Very easily we can have a lot of threads created
and all of the threads are accessing the same
memory in the same resources.
So, if we just for example created a buffer
in main memory and had all the threads have
access to the buffer then we wouldn't need
the operating system to intervene as we would
if we had multiple processes.
So, multiple processes can only communicate
with each other via IPC via the interprocess
communication system, but multiple threads
can communicate with one another directly
because they're both accessing or they're
all accessing the same amount of memory.
So this is a really effective solution.
For example when we’re reading in data from
an IO device we could have two threads one
that processes data that's already been read
in and another thread that's actually doing
the read operation.
So when the thread that's doing the read operation
performs a blocking system call to actually
bring in the data from the secondary storage
device the operating system blocks the thread,
but the other thread that's processing the
data is allowed to continue operating.
So, we have the ability to do a read in operation
while we're doing some processing on data
that's already been read in.
The other nice feature about having a thread
is that it's relatively easy to create.
It takes a very very little memory and we
can create it very quickly and easily as compared
to a process but the big downside of having
multiple threads is that we run the risk of
asynchrony we run the risk of these threads
doing something out of a normal order and
we're going to see that in this module.