So the code that I'm going to show you right
now is what we call a supplier demander example
and the supplier demander example really just
has multiple threads running of either a supplier
thread or demander thread.
In fact we're going to have multiple instances
of both suppliers and demanders.
So, think about a factory for example where
things are coming off the production line
there's a lot of people producing things,
there's a lot of people taking those things
and moving them on to the next stage in the
production.
So, we have both supplier and demander one
of the important considerations here and why
this has a critical section is that there
is a shared variable there what we're calling
the buffer and the buffer count is actually
two shared variables there.
The buffer count tells us how many items there
really are in the buffer.
Now you recognize from the code that the buffer
can store five hundred items.
The buffer count let's say it's initialized
at zero there's nothing in the buffer when
the morning starts the suppliers come in and
they start producing things that go into the
buffer.
Now the supplier just has a simple piece of
code that says as long as I'm not finished
then I'll put something in the buffer.
Now the reason that we have that while not
done is because it's possible that the buffer
is full and if the buffer is full we want
this thread to just kind of pause, pause for
maybe half a second and let one of the demanders
take something out of the buffer so it makes
space and then we can put this thing in the
buffer.
We can update the buffer count and then we
can be finished.
So the suppliers a very simple piece of code
the demander is almost the same thing except
it checks to see that there's actually something
in the buffer.
So the while not done here is for checking
to make sure that there actually is something
in the buffer rather than making sure that
the buffer is full as long as there is something
in the buffer we’ll decrement the buffer
count and return the item that was in the
buffer at the position.
So that's the supplier demander idea.
Now we do have multiple supplier threads and
multiple demander threads they're all active
they're all running in the system.
However we've got a uni processor system so
we can only run one thread at a time we choose
either supplier or we choose demander and
we have to remember that there are still going
to be interrupts they're still going to be
preemption there still going to be situations
where the thread is interrupted and we don't
know when it's going to be interrupted.
Now the core idea of this is that the buffer
count should never exceed five hundred.
We should never exceed five hundred because
there are only five hundred places to store
in the buffer.
So we can recognize that the buffer count
can get as high as five hundred but it can't
ever exceed five hundred.
Unfortunately as we'll see because of asynchrony
because we haven't taken care of the fact
that the code is protected by a critical section
that buffer count can easily go higher than
five hundred.
So we'll see that.