So here we can see the steps that we can run
through to produce this problem.
What we see here is that we're running the
supplier thread the buffer count is already
at four hundred ninety nine which means there's
only one slot left in the buffer that we can
fill up.
So at this point in the code the supplier
thread let's call it thread number one supplier
thread number one is going to be running.
It checks to make sure it's not done, it checks
to make sure that the buffer count is less
than five hundred, and the buffer count is
less than five hundred.
It's four hundred ninety nine so that thread
is allowed to enter that if statement.
It goes past that if statement and then out
in thread one right at that point for whatever
reason either because of preemption or because
of a hardware interrupt we get an interrupt
and after entering the if statement we haven't
made any changes but interrupts.
So, now we have an interrupt and when we run
from the interrupt, when we return from the
interrupt the operating system has to choose
a thread to run and it's not guaranteed that
it's going to choose thread one again.
So, what does it choose?
Unfortunately in this example it chooses to
run thread two.
So now Thread two is allowed to run and what
does thread two do?
The first thing it does of course is say while
not done is equal to while not done so it
says Yeah I'm not done checks the buffer count
buffer count is four hundred ninety nine.
So that's allowed, we enter into the if statement.
It adds the element to the buffer it increments
the buffer count now to five hundred so effectively
at this point the buffer is completely full
so thread two is finished thread two ends
and we're going to go back now and finish
out thread one.
But what's already happened is thread one
checked to make sure the buffer count was
less than five hundred and buffer count was
less than five hundred it was four ninety
nine the last time thread one ran but we didn't
take into account the critical section.
we didn't take into account the possibility
for asynchrony, so now we don't go back and
recheck the buffer count so the buffer count
now is five hundred but thread one the last
time it ran checked it was for ninety nine
so we left off at that opening curly brace
and that's what we're going to pick up from
and the first thing it does is increment buffer
count to five hundred and one.
How do we get to five hundred and one when
we only have five hundred positions in the
buffer.
So this is really the problem that we're going
to run into we don't have that extra one space
and it can get much much worse than this in
a real scenario but I'm just demonstrating
simply that we can run out of buffer space
and continue on if we don't take into account
the asynchrony that can happen between these
two threads.