Another example that we've got of a concurrency
control problem is one of a double update/missing
update situation.
And in this scenario what we have is two pieces
of code: just a deposit function and it withdraw
function.
So you can imagine a situation where you have
two ATM cards for the exact same bank account
and you go to the bank, not at not at nearly
the same time but literally at exactly the
same microsecond in time, and one person is
doing a deposit and the other person is doing
withdrawal.
And when we do that, we have two transactions
that are happening at the same time on different
processors.
So, now we have the possibility of asynchrony
because we're dealing with this with separate
processors and symmetric multiprocessing.
We're going to assume that the bank has a
good enough system that we have more than
one CPU, so we can expect that this these
pieces of code are running on two separate
processors at exactly the same time.
The biggest issue is that they share a balance,
and the balance starts out at one hundred
dollars and the first transaction is the deposit
which is fifty dollars and the second transaction
is the withdrawal of a hundred dollars.
So, we can imagine a situation where two people
go to the bank at same time and one is depositing
fifty dollars, and the other is withdrawing
one hundred dollars.
Ultimately, what we should see is that the
bank balance is fifty dollars because we had
one hundred plus fifty minus one hundred and
I'm not great at math but that's pretty easy
to do and we'll say that that's fifty dollars.
So let's go out and see if that's really the
case.