Let's talk about two fundamental searching
algorithms. The first one is the most general
searching algorithm; it will implement a function
search that is given an array, basically the
starting address when of an array and its
logical size, and in addition it would also
get value, an integer value, val. And this
function should return an index inside this
array where val first appears. Or if val doesn't
appear as one of the elements in A R R this
function would just return a negative one.
So, for example, if array contains five, eight,
twelve, seven, eight, and ten; for example,
if we call the search function with this array
of size six searching for the value eight,
we're expecting to get the index of the first
time where eight appears. That's the second
position so the index would be one; this function
in this case should return one. If we call
the search function on the same array of size
six searching for four, which as you can see
doesn't show in the array, the function should
then return a negative one. So let's implement
the search function.