Very intuitively we should basically iterate
over the elements of the array. And check
each one whether its value is valid or not.
Since we're not sure how many iterations we're
going to have, cause may be not all we won't
need to go over the entire array, we’ll
see val somewhere in the middle, we can just
break out. I think it's better to use a while
loop, in this case. Let's use a while loop
and have indexes I, in this case, iterating
over the array, let's initialize I to zero.
Each iteration will increment I by one, I
plus plus, and we’ll go while I is still
inside the logical portion of the array the
while I is less then there A R R’s size.
And then for each element let's check if there
A R R I is value is val, in this case let's
break the function and return this index,
let's return I. if will go over the entire
array in none of the elements match value,
in this case outside of the a while loop we'll
return negative one. Basically meaning we've
gone over the entire range and none of the
elements are val, so valid doesn't appear
negative one should be the return value. Very
basic implementation so let's try to analyze
the running time. So, the instructions, we
have the expressions we have before and after
the while loop or constants, so they each
take a Taito of one. The while loop cost;
let's try to figure out. So, the body of the
while loop is a constant, an if statement
and the I plus plus are one, two, three statements
each iteration, so let's say Taito of a one.
Then the entire while loop, since we're either
iterating, so let's figure out how many iterations
we have for the while loop. So, it would cost
us as the order of the number of iterations.
So, if T of N, is as we said Taito of number
of iterations, we notice that the worst case
scenario is when the number of iterations
is basically the size of the array, basically
N. So, in this case, T of N for worst case
would be paid over. So, this search as you
can see is a linear search; we're going over
the entire set of elements of the array and
it is in a linear time, so T of N is Taito
of N.