So let's try to think how we can solve this
problem.
First, most basic idea would say do the same
thing as we've done before, basically searching
the array element by element.
So let's see what the first value of the array
is, in this case it is one.
So, we're searching, for example val equals
seventy nine, so it's not one.
Let's go over to the next one three; that's
not seventy nine.
It's go over for the next one, four that's
Once again eight; that's not seventy nine
and so on.
We can continue on iterating over the elements
with an array.
Yeah, basically could work, once again the
running time of this approach would be linear
because we'll worst case have to iterate over
the entire range of elements, basically Taito
of N.
But this approach here doesn't take advantage
of the fact that our array is given to us,
basically, in an increasing order and we can
take advantage of that if we do something
a bit differently.
So, for example if we’re again searching
for seventy nine.
Let's take a look at the entire range and
look only at the element that appears in the
middle of the array.
Let's test that element for its value.
for example, this element could be ninety
six; since we know we're searching for seventy
nine and at the middle there is ninety six,
we don't really have to go over the entire
left side of the array right because after
all on the left side of ninety six would appear
only values that are greater than ninety six.
So, just by looking at ninety six, we can
rule out all the greater part there or the
left part of ninety six and keeping us with
only the smaller values smaller than ninety
six to look for seventy nine.
So, with one check we basically ruled out
half of our range.
And then once again for the half of the numbers
we still have to search for; again we can
look at only the middle point of that range,
testing the value of the element that is there.
For example, twenty eight and then once again
since we're looking for seventy nine the numbers
are in an increasing order, if we know that
in some position there is twenty eight we
can rule out all the elements there are smaller
than twenty eight; we can basically rule out
all of these elements and keeping us with
only the range of elements between these twenty
eight and ninety six.
Once again, we can check what's in the middle
of that range; for example, eighty four and
we can rule out all the elements that are
greater than eighty four.
We can, we’re then left with the inner range
over there looking at the middle point and
luckily seventy nine; so we've just found
our seventy one.
So, basically we are starting with the regional
range, and each time we're ruling out, we're
taking off half of the elements, basically
closing on the element we are searching for.
Let's try to implement this approach on the
computer.