Let's try to analyze the running time of the
sorted search function.
Hopefully, it would give us a better result
than linear running time; we’ve worked quite
a lot in order to get this coded.
It's much more complicated; I hope it's worth
it.
Let's take a closer look.
So, once again if we look at the code we have
a few statements before the while loop but
they are constants.
So, let's consider them as Taito of one.
There is the if statement after the while
loop, also constant, Taito one.
And I think the dominant part here is basically
the while loop, so let's try to analyze the
running time of this iterative process.
Once again if we look closer at the body of
this a while loop, there are a few statements
here but we can count them; they are not depending
on the size of the input, no matter what the
size of the range the number of operations
we're doing there remains the same.
that's why we're staying saying it's constant,
it's also Taito of one.
Which basically implies that the number of
operations, the total number of operations
for the while loop, is once again the number
of iterations is the order of the number of
iterations.
But in this case it's a bit more tricky to
figure out what's the number of iterations
that this algorithm can do.