Let's try to make a table that would help
us estimate how many iterations this algorithm
does.
So let's try to find the relationship between
the iteration number and the size of the searching
range.
We have each time, right.
We are basically cutting half of the range
each time.
So, let's try to find the relationship between
these two sizes.
So first iteration, the size of the searching
range is the original size basically N right.
Second iteration, we cut the searching range
by two, by half.
So, that gives us, leaves us a searching range
of size N by two.
Next iteration the range is again cut by half,
so we'll have a range of N by four and next
iteration the range would be N by eight and
so on.
In a general iteration number for example
K, let's try and figure out or formulate the
size of this searching range.
So if we take a closer look at the first four
numbers will see that N by eight is also can
be written as N by two to the power of three
and N by four can be written as N over two
square and N by two can be written as N over
two the power of one.
They're all N over two to some power, even
the first N can be thought as N over one or
in other words N over two the power of zero,
which is one.
And we can see that each iteration we have
N over two to the power of one less than the
iteration number, right; two to the three
is two to the power of four minus one.
And two to the two is to to the power of three
minus one or in general form we can say that
in a ration number K, the size of the searching
range is N over two to the power of K minus
one, right.
It matches the pattern we've found before.
So the biggest question is: what's the number
of the last iteration, right?
That's basically would tell us the worst case
scenario right.
Obviously we can stop at the first iteration
and find the value we're searching for, but
the worst case is we'll keep on reducing the
sorting range more and more and more till
we have only one element in that certain range
and then low and the high would cross over
one another.
So we should figure out what the iteration
number where our searching range basically
equals one.
This question mark: what's the number of this
iteration where the searching range is one?
If we figure that out that would be basically
our running time; that would be the number
of iterations.
So let's do the math; let's ask ourselves
for what value of K, N over two to the K minus
one equals one right.
If the general form of the size of the searching
range is N over two to the power of K minus
one for which K this size equals the size
of the last searching range, basically one.
So let's do some math tricks here; let’s
multiply by two to the K minus one that says
that N equals two to the power of K minus
one.
Let's apply log base to both sides of the
equation, basically saying that Log two of
N equals log two of two to the power of K
minus one.
I hope you are familiar with the log rules
here; where you can say that log two of two
to the power of K minus one basically equals
to K. minus one times log two of two.
So that means that look two of N. is then
equal to K. minus one times Log two of two.
Again, Log two of two is one so that means
that Log two of N basically equals to K minus
one.
Let's add one to both ends; that means that
K, which is what we're looking for, equals
to one plus Log two of N. In order of growth
means that is K. is theta of Log two of N,
saying that the number of iterations is theta
of log two of N. And that concludes the worst
case running time of the sorted search here.
A lot of people also name it ‘Binary Search;’
the running time of this binary search algorithm
is T of N equals theta of Log two of N. The
next video we’ll talk about how great improvement
log two of N versus a linear algorithm is.