The level order traversal gets even more complex
and I'm going to tie this into the previous
module that we did which was talking about
stacks and queue's.
And here we're using a queue to store the
binary search tree pointers, the node pointers.
So what we're doing is we start off with the
level order traversal by pushing the root
node pointer so we push the root node pointer
on to the tree, onto the queue excuse me,
and then as long as the queue is not empty
what we do is look at the front node look
at the top of the of the queue.
And then pop that off process that node and
then push the left and push the right as long
as there are not know.
What that does is process the root node first
of course but then a process is the left child.
And if the left child of the root has any
children those get pushed onto the queue after
the right child of the root.
So what we're doing is processing the tree
from the top down and outwards.
Which is known as a breadth first search,
we're going to breadth of the tree first before
we go to the next level.
So, you can see that this level order traversal
tends to operate on the higher nodes the nodes
with the less depth first.
And it's just another way of going through
the same tree and it might help us if we're
searching a very, very large tree or for doing
some operation on a very, very large tree;
it might help us get the nodes that we care
about most done first.