I wanted to show you what the traversal results
look like, so I’ll come back to that same
tree that we came that we showed you earlier
with the twenty at the root node.
And what I want you to see is that the pre-order,
in-order, post-order and level order traversals
really produce very, very different outputs.
And so what we're doing is we're saying that
the in-order traversal would actually process
all the left nodes first and then the node,
and then the right node first.
The pre-order traversal tends to process the
root node first and then it processes the
left and processes the right recursively,
and that's the important characteristics here.
So, take a look at the pre-order traversal;
it means we process twenty first of course
because we're doing the pre-processing.
So we process twenty first, and then recursively
process the left sub-child which means a five
comes out next, but that means recursively
we have to do the left sub-child of five before
we can go back and do anything else.
Three comes out and because three doesn't
have any left child or right child, we're
done and we move back to five in which case
we have to process the right sub-child of
five.
We only process the left; it's now time to
process the right.
So, if we if you take a look back at the code
after we're done processing the left child
of five, we're going to have to process the
right child of five, which is ten and then
we're done because it has no left and no right
child.
When we come back the five, we're done with
five, we go back to twenty and we still have
to process the right children.
And so that's the way that the pre-order traversal
is going to operate.
The output would be twenty-five, three, ten,
thirty, and twenty-five because we're doing
it pre-order.
In-order; you can see that this actually is
in order so it's sorted if you will.
We're processing all the left children first;
when we go to process the left child of three
since it has no left child we can simply process
the node at three and then process its right
child.
It has no right child, so we process three
first.
In other words, the minimum value is the value
processed first which makes sense.
Likewise, the maximum value is the value that's
processed last.
So, the output from the in-order traversal
would be three, five, ten, twenty, twenty-five
and thirty.
Just simply because we're going through this
in order and since it is a binary search tree
it's kept in order.
The level-order is the most interesting one
here.
Which is that we do twenty first and then
if you look at the queue, when we push twenty
we're then going to push five and thirty,
which are the nodes on the left and right
child of twenty.
When we're done processing twenty and we start
processing five, we'll push three and ten
but three and ten are actually after thirty
on the queue.
So, if you look internally at the queue, what
we're going to see is three, thirty, three,
ten, and then it's not until we're finished
with ten and we process twenty-five that were
done with the entire tree.
So the level-order traversal would be twenty,
five, thirty, three, ten, and then twenty-five
and that is exactly in the order of the levels
if you look at the picture.