So if we look at removing from a tree element;
insertion is easy, removal does require a
little bit more work.
So removing from a tree is easy if the node
is empty.
If the node is a leaf node, then just remove
it and update the parent to point to the null
pointer.
So there's not much work that has to be done
if the node is a leaf node.
If the node has just one child then that's
not difficult either, because we can promote
that child and the child will match the characteristics
of the parent.
If, for example, it's a left child then the
left child is going to be promoted; it's going
to have a value less than the parent but the
parent relationship to the grandparent will
not change and so that should all still work
out well.
The problem comes when the node has two children,
and we have to choose what's called a candidate
replacement.
So now we're not going to accept the fact
that we can promote; we can't promote a child
to the parent position because what if that
child has children of its own.
We can't just move that child up; what do
we do with its children and what do we do
with the other child of the grandparents.
What we're going to have to do is decide whether
we choose the maximum of the right sub-child
so in other words go right and then go left,
left, left, left, left, left, left, left,
and we'll end up with is the maximum value
of the…
Sorry the minimum value of the right subtree.
Or what we can do if we're talking about going
to the left is we can go to the left, and
then right, right, right, right, right, or
we can go to the right and left, left, left,
left.
Either way that we decide to go, what we're
choosing is either the previous node from
the node that we're going to delete or the
next node from the node that we're going to
delete in order traversal.
So, if we look at this traversal in order,
it would either be the node immediately before
which would be the minimum of the left-most,
sorry the minimum of the right subtree or
sorry the maximum of the left subtree or would
be the minimum of the right subtree.
In other words, we're going to delete a node
and let's choose to promote, the one of the
nodes that are either the on the left or are
on the right.
So, one of the nodes adjacent to the node
that we're going to be deleting in value,
is going to be promoted to the current node.
So, that's the way that we're going to handle
this; we're either going to go to the left
and then go right, right, right, right, right,
to find the find the maximum node.
Or we're going to go to the right and then
go left, left, left, left, left, to find the
minimum node.
So, the point is that we can actually process
this by promoting one of the children and
then deleting that child instead of deleting
the actual node that we're going to trying
to leave.
We're going to see that in just a just a minute.