So here we are in the else condition.
And in the else condition we've already checked
to see if we have no children or if the left
child is equal to null, or if the right child
is equal to null.
So, we've already decided that what we ended
up with is that we have two children of the
Node that we're trying to delete.
And that's not going to be the easiest solution,
again we're going to either have to decide
to find the minimum of the right subtree or
the maximum of the left subtree.
So, we have to make a decision and this is
just a programmer's decision; it's entirely
personal preference.
Now for me it's easiest to find the minimum
value of the right subtree; so, to go right
and then go left, left, left, left.
And ultimately what I'm going to decide to
do is do that, go right and then go left,
left, left, left, left, and take that last
value that I find, when the left's left pointer,
when the the items left pointer is equal to
null that's the minimum value of that right
subtree.
And what I’m gonna do is copy the data value
up and then delete that node.
So this is recursion; this is a recursive
algorithm that simply says once we found the
data value that we want to delete which is
not the data value that somebody told us to
delete.
We are going to find the minimum value of
the right subtree, we’re to go right, left,
left, left, left find value and promote that
value but then we're going to have duplicates.
And so what we do is remove that value that's
down further in the tree.
Now here, I've guaranteed that it's not infinite
recursion.
And the way that I'm guaranteed that is by
making sure that the minimum of the right
subtree is the one that I'm using.
And if I'm using the minimum of the right
subtree it can't have a left child.
It cannot have a left child because if it
did that would be the minimum of the the right
subtree.
So here we've proven that we can use recursion,
but we're only going to go recursion on one
level further.
Because what we're actually going to be doing
is removing the minimum of the right subtree,
which means that by definition it can only
have it at most one child, hopefully it has
zero.
But even if it does have one we solve that
in a previous example and we don't have to
worry about infinite recursion from that sense.
So, in fact what seemed to be a very complex
problem of removal of the node given that
it has two children, actually turns out pretty
easy because we're just going to deal with
deleting some other node and promoting its
data value.