We've got a lot to cover in this module.
We're going to talk about trees and binary
search trees.
And we're going to start by talking about
the definition for trees and some of the definitions
of words that we use in conjunction with trees.
We're going to talk about tree storage methods
and how we can take this model of what a tree
is and put it into main memory.
We're going to talk about the design of binary
search trees and what they are, and how they
can help us.
We're going to talk about why we need binary
search trees and then we're going to talk
about tree traversals.
And what happens when a binary search tree
doesn't meet our requirements that we need
and then we're going to talk about balance
binary search trees including AVL trees, and
a little bit on red-black trees.
So we've got a lot to cover in this module;
stick with me.