AVL trees are named for their creators and
it's two guys named Adelson Belsky and Landis.
What they do is they record a height for each
node of the tree and it's a balanced binary
search tree because the AVL tree puts in a
stipulation that the height of the left and
right subtrees can differ by no more than
one.
So the heights, by definition, can differ
by no more than one and that means that we
never get to the point where we end up with
a linked list where everything is always going
to the right or even worse everything's going
to the left, but the point is that the heights
are restricted.
Now one thing that the AVL tree does, or actually
the point of the AVL tree is that when we
determine that the heights differ by more
than one then it's time for a rotation to
rebalance the subtree.
And we're going to talk about rotations in
just a minute, but the heights of the trees
should cause a rotation to happen.
If they differ by more than one, we're going
to have to do a rotation to reproach to choose
a better route of that subtree so that we
can balance out the tree into.