Let's look at a problem where we have a grandparent,
parent, child kind of situation that's unbalanced.
So, we have a grandparent node which has a
child of a parent node, and the parent node
has a child of the child node.
So, we have that sort of situation and it
doesn't really matter whether we're doing
insertions on the left or insertions on the
right, but the grandparent parent child situation
is set up here so that we have an unbalanced
situation.
If the left parent’s left sub child is greater
than the left parent’s right sub child,
or if we have the heights what we're talking
about is the height, or we have the right
parent’s right sub child is greater than
the right parents’ left sub child.
Or what I like to call it is either an outside-outside
insertion versus an outside-inside insertion;
outside-inside is a different problem, outside-outside.
So if we go right right, that's one condition;
if we go left left, that's one condition and
that's solved by a single rotation.
And what we're talking about with the single
rotation is taking the parents and making
it the new grandparent position.
So, in the case that I have described here,
we've got a node twenty and it's left child
is ten and the left child of ten is three
and what we've got is we're going to promote
ten.
Now when we promote ten, it's like picking
up the node ten and the rest of the node sort
of drop like Christmas balls.
So,if we pick up ten, the twenty node converts
(turns into) the right node of ten; the twenty
node becomes the right note of ten.
So the reason that that works, picking it
up and then having ten’s right node become
twenty is because in this condition, ten doesn't
have a right child.
What would happen if ten did have a right
child?
Well if ten didn't have a right child, then
the left child of twenty would become empty;
it would become null pointer.
Because we're picking up then the left child
of twenty is no longer important, because
that was the pointer that pointed to ten,
but we don't need that anymore.
So, the perfect solution is to make the left
child of twenty, actually point to the right
child of ten.
And if we do that remembering the fact that
all the nodes to that are greater than ten
would be on the right of ten.
Then it's important to recognize that this
still holds the binary search tree property,
because when we pick up ten and its right
pointer now points to twenty; that's a value
greater than.
And remembering that all the values that were
greater than ten were on the right side of
ten.
So, if we make the left pointer of twenty
point to the values that are greater than
ten (were greater than ten before) then we
still have that binary search tree property
maintained and everything still works out
the way that we wanted to.
So, this is what's known as a single rotation,
in this case actually it's called a single
clockwise rotation because we're kind of going
clockwise. and what we can do is recognize
that this works.
Now it only works in the case of an outside-outside,
so if the heavier node that the node with
the higher height, the bigger height, the
greater height is right right or left the
left this work.
But if we have a problem, we do have a problem,
if we're going left rights or if we're going
right left and that's the higher node.
So, we're going to see that as another solution
in the next slide.