We covered a lot of stuff in this module.
We talked about the definitions for trees,
we’ve talk about the heights and sizes and
the depths and that sort of stuff.
We talked about how we can store trees in
main memory; remember, we talked about the
parent-child relationship, parent-multi-child
relationship and then we talk about the parent-child-sibling
relationship.
We talked about the design of binary search
trees and what we need them for.
We actually went through the binary search
tree code.
We talked about tree traversals: in-order,
pre-order, post-order and level-order.
We talked about when binary search trees fail
and fall back on a linked list, and even if
that doesn't happen as an actual linked list,
even a portion of that could cause us to lose
our big O of Log N. And then we talked about
balanced binary search trees: the ATL and
the red-black trees.
So we certainly covered a lot in this module
and I want you to take away the idea that
trees are very popular.
We come across them quite often in computer
science.
In fact, if you just look at the files on
your on your hard drive, what you're looking
at is a tree.
You're looking at a regular tree; it's not
a binary search tree but it is a regular tree
because you do have folders inside of folders
in this higher structure.
But they're not difficult and they’re not
complex.
And they are incredibly useful, certainly
in the binary search tree for being able to
store a large quantity of data and being able
to search it in big O of Log N time.
So, I hope you took away a lot of good information
from this module.