The most common form of tree that we're going
to work with is actually a binary search tree.
And I'd like to go over that and talk about
it, because we are going to use it extensively
especially in this module.
The binary search tree as I mentioned before,
only has…
It's a binary tree first off, so that means
it only has a left than a right pointer.
And it actually has an additional property,
and the additional property helps us serve
the order of the nodes, helps us decide the
order of the nodes.
So, in other words which one goes on the left
and which one goes on the right.
And the order property in the binary search
tree says that: all the values in the left
sub tree are going to be values that are less
than the value of this node, and all the values
in the right subtree are going to be values
that are greater than the value of this node.
And that means whatever the data is in the
data section, and I usually use just integers
just to describe it and you can see that here
in this in this graphic, the value of the
nodes are what the value is in the data section.
And if we have this templated then of course
that means we need to overload the less than
operator for whatever the classes that were
storing, but that's outside the scope of this
discussion you can look at the previous modules
and operator overloading to talk about the
less than operator.
But if we have that then we can keep these
in a regular order.
So here now in this graphic what I have is
module, sorry, value twenty is that the tops
of the root is value twenty that was the first
to know that was inserted into the tree.
So, we inserted twenty and then we inserted
five, now five is the value less than twenty.
So, of course five is going to be on the left
hand side of twenty five would be the left
child of twenty.
We then either inserted three maybe, or ten,
or thirty, I'm not sure which the order of
insertions wasn't doesn't really matter but
if we insert three then three should be on
the left of twenty.
Unfortunately, five is already on the left
to twenty so what we can do is progress down
the tree to insert three as the left child
of five.
So what we're doing is we're looking for a
place where, when we do insertion where that
value should belong but there's actually a
null.
And then when we find that we can go ahead
and insert a new node at that location.
So when we go to insert ten, ten belongs on
the left there are twenty but it belongs on
the right of five because it is a value greater
than five.
If you take a look at that subtree, that three
five ten sub tree, that is the left of twenty
all the values in that sub tree are less than
twenty.
And all values in the left subtree of five
are less than five and all the values in the
right subtree of five are greater than five.
So we can evaluate where an insertion should
happen based on the comparison of the current
value that we're trying to insert, with the
value that's already inside the node. and
if you take a look at the values on the right
of twenty There's a value of thirty on the
right of twenty but if it's left child is
twenty-five.
Twenty-five is a value between twenty and
thirty, we can describe it that way.
If we were going to insert one into this tree,
the only place acceptable in this entire tree
that we could insert one would be on the left
of three.
The only place settable to insert thirty-five,
for example or a value any value greater than
thirty, would be on the right sub child of
thirty.
So the binary search tree holds the properties
that all the left's children are less than
and all the right children are greater than
and that happens recursively over and over
again.
So we have to maintain that property, not
just for the tree as a whole but for each
node individually.
Now if we also allow equal values then it's
very common to say that the right sub child
will hold all the equal values but in trees
it's very common to prohibit equal values
inside of the tree.
So you may you may recognize that we don't
allow equal values.
In other words, insertion of twenty five onto
this tree simply wouldn't have any effect
on the tree at all.