wanted to give you an example of that here
with that get size function inside the BST
node class.
So here what we're saying is, we’ll start
out since we are in a node already we can
assume that there is one value the size at
least one, so we’ll start that counter at
one.
And then all going to do is just check to
see if this node has a left: if it does then
add the size of the left, if it has a right
then add the size of the right and then return
count.
And if you take a look at that count, plus
equals left arrow get size, that's a recursive
function call to a different node.
So, what we're doing is checking to see if
that node exists first, because we don't want
to de-ref null of course, if that no does
exist then we'll call its get size function
and we'll add its size to our size.
So if we have any children, we can assume
that our size is the sum of the child sizes
plus one.
And that's really all there is to recursion
in trees, trying to do this with iteration
is really, really hard because you have to
keep track of what level inside the tree you're
on what depth you're at and then move backwards
and forwards.
Remember if, for example, there's no…
There's no association; there's no pointers
between a child node and its cousin node.
So, if we have to go back up to an uncle node
which would be the parents sibling node, that
takes quite an effort and even worse if this
these cousins are separated significantly
by more and more uncles and aunts in the family
tree that looks really crazy.
But with recursion it's rather simple because
we can just call the recursive function to
take a pointer to the child nodes, or in this
case we embed it inside the node class and
we can use the getSize function for the child
nodes inside the parents get size function.
So, recursion is going to happen quite often
in trees.