We covered a lot of material in this module.
We’ve looked at what is a linked list.
We’ve looked at why do we need linked lists.
We also talked about templates, and templates
are something that are going to keep coming
up time and time again throughout the rest
of the semester.
And in the data structures that we're going
to talk about because we never know what they
the type are storing inside of a data structure.
We talked about the design of a linked list
and you should definitely take a look at the
code that we've posted in the CPP file for
this module associated with this, so take
a look at that because that is very useful
resource.
And then we talked about what linked lists
are used for and get some real world example.
So going forward you should understand linked
lists and you should be able to make a judgment
call of whether you want to use an array or
vector or a linked list because that's going
to make a very big difference in terms of
your performance of your program.
And it's an important distinction that you
should understand.