The linked list data structure is one of the
fundamental data structures in computer science.
It’s basic idea is that it has two parts
each: it's made up of nodes and each node
has two parts.
The first part is a data section which could
be any data type, but that's the component,
that's the element that we're going to store.
If we were talking about an array this would
be the individual item in an array but it's
not so keep that in mind.
So we've got this node that has a data section
and it also has at least one pointer, if not
multiple pointers to the next sections or
to the rest of the list.
And the idea is that the pointers are connected
in a form of a chain, so that we have a pointer
to the first node in the list and we call
that the head pointer.
We record the head pointer to the first node
of the list and then the first node of the
list’s next pointer will point to the second
node of the list, and the second node of the
list’s next pointer will point to the third
node of the list, and so on and so forth and
so on and so forth.
When we get to the end, we have what's called
a null pointer; so we have the null which
is an indication.
So when the next pointers pointing at null
that's an indication, that this is the last
node on the list.
So these nodes are tied together through one
direction at least, where each node points
to the next node.
Now since this is only the most basic form
of the linked list, in reality what's usually
stored is both the next pointer and a previous
pointer; so you may end up having two pointers
in the in the linked list structure and of
course the previous pointer just points at
the node before this node, and of course the
before the first node would be a null pointer.
So it's sort of like a linked list in reverse:
we've got the head pointer that points of
the first node, the first node points at the
second node, the second node points at the
third node and so on and so forth.
So this is the idea of how we can store a
large amount of data in a linked list and
we're keeping them in individual nodes; remember
these are node pointers and they're pointing
at individual nodes.