So, we can take a look at the way this code
is going to run; we can see the program counter
here.
I've broken it down into multiple steps, so
that you can see.
What we start off with is the deposit function
which is going to put in fifty dollars into
the account.
The balance, the new balance, becomes a hundred
fifty dollars so this new balance variable
is local to the deposit function and it makes
a copy of the balance which was one hundred
dollars and it adds the fifty dollars, so
we have one hundred fifty dollars.
Unfortunately, we get an interrupt or we’re
running on a separate CPU, so we go to the
other CPU and we check out what's happening
there.
Now we look at the withdrawal function now
and it's running on the other CPU or it's
now running on the one CPU, and we say that
the new balance is now the balance minus the
amount, which would now be zero, so the new
balance is now zero.
And then we go back and check the previous
thread which then goes back and copies the
stored New Balance information.
We go back and finish out the deposit function
put the balance in as a hundred fifty dollars,
which makes sense because if we had a hundred
dollars and we deposited fifty dollars then
we go ahead and put that a hundred fifty value
back into the common shared variable, which
is balance, and then the deposit thread is
finished; the deposit thread exits.
But we have to go back and finish out the
withdraw thread, and when we do that we get
into a lot of trouble because we're going
to copy New Balance back up into balance and
New Balance is now zero.
So, our fifty dollars disappeared, because
it was hidden; what happened is we had asynchrony.
We had the deposit function running at the
same time as the withdrawal function, and
the deposit function performed its action,
asynchronously, with the withdraw function,
and the withdraw function never got the update
according to The New Balance.
So, in other words when deposit changed new
balance, withdraw knew nothing about the new
balance and it used the previous balance.
So, that over wrote the original balance.
So, ultimately what this means is that our
bank gets a free fifty dollars, and we're
going to have to go to the bank and fight
for our fifty dollars and that's kind of annoying.
Thankfully we're going to take care of this
with critical sections, so that we know that
we're not going to change the balance, so
we're not going to lose our money.