So, we saw in the supplier/demander thread,
an example of checking and changing the buffer
and the buffer count and how that has to be
done atomically; we have to look at that as
one atomic instruction.
We have to not be able to stop running that
or run anything else until we finished running
them, that set of instructions.
So, we have to consider the complete supplier
threat or at least the subset of the supplier
thread in that portion where does the checking
the if statement and the changing of the buffer
count and the buffer; we have to do that in
one atomic instruction, although we can't
do it in one atomic instruction.
So, the only way that we can consider this
is that the that portion of the function needs
to be protected by a critical section and
we'll see how to do that.
In the double update/missing update problem,
really those entire functions which are very
simple functions well they are as two lines
of code, both of those functions need to run
atomically so they cannot be interrupted from
the time we start the function to the time
we finish the function.
The need for running those sections of code
atomically, actually indicates that those
sections of code are critical sections, and
that's what we're trying to identify.
We're trying to make sure that we know where
the critical sections are and that we protect
them by protection mechanisms, which we'll
talk about in just a few minutes, from any
untoward asynchrony that might happen inside
the system.