The hardware provides us with the mutual exclusion
protection mechanism, built into it; we have
the system bus, and we know that the system
bus can only be used by one processor at any
given time.
So, even in this scenario where we have symmetric
multiprocessing, with multi processors in
the system, we recognize that it's impossible
for two processors to change the same memory
location at the same time.
It is absolutely impossible because one of
those processors will gain access to the system
boss will be allowed to change that memory
location and then the other will have to wait.
So, we have a protection mechanism built directly
into hardware just by the nature of the way
we do things, so that we can't change a memory
location to two different values at the same
time.
So, what we'd like to do is develop something
that we can use at a much higher level, to
protect our code in C++ or in a high level
language, from any problems that might happen
because of mutual exclusion cases.
So, having that fundamental hardware mechanism
is very useful, is helpful, but ultimately
we need something a lot easier to deal with
on a high level and we'll see that.