We have better solutions today; we definitely
do, we’ll deal with some hardware solutions
in just a minute.
But originally we didn't have hardware that
could help us deal with this mutual exclusion
problem and so computer scientists started
working to try and solve the mutual exclusion
problem using just software, so not having
anything in the hardware to directly deal
with this except for that system bus limitation.
Peterson came up with a fundamental way to
protect two threads from accessing the same
resource at the same time and what he did
was he provided each thread with the Boolean
flag variable.
So, there's an array of Boolean flag variables
for each of the threads and each thread would
put up its flag; would set it its Boolean
value equal to true, if it wanted to access
its critical section.
Now, unfortunately that's not enough because
we're going to have to go and check everybody
else's, or the other thread let's say if there's
only two threads, we're going to go and check
the other threads flag to make sure it's not
in its critical section.
And we run the risk if we set our flag and
then go check the other thread, that the other
thread is doing exactly the same thing at
the same time, and now we have both threads
have their flags up and both threads think
that the other thread is in it's critical
section and in fact, nobody is in a critical
section.
So, what Peterson did to solve that problem
specifically was introduce another variable
he called the turn variable.
And in here it's being generous is very helpful
he thought, so what the threads do is they
offer the turn to the other thread so thread
zero would offer the turn to thread one and
thread one would offer the turn to thread
zero.
So, in that very rare situation where both
threads want to access the critical section,
both would raise up their flags and one would
offer the turn to the other and the second
one would win; the second turn right, if you
will, would overwrite the first change of
the turn variable.
So, either thread zero or thread one would
be allowed access into its critical section,
and then of course eventually it would unset
its flag and allow the other thread to access
its critical section because it no longer
has its flag up.
So, the nice feature here is that it does
provide protection for mutual exclusion, if
we have two threads that need access to mutual
exclusion.
If we have more than that we have a bit of
a problem, but Peterson's algorithm allows
us to deal with the situation where we have
two threads and we can provide mutual exclusion
for those two threads using only software
solutions.