Now that we have the software solutions figured
out, we'd much rather take a look at hardware
solution.
So, this is what we're really going to do
today, after a very short while the CPU designers
realize that the computer scientists were
having this problem and they said: hey guys
we can deal with this much easier and give
you some hardware solutions to take care of
your concurrency controllers, take care of
dealing with your locks.
And so what they did was they created some
hardware built into the CPU to take care of
this; most of these are instructions that
are built directly into the CPU.
Now the first one is the disabling of interrupts.
I don't think this is a great idea because
interrupts are really necessity; we want to
have interrupts in the system.
If an interrupt does occurs it means a piece
of hardware needs immediate servicing and
we want to go ahead and do that.
But if we take away the possibility that an
interrupt might occur then we effectively
take away the possibility of asynchrony; we
guarantee that this thread will not be interrupted
until it decides to re-enable interrupts.
Now this would probably be limited to the
operating systems control, so this would require
some intervention by the operating system
to use this because imagine a situation where
a thread disables interrupts and then crashes;
the whole system is stuck you can't get out
except with a big power switch.
So, disabling interrupts is something that
we use very sparingly if it is in existence
and even then we try to avoid it.
The other options that we have our instructions
that are built into the instruction set on
the processor.
So, the first one is called a test and set,
and in the test and set function, test and
set instruction, what we do is check a memory
location and if its value is of a particular
value.
So, for example zero if we find that there
is a zero stored in that memory location we
will change it to a one.
So, this is perfect for a Boolean flag variable,
for example, which says that maybe somebody
is in the critical section.
By having this test and set instruction, we
can have that single variable that single
Boolean variable that says there's somebody
in the critical section and we can set it
equal to one at the same time it’s testing
it.
Now this is an atomic machine level instruction.
So, the CPU takes control of the system bus,
goes and checks the location in memory, and
then if it is the zero, goes resets that value
to one in one atomic instruction; nobody else
will be allowed to access that memory location.
So, even if we have another processor that
processor will not be allowed access to the
memory location during a test and set because
it has to happen atomically.
So, a result is returned back to the back
to the operating system or back to the calling
program that asked for the test and set, and
that indicates whether it was successful.
Meaning, we both tested this to make sure
nobody's in their critical section and at
the same time we set it to go so indicate
that you are in the critical section and that
means that the process is allowed to go into
its critical section.
Or we have a failure in which case the thread
or the process has to pause and delay and
try it again.
So, the test and set actually works fairly
well.
The other option is very similar it's called
exchange, and this is a very common one that
we use today, in which we have a swapping
of a location in main memory with that of
a register.
So, we can again use, this is a Boolean flag
variable, except now we can put a one in a
particular register, call exchange for the
memory location and we literally get a swap
of the value in the register with the value
in the memory location.
So, if the memory location had a zero, it
will now be set to one and we can go back
afterwards and check to make sure that it
was a zero, if it was a one then we'll know
that it was a one because we'll get it back.
But the nice feature is that when we do the
exchange, even if we're interrupted immediately
after the exchange instruction, the indication
that we're in the critical section has already
been set and now we just have to check to
make sure whether it was successful or not.
So, the exchange instruction is a very common
one that's in use today and it's relatively
easy to understand.