The common solution that a programmer would
use today as a high-level solution would be
the semaphores.
Now semaphores of course are going to have
some issues internally to them, so they're
going to use some of the hardware level instructions
that we just talked about.
But the semaphore will provide for mutual
exclusion.
Now the word semaphore actually comes from
a nautical term; I think it's needs a flag
that used to be flown on top of the ship and
it's very much similar.
So, what we have here is two functions that
we generally use inside the semaphore, we
construct the semaphore and then we send it
a signal.
The idea of a semaphore is that it's a message
passing structure, so one thread could send
a signal and the other thread could receive
that signal.
Now the way we receive the signal is by calling
wait.
But here's where this is very useful for mutual
exclusion, the wait function is blocking.
So, if there is no signal that has been sent,
then the wait function causes a block to wait
for the signal to be sent, and that's where
we can really use it for mutual exclusion.