So, initially when we create the semaphore
we send a signal in the semaphore, so that's
an initial cueing of the signal.
Now assuming that we just created it I'm going
to assume that nobody's waiting on the semaphore,
so the signal is just going to sit there and
wait to be received.
When we enter a critical section the first
thing that we do is call wait.
Now as long as there's a signal already there,
then wait is non-blocking and the thread is
just going to be allowed to enter its critical
section.
But the key feature is that the wait will
consume the signal that's queued, so now there's
no signal that's queued.
If another thread calls wait to enter its
critical section then it will not have a signal
and it will be blocked and the operating system
will keep a queue of the blocked processes
so that it can start those processes again
as the signals come in.
When we're done, when the thread is finished
with its critical section, it’s going to
call signal and signal is going to either
queue up the signal if there's no threads
waiting or if there is a thread waiting then
the signal is going to release the next thread
from the queue.
So, this allows us to create a mutual exclusion
protection mechanism using just a simple signal
passing routine