Now that we've talked about semaphores enough,
we have to talk about one downside to having
all these locks and that’s the idea of a
deadlock.
And the deadlock occurs in a system, or can
occur in a system, if all the threads are
waiting for each other; if we have a set of
threads that are all waiting for each other,
then there's really no way that any one of
them are going to complete.
Usually it results from one thread waiting
for another thread to release a resource,
and it's not really clear what that resource
could be; it could be a lock, in terms of
a mutual exclusion lock like semaphore, or
we could be talking about a file, or we could
be talking about a mouth of memory.
But there's some resource which is shared
among the threads and one thread is waiting
for another thread to release the resource,
while that other thread is waiting about eventually
back for the first thread to release the resource.
So, we have one A waiting for B, B waiting
for A neither is going to get done; it's a
permanent block, it is not going to resolve
itself over time.
This requires the intervention of an operating
system if the deadlock does occur, there’s
going to have to be some resolution that the
operating system or that's a monitor program
takes on top of the the deadlock threads to
resolve the issue.
And unfortunately today there's really no
efficient solution, even today we don't have
a very efficient solution to deadlocks.
It either amounts to a considerable waste
of system resources, processor time or memory,
or it amounts to a deadlock occurring and
then resolving the deadlock.
So, we really don't have a good solution today
to deadlocks, other than to say we have to
keep them in mind and make sure that they
don't happen.