I've been talking about using locks, or using
a semaphore, but in reality we have two different
resource types that we can talk about when
we get into deadlocks.
One is reusable resource types, and the other
is consumable resource types.
Now a reusable resource type happens when
we have a resource that we will temporarily
consume, for example, we will temporarily
take action on the resource, we will temporarily
take over control of that, resource.
But then once we're done with it we'll return
the resource back to the operating system
or back to the the whole so it can be reused
again.
So, examples of this include things like memory,
devices, data structures, even semaphores;
once we're done with these things we return
them back to their original state and they're
allowed to be used again.
But there's consumable resources, which once
we use it it's gone.
For example, if we have an interrupt and we
deal with the interrupts, or we if you will
consume the interrupt, the interrupts can't
be replaced.
If we get a signal then the signal can't be
replaced; if we got a message then the message
cannot be replaced.
If we're for example, processing data in an
IO buffer as you did in previous examples
where you read in from the keyboard, once
you read in that data there's an easy way
to put it back into the buffer.
So, consumable resource types, once they're
used they're gone, and the reason that we're
recognizing this is because how we deal with
a deadlock on these different resources is
going to be different from one resource type
to another.