There are four things that have to come into
play for a deadlock to actually occur.
And some of them are requirements that the
operating system needs to have, and some of
them are just bad luck that have to happen,
but we need all four of these to happen in
order for us to have a deadlock.
The first one is mutual exclusion and we already
know what mutual exclusion is, we've been
talking about it, we understand that there's
going to be a resource and this resource can
be held by only one thread at a time; so we
have a lock on that resource if you will.
If we have that then, we have the first item
that's required for a deadlock.
The second one is called a hold-and-wait and
that means that while a thread is waiting
on the allocation of a new resource it retains
all of its existing locks on the old resources.
So, if a thread obtains a lock on A and then
requests a lock on B, and the lock on B is
not available immediately, the thread is going
to be blocked.
So, it means that the thread could possibly
have a lock on something and be in a block
state at the same time.
So this happens, we understand that this happens,
certainly when we're creating more than one
lock at any given time.
The third thing that we need in order for
deadlock to happen is that there is no preemption.
The operating system cannot forcibly remove
a resource from a thread.
So, for example on a semaphore, once we've
decremented the semaphore counter and it's
now zero, the operating system has no way
of intervening and saying, ‘oh whoops I'm
sorry you no longer have that lock on that
semaphore and you have to go back to doing
something entirely different.’
We usually don't have that as a possibility;
it's the idea of no preemption.
The last one: and the last one is just case
of bad luck it's called a circular wait.
And that's a closed chain of threads in which
the last thread is waiting on the first thread.
This could be as simple as A waiting for B,
and B waiting for A, but it's often not as
simple as that.
We can have four different threads: where
we have A, B, C, and D. And we have A waiting
for B, B waiting for C, C you waiting for
D, but D waiting back for A, so it's not easy
to recognize that a circular wait has occurred;
it’s not just take a snapshot and see which
process, which threads are waiting for which
threads it doesn't work that that easily.
There's lots of levels of iteration and recursion
that might have to happen in order for us
to detect that the circular wait is actually
happening.
If we have all four of these things in play:
we have mutual exclusion because the operating
system provides us with locks, we have hold
and wait because we can have more than one
lock and we request one lock separate from
the other locks, and we have no preemption
meaning the operating system can't take things
away from us, and we have a circular wait
which just happened to occur, we have a deadlock.