So there's three ways of dealing with deadlocks:
and the first way is called deadlock prevention,
the second is deadlock avoidance, and the
third is deadlock detection.
Deadlock prevention requires us to take away
one of those four requirements; either we're
going to take away no preemption, or we're
going to take away holding weight, or we're
going to avoid the possibility of a circular
weight.
The idea of taking away preemption, kind of
difficult, we’ll talk about that in just
a minute.
We might have dead lock avoidance; deadlock
avoidance creates an algorithm in which we
are going to check the system to see if a
deadlock could occur whenever we make an allocation
for a resource.
So, now the operating system now is going
to intervene, and say, if you're going to
make a request if you're going to lock something,
the operating system will check the state
of the system to see if a deadlock will occur
as a result of you're making a lock on that.
And if a deadlock will occur as the result
of you're making a lock on that device, the
lock is not approved and the thread is either
told to go do something else or it's blocked
all together until the lock can be approved.
So, deadlock avoidance says we recognize that
all four requirements for a deadlock are in
play, however, we're going to avoid the deadlock
by preventing such a situation just from occurring.
Deadlock detection is the last way and it's
the easiest way, it just says deadlocks are
going to happen we'll let them happen and
periodically we'll just check to make sure
that if there are any dead locks that we just
deal with them in some method.
So, deadlock detection is the easiest, so
to speak but it's also the most difficult
to deal with after the fact.
So, now we have to deal with the fact that
a deadlock has occurred, and we have to recover
from it.
Those are our solutions that we have for dead
locks and we're going to look at them individually.