The idea of deadlock prevention is that we
eliminate one of the four requirements for
a deadlock.
The first one is mutual exclusion, and it's
really hard to get rid of mutual exclusion
because it's usually a requirement.
Whenever we're working with threads, we recognize
that these threads are going to have the possibility
for asynchrony and if they have the possibility
for asynchrony, we have to provide a possibility
for mutual exclusion.
We have to provide the protection mechanisms
for mutual exclusion; so getting rid of mutual
exclusion is usually not a possibility.
Hold-and-wait: we can say that all locks are
required to be obtained at the same time and
either they're all approved or the thread
is blocked.
Now if we do that then there's no additional
lock that might occur.
If a thread holds a lock, it cant obtain another
lock, which means that we can't get into a
situation where we're holding a lock and we're
asking for a new lock and therefore, we're
blocked because we're asking for the new lock.
So, if we make the threads ask for all of
its locks at the same time, then we've eliminated
the possibility of hold-and-wait.
No preemption: we can say that if a thread
requests a new lock and the new lock is denied
then the thread has to release all of its
existing locks.
So, that's a possibility, it's got to require
a callback from the operating system to the
thread to say if the request for the lock
is denied unlock everything else.
Put it back in a safe state; undo what you
were doing and release those locks.
The operating system might also have the possibility
the authority to remove existing locks individually
but that's a bit of a bad idea.
The last one is actually an easy one to deal
with especially if we're talking about locks
on individual items that the programmer can
control; one of the easiest solutions for
dealing with the circular wait is to order
all the resources.
We can number them and order them so that
there's never a possibility of holding a higher
level resource and requesting a lower level
resource.
So, one of the problems of the circular weight
is that the last thread is waiting on the
first thread.
What that means is that the first thread holds
a lower lock and the last thread holds a higher
level lock and if we prevent the last thread
from accessing its lower level lock, because
it holds the higher lock number then we've
prevented the situation of the circular wait.
Either that higher level, that last thread
will either release the higher level lock
and then request the lower level lock allowing
other threads to continue or it won't be allowed
to do it.
So, the circular wait is actually an easy
one and it's the one that's recommended by
a lot of computer scientists because the programmer
can protect his own program internally, just
simply by ordering the locks, ordering resources.
So, that we never ask for a lower lock while
we're holding a higher lock