In the deadlock avoidance scenario, the operating
system has to know everything that the thread
is going to do before it actually does it.
So, the operating system has to know what
locks the thread is going to want, in order
to look into the future, in order to have
a premonition about what could happen in this
deadlock scenario.
So, what the operating system does is it takes
all the information for all the threads that
are running, and says that whenever a thread
makes a new request, the operating system
is going to run what's called a banker's algorithm,
or what's often called a banker's algorithm.
And the idea is that we know all the resources
that the operating system has, we know all
the resources that the threads have, and we
have some premonition about what the resources
the thread is going to want in its entire
lifetime.
So, we can tell which threads are going to
run to completion just by knowing what we
currently have available and what the threads
are going to want before they're finished.
And what we can do is constantly check, whenever
a resource is requested, the operating system
is going to run the bankers algorithm to try
and figure out if the allocation of that request
would cause the system to be in what we call
an unsafe state.
And an unsafe state is one in which all the
threads cannot complete, rather that we can
say that any thread cannot complete, so we're
protecting the system from ever getting into
that unsafe state.
So, we sort of simulate by making the allocation
in a simulation, and saying can we now finish
all of the threads and if we can, we can say
that that allocation keeps us in a safe state
and we make the allocation and if we can't
then we deny the allocation.
So, the system is by definition always in
a safe state, but we're checking every single
time to make sure that the allocations will
not put the system in an unsafe state.
It’s a lot of work and we usually don't
have information about what the threads are
going to ask for ahead of time, until they
actually ask for it.
So, that makes dead lock avoidance a very
rare strategy.