In deadlock detection, it's really easy going.
All it does is say we have all the requirements,
there’s a possibility for a deadlock, so
we'll check periodically to see that the deadlock
is not occurring.
It's not at all restrictive; we're not saying
that we were going to stop any situation from
occurring.
We're saying in fact the exact opposite: that
deadlocks will occur and when they do occur
we're going to have to deal with them, and
we'll talk about that in just a minute.
But we recognize that the deadlocks will occur
and that periodically we're going to have
to check the system to see if there are any
dead locks that are in existence.
Once we detect the deadlock, well we have
to figure out what that's going to do and
the only ways that we can really deal with
a deadlock are either rolling back the deadlock
process, or the deadlock thread, to a previous
unlock state that's useful for things like
SQL servers and database servers, but it requires
transaction logs.
So, we have to know what this thread, or what
this process that's deadlock did in the past
X time interval, so that we can roll it back
to that X time interval and either restart
it or let it continue from a previous state,
when which it wasn't deadlocked.
We could also just say let's abort all the
deadlock threads; we'll kill them all.
We could abort a single thread and see if
the deadlock is being resolved, so we can
arbitrarily just pick one of the deadlock
threads and say it's now killed, its resources
are released, and now see if the system is
back to a stable state, let it run again and
see if there's a deadlock or not.
Or we can start pre-empting resources.
Unfortunately, in all of these situations
we have the potential, except for rolling
back, in all of these other situations we
have the potential for catastrophic loss of
data or corruption of data.
Basically we're saying that we don't think
that the system is in a consistent state,
but we really have no other resolution other
than to just say we have to take some emergency
action and that means we recognize that if
the data is corrupt we have to deal with that.
So, deadlock detection says, just let it happen
and then we'll deal with it afterwards, we
hope it doesn't happen.
And believe it or not this is the one that's
most common today, that we just say let it
happen and if it does happen we'll deal with
it.
You might have had this in your past you have
an application that just completely freezes
up on a Mac, you get the beach ball on a Windows
machine you just get the screen graying out;
it's doing something we have no idea what
it's doing, so what happens we kill it.
We are the deadlock detection algorithm; we
have recognized that a deadlock has occurred
and we abort all the deadlock threads by killing
the entire process.
So, congratulations everybody has been promoted
to a deadlock detection algorithm.