I'd like to take a look at one classic computer
science problem.
It was first presented by Dr. Edsger Dijkstra
who was a famous computer scientist that you're
going to hear a lot about Dr. Dijkstra with
his various assorted algorithms throughout
your careers in computer science.
But it's a computer, sorry, it’s a concurrency
control problem and what he said was… and
I really have no idea how he came up with
this idea, this scenario but somehow he created
it.
He said that there's a house where we have
five philosophers and the Philosopher's are
numbered 0 through 4.
And they alternate, they only do two things,
philosophers only do two things: they eat
and they think.
And when it's time to eat, somebody, we were
not figuring out who, sets up a circular table
and it has a place setting for each philosopher.
And the place setting consists of one fork
on the left side, and one plate in front of
the philosopher.
The meal unfortunately that they're going
to eat is a particularly difficult to eat
kind of spaghetti.
I’m quoting dr.
Dijkstra here, this is not me, this is Dijkstra's
dining philosophers problem.
I don't know why spaghetti, or why you eat
spaghetti with two forks, but he said that
you need to have two forks to eat this kind
of spaghetti.
And unfortunately, each philosopher is only
given one fork.
But we recognize that there's a fork on the
left of the philosopher and a fork on the
right of the philosopher.
The way that we can think about this is that
when the philosopher comes he can pick up
the fork on the left, and he can try and pick
up the fork on the right, the unfortunate
problem is that if all five philosophers come
to the table at exactly the same time, all
of them will pick up their left forks and
there will be no right forks.
In other words, all of them are holding a
lock where there's mutual exclusion because
the philosopher doesn't let go of his fork,
all of them are holding the lock on the left
fork and waiting for the lock on the right
fork.
All of them have no preemption so nobody's
going to reach across the table and start
grabbing a fork these are nice philosophers,
I guess they're not from Brooklyn, I'm kidding.
And we have a circular wait we have the last
philosopher in a sequence waiting for the
first philosopher on the sequence.
So, ultimately what we have is all four requirements,
we’ve met the deadlock requirements, and
in fact you can see that we have a deadlock.
In this scenario all the philosophers will
starve to death, because none of them will
put down the fork and allow somebody else
to eat.