So like we see, if all the philosophers are
allowed to take a fork, all will have one
fork and none will ever eat.
So, what's the solution to this?
Well Dijkstra proposed the solution of resource
ordering, of course.
That's the easiest one.
And he said, let's order the forks zero through
four.
Now, if you pick up fork zero, you're not
allowed to pick up fork four, and that leaves
fork four for the philosopher on his right
to pick up, and that means that the fourth
philosopher will be allowed to eat because
he has his own fork plus the last fork.
We can't select a larger, we can't have a
larger fork and a smaller number fork at the
same time unless you ask for the smaller fork
first then the larger fork second.
So ultimately what this means is that one
of the philosophers will get both forks, will
eat, and put both forks down, allowing more
philosophers to eat and more philosophers
to eat and ultimately, everybody eats.
So that's the resource ordering solution.
But there's another solution in which we have
a semaphore.
And obviously, we're going to have semaphores
for each of the forks, you can see that already
cause we need mutual exclusion on each of
the individual forks.
What we're talking about is adding yet another
semaphore, and saying that there's a semaphore
that has to be met that has to hold mutual
exclusion for the entire room.
So with the semaphore solution, we have four
signals that go into the queue under semaphore;
the first four philosophers are allowed to
enter the room, and they're allowed to eat.
The last philosopher, of course the fourth
philosopher, will pick up the fork from the
fifth philosopher because he's not allowed
in the room at all.
And that allows the fourth philosopher to
eat, and then he'll put his fork down, allowing
the third philosopher to eat, and then he'll
put his fork down, and so on and so forth.
Eventually, after the fourth philosopher leaves
the room, the fifth philosopher will be allowed
in and he'll eventually be allowed both forks;
everybody is allowed to eat and the problem
is resolved.
So, we've got two scenarios here and there's
actually even more scenarios that get even
more complex; there are more solutions that
get more complex.
There are solutions using a monitor, and there's
even more complex ones.
But the fundamental, the easiest to understand,
is that we either order the resources, and
order the forks, or we have a semaphore to
prevent one of the philosophers from even
entering the room.