So a quick reminder threads all share the
resources of the process, which means that
they have access to all the same memory access
to all the files access to everything that
the process has access to and each of the
individual threads work as a separate program
but they're all working towards the same goal.
So, if the process that we're talking about
is Microsoft Word the ultimate goal is to
create a document and print it, save it, do
something with it but the problem that runs
is that threads can run asynchronously.
The problem that we have is that these threads
are going to do work and that the work is
not done in a synchronous manner in other
words we don't have one thread running to
completion and then another thread starting
up we have all the threads running at the
same time and if we have multiple threads
running at the same time accessing the same
resources we have the potential for conflict
on those resources and we have to figure out
ways to deal with the conflict and address
the potential for catastrophic loss of information.