So what is asynchrony?
Well asynchrony occurs when two threads are
running seemingly at the same time.
So for example we might have a running thread
that is interrupted due to some hardware considerations
maybe the network card needs processing it
doesn't really matter and a different thread
is chosen to run.
So, we have one thread that's running on the
CPU and it stops running.
It does some work and it stops running and
then when we come back we're choosing a different
thread to run.
We could also have a thread that runs out
of time.
Remember we're in a preemptive system.
So we're not allowing threads to run until
they're finished we're not allowing processes
to run until they’re finished.
We're allowing them to run only for a certain
period of time and when that period of time
runs out whether or not the thread is finished
we have to pause the thread we have to bring
the thread out of the running state bring
it back into the ready state and then we can
go on to running either this thread or we
can choose a different thread to run.
So, there's a possibility of asynchrony there
and the other possibilities if we have actually
multiple CPU’s multiple different CPU’s
we can have two of these threads running on
the CPU all at the same time.
So, what's happening here is that these threads
are doing some work and the work that they're
doing it is not a complete atomic instruction
in other words we don't start it and know
when we finish it.
We don't do one function call and finish the
function call and then pause to run another
thread.
We could be in the very middle of an instruction
or in the very middle of a line of code and
we could stop and run a different thread altogether
so we always have to keep that in the back
of our minds when working with threads that
we never really know when the thread is going
to be stopped and when a different thread
and possibly a conflict thread would be run.