So sometimes code is going to be written with
the expectation that once we start running
a particular piece of code it's going to run
through with to completion without being interrupted
and we know from our discussion just a minute
ago that that's a fallacy we know that.
It's not going to be run as an atomic element.
It's not going to be run from start to finish
without interruption that interrupts are going
to happen in the system and that we're going
to stop this thread and started up again at
almost random intervals and in fact I would
say that we would consider the worst case
scenario and the worst case scenario is where
we have a real bad luck situation where we
run some piece of code stop at a really bad
place and choose a different piece of code
that conflicts with exactly the first piece
of code.
So the code is going to be interrupted and
we know that asynchrony can occur during interruption.
So we have to take that into account.
What we do is we identify those pieces of
code that have to be run atomically In other
words we identify those pieces of code that
once we start doing this code we can't be
interrupted.
Now unfortunately we can never say that we
can't be interrupted.
So the better solution is to say that we if
we are interrupted that no other thread is
allowed to go into that piece of code that
could conflict with us and what we're trying
to do is identify something known as a critical
section and a critical section is a piece
of code that once entered you have to prohibit
all other threads from entering the critical
section on the same resource.
If we have two different resources and two
different critical sections.
We can run both those critical sections at
the same time because the two different resources
don't conflict with one another but if we
have a critical section that operates on a
particular resource then we can't run one
critical section in conjunction with another
critical section or else we have asynchrony.
So, if we reach a critical section in thread
one for example then if thread one is interrupted
thread two can't enter its critical section
until thread one is allowed to complete.
So, if thread two wants to enter it's critical
section it has to be blocked it has to be
paused.
The critical section should be as small as
is possible because we don't want to spend
a lot of time blocking all the other processes
from accessing sections of code, their critical
sections if we don't have to.
So, we want this these pieces of code to be
absolutely as small as possible but we do
recognize that they exist and that they'll
have to be there.
So, there will be situations in which we block
other threads from running because we don't
want to have the possibility that those threads
are going to interfere with what we're doing
and once we're complete with that critical
section we’ll allow all the other threads
to continue running.