Windows device drivers, or device drivers
in general, are kernel layer software that's
written by the companies that designed the
hardware.
Now let’s take for example a video camera
that's built into your laptop computer, so
you might be looking up at the top of the
screen right now you see a little video camera.
That video camera was designed by a hardware
company and we don't know who designed it;
it may be some Apple company or some company
that Apple contracted with or perhaps it's
Logitech, which is one of the most popular
web cam companies perhaps Microsoft contracted
with, who knows.
Some hardware developer designed a web cam
and the manufacturer of your computer incorporated
that hardware design into their laptop so
that they could use the web cam.
Now when the hardware designers designed their
web cam, it works differently from one designer
to the next.
So, Logitech’s commands for taking a picture
are not the same as Microsoft's commands for
taking a picture, or Apple's commands for
taking a picture.
Whoever the hardware designer is, they designed
the chip so that it takes a picture after
it's given a certain command.
Now Microsoft doesn't want to have to know
all of the commands for all of the hardware
manufacturers that could possibly create a
web cam, so what they do is they provide a
facility for incorporating a piece of software
that the hardware designers will develop;
software that the hardware designers will
develop into the operating system and allow
it access to the camera so that it can program
the camera to take a picture.
Now what happens is Microsoft says if you
are a web cam designer you create these functions:
Take a picture, take video, turn on light,
whatever it is.
And if Microsoft calls the take picture function
then the code from that device driver does
whatever task is necessary in order to take
a picture and return it back to the operating
system in whatever way that Microsoft is expecting
it.
So, they define this protocol for communications
between the operating system and the device
driver. and then the device driver can do
whatever it needs to do in order to actually
take the picture and return it to the operating
system.
Now that works great, except for the fact
that these device drivers have complete unfettered
access to the entire operating system and
what they discovered was that while hardware
designers might be very good at designing
hardware, They're really not good at writing
software.
So, in the late one 1990’s and even in the
early 2000’s, Microsoft had a real problem
with device drivers causing device driver’s
code, which remember it’s code, crashing
and causing the entire system to become unstable
and eventually crashing the whole system in
what we call a “Blue Screen of Death.”
So what Microsoft did was design or specify
a lab… they created this lab that says:
if you're a hardware designer and you want
us to certify your drivers, send us your software,
send us the source code as well as a piece
of hardware, we’ll test it out, make sure
it's one hundred percent compatible with Microsoft
Windows and it doesn't cause a crash inside
the operating system.
It can't crash the operating system and as
long as everything's working properly and
we'll certify your driver and give it back
to you with the our stamp of approval.
And they call this the Windows Hardware Quality
Labs or WHQL.
And nowadays it's nearly impossible to install
in Windows ten or any of the later versions
of Windows, to install any drivers that are
not WHQL certified.
You have to go through an enormous process
to install those drivers, just for testing
purposes.
You basically certify that Microsoft, that
you know that Microsoft has no knowledge of
these drivers, and that it may destabilize
your system and cause mass floods and virus,
and I'm kidding about that.
But you know that you're doing something that's
outside of the ordinary.
So, the whole idea of the WHQL was that this
device driver code had so much access to the
system that if it was not written perfectly,
it would crash the whole operating system
and we don't want that.
So, we have avoided the whole “Blue Screen
of Death” now by having certified drivers
that are certified with WHQL.
And I think you can we can all agree anybody
who lived through that era of blue screens
of death, every day, if not multiple times
a day, we found the this is actually a very
good idea.