So, we covered a real basic of operating systems;
think just kind of the intro stuff.
We talked about what an operating system is,
we looked at some history of operating system.
We did talk about preemption remember that's
the stopping and restarting of a program,
even if it's not doesn't need to be stopped
and restarted.
We talked about the architecture of an operating
system.
We talked about a lot of things and we're
going to keep going with that.
And more discussions in later modules with
more of that we're going to cover on operating
systems, including further discussions on
processes and scheduling.
We're going to talk about memory management.
We're going to talk about threads and concurrency
issues.
So, we've got a lot to go over so keep going.