First, we need a definition of an operating
system and what I've come up with as a definition
is: a program that controls execution of application
programs and acts as an interface between
applications and computer hardware.
And we're going to delve into that a lot more
in later slides.
But what I want you to understand here is
that the operating system is a piece of software;
it's not a component of the of the computer.
So contrary to Apple's view when you buy a
computer, you don't necessarily buy an operating
system and that you can mix and match which
operating systems you want on which hardware
with some limitations.
Now the operating system does interact directly
with system hardware and it has to be very
closely matched to that system hardware.
So, it's not like we can mix and match any
operating system with any hardware; there
has to be some compatibility concerns there.
But if we take a look at the hardware for
example that Apple uses on all of their laptops
and desktops.
It's the exact same hardware as any PC In
fact, the CPU is the same, the system bus
is the same, the DMA controllers the same,
the interrupt controllers the same; all of
it is exactly the same as one made by HP or
Dell or any other PC manufacturer.
What makes the huge difference is the operating
system, and Apple has designed its operating
system only to work with their hardware, but
the operating system is a piece of software
fundamentally.
And it runs on the same processor as the user's
program code.
So, your programs that you're writing, your
‘hello world’ applications that you're
writing, those are running on the processor
which is the same processor as the operating
system.
So, we don't have more than one processor
in the system; let's keep it simple and consider
a system that doesn't have multi processors,
uni-processor systems what we call it.
The operating system has to divide the time
between itself running code for the operating
system to manage the hardware and manage the
execution of the whole system, and actually
running your program that you really care
about.
What the operating system doesn't include
is applications.
And this is going to be a big difference for
you to understand, because we'll talk about
it in a later slide.
When you go and buy an operating system from
Microsoft or something like that what you
get is a lot more than just the operating
system so, we're going to talk about that.
But I want you to think of the operating system
as the fundamental hard software that goes
along with the hardware for the computer.
It doesn't have to be directly matched to
the exact hardware; there can be some compatibility
for multiple operating systems to multiple
hardware.
But fundamentally we can talk about the operating
system being a piece of software that manages
this system hardware and runs applications.