It's good to have an idea, at least a visual,
of what we're talking about where the OS is
concerned.
So, the thing that you've probably experienced
as users of computers and we've all been users
of computers basically our whole lives we
interact with applications.
So, as a user, we are only interacting with
the application side of the computer.
So, when we look at Visual Studio, or when
we look at our Web browser, or when we watch
this video we're interacting with an application.
And we can control that application; we can
choose which website we're viewing, we can
type code into Visual Studio, or you can pause
and restart this video.
Don't pause and restart this video right now.
The thing that applications do is they'll
interact with the operating system.
So, in order for the for the application to
do what it needs to do, it needs to communicate
with the operating system.
For example, this video is going to need to
accept from the operating system a stream
of data from the network, and then process
that data and then display it on the screen.
So, we're using the operating system both
to read the data in as well as produce an
image on the screen as well as produce the
sound of my voice on the audio.
So, the application is going to use services
that the operating system provides to get
that done.
In your ‘hello world’ programs that you've
written before you've opened up files and
just the act of opening up a file is an operating
system call; it’s what we call a system
call.
We're asking the operating system for some
help.
So, as the application programmer, you've
interacted with the operating system by calling
a function like open and when an open opens
the file it was using the service of the operating
system.
The operating system of course is going to
need to interact with system hardware.
So, in order to open that file, it's got to
read from the hard drive and so the operating
system directly communicates with System hardware
to get the job done.
These are the layers of interaction that you
see.
So, the user is never directly interacting
with the operating system and the operating
so the application is never directly interacting
with system hardware; everything is insulated.