If we look at the system, as a whole the computer
system, what we can see is that it's a collection
of resources.
And the resources that we have are memory
and CPU time and file handles and network
connections and it goes on and on and on and
on; those can all be seen as a resource. and
the operating system, since it is the primary
controller of the entire system the first
software that will run, the operating system
controls all of those resources.
And it needs to allocate those resources to
some programs that you as a user decide to
run.
Now the operating system itself is software.
So, it's going to need to use some of those
resources; it's going to need some memory
for itself, it's certainly going to need to
run code so that CPU time, it may need files
to open up more connections or may need files
to open up more information, whatever has
to happen.
The operating system is a client of itself
in a lot of cases.
But the applications are really what the users
care about, when you as a user start up your
machine the forty five seconds or two minutes
or however long it takes to boot up your computer
and get to the screen where you can finally
do something: the desktop.
You consider that time wasted; you consider
that time that you can't do anything with
your computer.
And we try to minimize that time as operating
systems designers; we try to minimize that
time, so that you don't have to go to waste
that time, you can use that time for other
purposes.
For example, sleep mode on either a MAC or
a PC, when you close the lid the computer
goes to sleep rather than shut down altogether
so that when you open the lid again on a laptop,
it comes back to life and most immediately.
The way that we can do that is actually quite
simply the computer still running; it just
shuts down all the non-essential services
like the screen, and the wireless card and
things like that and it has uses a very, very,
very small amount of power to keep running
to continue keeping the memory active.
But the point is the resources that we have
are going to be allocated to different applications
as well as to the operating system.
And these resources are limited, so we have
to keep track of them and we have to make
sure that we're not wasting any of those resources.
There's going to be a lot of situations in
operating systems we concern ourselves with
this in the operating systems design classes
here at NYU, but one of the things we take
into account is that we might have an algorithm
which solves our problem perfectly but we
can't use it because it takes way too much
time to run that algorithm.
And if we did that it would actually slow
the system down as a whole.
So, even though the algorithm works perfectly
and doesn't exactly what we need to do, we
can't use it because it just takes too much
time to run.
So, the operating system has to dole out these
resources to various applications as well
as to itself, in a studious manner so that
it takes care of not wasting the resources
as well as allocating them effectively so
that the programs can do what they need to
do.