So let's take a look back at the old days
and see what used to happen, and that's going
to help us (bring us) up to speed on what
we do today.
And what I want to do is dial the clock back
to the era when mainframes really dominated
the computing industry, and what we're talking
about is the late maybe 1950’s, early 1960’s,
maybe even into the seventy's.
We generally had one computer and by that
I don't mean, we as an individual had one
computer, I mean the whole company, or the
whole university or the whole organization
would have one computer for the entire organization.
So, computing time was very, very limited
and we had to allocate that computing time
effectively.
The computer ran only one program at a time;
there's only ever one program running on the
computer at any given time.
We would not flip flop; we would not open
Chrome to view a web page, as well as, Excel
to start typing things into a worksheet or
so on and so forth.
We would not have two programs open at the
same time; there would be one program doing
some complex calculus, because it was almost
always math based, doing some complex calculus
to try and figure out the solution and when
it finished and found that solution it was
done and it would move on to another solution,
another program.
One program had complete access to all of
the system resources; it had access to all
of system memory, save for a small little
area for the operating system.
It had access to all of the CPU time.
This one program was started, processed all
of its data, ran through to completion, and
when it ended another program was started.
Now there was always a mainframe operator;
it was always a human being who decided which
order to run programs.
So, this was somebody who if you wanted your
program to run, if you knew your program had
to run early in the morning, you went to Dunkin
Donuts and got a dozen donuts and gave it
to the mainframe operator and he pushed your
program up a little further up in the stack;
make sure that you get that guy on your good
side or else your program is going to be the
last one to run in the day.
When one program finished the operating system
had to be ready with the next program.
So, the next program had to be ready to be
loaded into main memory and start executing
almost immediately.
The processor was really the limiting factor
in these older computers, so you'd bring in
everything that was needed for the one program
to run and then you'd put that program on
the processor and let it do whatever it wanted
to do until it said it was finished.
In order to do that you require some JCL and
JCL is what we call Job Control Language.
Job Control Language tells the operating system
what facilities: what printers, what files,
what network connections, anything that the
program needed.
The JCL would indicate that that program needed
it before even the program started.
So, imagine opening up Word and when you start
Word, it says list all the things that you're
going to need for this run of word and you
have to say I need these three files, and
I need this printer, and I'm going to need
this to save, and I'm going to need the spell
checker, and the grammar checker and all of
that.
You had to say that at the beginning of the
program, even in some cases you had to say
that before the program was compiled; so that
when you're creating a program you would have
to say what resources were going to be needed.
So that the operating system could make sure
that all of those resources were loaded and
ready to go immediately rather than having
to pick and choose.
So, if you didn't have JCL and your program
goes to open a file, the whole system has
to stop and wait until the file is actually
open and ready because you're the only program
that can run, and you only run…
You only stop when you're when you indicate
that you're completely done.
So JCL was a way for the operating system
to sort of pre-load some of the material.
And what we do is call this batch multiprogramming;
this is called batch multi programming because
we're getting things ready in main memory
and batching them creating a back of programs.
So, when one finished, the next program was
right there in the operating system and gets
it going immediately.
That's the olden days; we don't do that anymore.
And the reason that we can't do that anymore;
there's a lot of reasons actually, but we
don't think this way anymore.
We don't we don't think about getting one
job done and then moving on to the next job.
We'd like to do a lot of jobs at the same
time and the other downfall of this environment
is the JCL, that when the program starts we
might not know everything that we're going
to need; it might not be until we do some
processing that we finally know what we're
going to need.
So, this doesn't get done anymore and in just
a minute we're going to look at what we're
doing today.