Hi everyone.
Today we will start discussing the computer
organization section of this course.
We will learn about the innerworkings of the
CPU that allows it to execute its instructions
and we will discuss different methods to optimize
CPU performance.
So this is the outline for today.
We will go over instruction types and formats,
which are critical in determining how instructions
are executed.
We will then detail the execution steps for
a small processor that we will design.
We will then discuss processor clock rate
to estimate how fast our processor is, and
go over processor pipelining, its benefits,
and the issues it presents.