An I-format instruction has a 16-bit immediate
value as an operand.
An I-format instruction can also have up to
two registers, Rs and Rt.
Rt itself can be a source or a destination
registers, whereas Rs can only be a source
register.
Unlike R-format instructions, each I-format
instruction has a unique opcode.
Therefore, there is no need for a second opcode.
Let us see how the processor breaks down an
I-format instruction.
Consider the instruction above.
The processor first reads its opcode.
The opcode matches to the double word add
immediate instruction, which is an immediate
instruction or an I-format instruction.
Since the CPU knows that D ADD I uses two
registers Rs and Rt, it reads the two fields
for Rs and Rt to determine the register numbers.
The CPU then reads the 16-bit immediate value.
Once that is done, the CPU has all of the
operands of the instruction and can go onto
the next step.