OK.
Now, we are going to the steps the processor
go through when executing instructions.
We will use the example of building a processor
to illustrate these steps.
Our processor is based on MIPS64 and has only
7 instructions.
Our CPU can execute four R-format instructions:
D ADD, D SUB, D OR and D AND.
It can execute Load double and store double,
as well as branch if equal to zero.
When executing an instruction, a CPU generally
goes through the following steps: instruction
fetch, instruction decode, instruction execute,
memory, and WriteBack.
During instruction fetch, the CPU reads the
instruction from memory to determine what
it is.
The CPU uses the program counter to determine
the address of the instruction in memory.
During decode, the CPU determines the format
of the fetched instruction, the operation
the instruction is supposed to do, and gets
its operands.
The execute step performs the operation of
the instruction.
The processor goes through a memory step if
the instruction needs to do a data memory
access.
For example, a store instruction would go
through the memory step.
The processor goes through a WriteBack step
if the instruction needs to write the result
of its operation in a general purpose register.
For example, the DADD instruction needs to
write the result of its addition to the destination
register and must go through the WriteBack
step.
As we can see, an instruction may not go through
all the steps we have described.
However, each instruction goes through the
fetch decode and execute stages.