The figure here shows the state diagram of
our CPU.
Each state in the diagram has a unique numerical
ID, where the first state has the numerical
ID zero.
Each state encompasses an execution step of
the processor for a given operation.
State zero and state one of the diagram are
common for all instructions of our CPU because
the same operations are performed for fetch
and decode steps.
The diagram starts diverging at the execution
step because that is when the operations vary
according to the specifics of the instruction.
We see that from state 1, many arrows in the
diagram that transition from one state to
another and they are labeled by specific instructions.
This is to indicate which instructions need
those states at the end of the arrows.
For example, coming from state 1, if the CPU
is executing a Load double instruction it
has to go to state 2.
One important thing to note is that the last
state of each instruction always transitions
to the state zero, which is the instruction
fetch state.
For example, the last state for the Load double
instruction is state 4.
Once that is complete, the CPU goes to state
0, which.
This allows the processor to execute the next
instruction upon completion of the current
one.