For the arithmetic and logic R-format instructions,
the ALU of the CPU simply performs the operation
using the values of the registers Rs and Rt.
Recall that during the decode step, the CPU
already has Rs and Rt in A and B respectively.
The only thing that is an issue is how can
the ALU determine what operation to perform
for that R-format instruction.
Recall the second opcode or function field
of the R-format instruction.
The ALU has a lookup table that contains the
arithmetic or logic operation to perform based
on the value of the function field.
So, the CPU simply sends the value of A and
B registers and the value of the function
field of the R-format instruction to the ALU.
The latter used its table to perform the operation
and stores the result in ALU Out 2.