For the branch if equal to zero instruction,
the CPU must perform several operations during
the execute step.
It must calculate the target address of the
branch instruction, check the branch condition,
and update the program counter.
Let us first see how the CPU calculates the
target address for the branch instruction
Remember the formula for func2 that is used
to calculate the target address.
During the fetch step, the CPU already incremented
the program counter by 4, and during the decode
step, the CPU sign-extends the 16-bit immediate
value.
Those two calculations from fetch and decode
steps are needed to calculate the target address.
Therefore, during the execute step, the CPU
can simply shift the sign-extended immediate
value and add it to PC to calculate the target
address.
This target address is put in ALUOut1.
The next operation is to check the condition
of the branch if equal to zero.
To check if a value is equal to zero, the
CPU used the ALU to subtract that value with
zero.
The ALU has what is called a zero flag.
That is a one-bit output that is set to one
when the result of its operation is zero.
So, to check the condition, the ALU used the
BranchOp operation, which is a subtraction
of the Rs, which is in the A, and R0, which
holds 0.
If the subtraction is zero, then the zero
flag of the ALU is set to one.
The last operation is to update the program
counter if the branch condition is true.
For this, the CPU simply writes the target
address to the program counter if the value
of the zero flag is one.
Otherwise, the program counter remains its
original value from the fetch step where it
was incremented by 4.
It is important to realize that although the
branch if equal to zero instruction writes
to the program counter register, this is not
done at the WriteBack step.
This is because the WriteBack step is only
for general purpose registers R0 through R31.
The program counter itself is not a general-purpose
register.