So if we know that each state takes one clock
cycle, to find out how many states it takes
to execute a given instruction. Once can simply
add up all the states it goes through. Consider
for example the load double instruction. Like
all other instructions, Load double goes through
states 0 and 1 for fetch and decode. Then
load double goes to state 2 of the diagram
for execute, state 3 for memory, and state
4 for WriteBack. The instruction thus goes
to 5 states and thus takes 5 clock cycles.
Using this approach, we can calculate how
long it would take for our CPU to execute
a given code. For example, using this A = B
or C code, we use the high-level state diagram
to calculate the number of cycles each instruction,
then add the number of cycles of the instructions
together, and we estimate that our CPU takes
18 cycles to complete this code.
So, how fast is this CPU? Well, considering
the fact that modern low-end CPUs such as
the ones used in smart phones can execute
at least 4 instructions per cycle, our design
is not very fast. This is primarily because
in our current design, the CPU can execute
only one instruction at a time.