The main issues with a pipelined CPU are conflicts
that it encounters when executing multiple
instructions simultaneously.
These conflicts are commonly known as hazards
and are categorized in three groups: structural
hazards, data hazards, and branch hazards.
Structural hazards occur when multiple instructions
need to access the same CPU resource at the
same time.
Data hazards occur when an instruction needs
to read a data that is being modified by another
instruction.
And branch hazards occur when a branch instruction
is being executed and the CPU needs to know
if the branch is taken or not before it fetches
the next instruction.