Data hazards are relevant for instructions
that have dependency issues.
Let us use this example to illustrate such
dependencies.
At clock cycle 5, the third instruction reads
the value of R10 because it needs it for its
double word OR instruction.
However, the correct value of R10 is written
at clock cycle 6 by the second instruction,
that correct data is not available when the
OR instruction needs at cycle 5.
This is known as a read after write data hazard.
Note that although we use data in register
to illustrate data hazards, they can also
use for data that is in memory.
One way to overcome data hazards is via data
forwarding.
The basic idea of forwarding is to send data
to the execute stage as soon it is available
in the CPU.
Using our example, the value of R10 is available
in the CPU at clock cycle 5, because that
is when the memory accesses and puts it in
the load memory data register.
Therefore, the CPU can forward the data from
that load memory data register to the ALU
in the execute stage to guarantee that the
correct value of R10 is used for the doubleword
OR operation.
Another approach to mitigate data hazards
is by instruction re-ordering.
The basic idea here is for the compiler to
find independent instructions to put between
dependent ones to avoid data hazards.
This can be done as long as the re-ordering
does not modify the correctness of the code.
Consider the following example.
The instruction at address C8 depends on the
instruction at address C4 because the instruction
at address C4 first writes to R10 then the
one at C8 reads R10.
We also observe that the two instructions
at addresses D0 and D4 did not depend on any
of the instructions between C4 and D0.
Therefore, the result of the previous instructions
will not affect them if we move it up in the
code.
We can thus move the independent instructions
at D0 and D4 in between the dependent ones.
This creates two clock cycles extra between
the instruction that writes to R10 and the
one that reads from R10.
Therefore, when the instruction that reads
R10 is doing so at the decode stage, R10 is
at least being written to at that same cycle.
We know that since the compiler is responsible
for doing this re-ordering work, the addresses
of the instructions that are re-ordered are
modified to reflect where they are in the
code.
We also note that this instruction re-ordering
is not the same as out-of-order execution.
Out-of-order execution is an additional re-ordering
that is done dynamically by the processor,
not by the compiler.