I want you to look here at this image that
I have which is just list the levels of what
we consider the operating system, and this
is just a rough diagram; it's not really hard
and fast rule.
But what we've got on the very, very bottom,
the bottom four levels, are not really that
concerned operating systems per se except
that we have to interact with them.
So things like interrupts, procedures, processor
instruction sets, and electronic circuits
as operating systems designers: we don't get
any control over that.
Those get dictated by hardware designers,
computer engineers, not computer scientists,
which are going to design the electronic circuits
which are going to specify the processor instruction
set, which are going to deal with how we can
do procedures small bits of code you know
the small items that are built into the processor
itself, as well as interrupts that have to
occur inside the system.
We don't get to control much of that stuff,
but we do have to interact with it.
Now in the primitive processes phase, what
we're talking about are very low level pieces
of code that are parts of the operating system.
And in fact, if you look at those two dark
lines that I’ve drawn, levels five six and
seven are what we consider what's called a
microkernel; that's the minimum that's necessary
in order to have a functional operating system.
Primitive processes deals mostly with scheduling
and resource management.
Secondary storage obviously we have to access
all the other code and all the other components
of the operating system, as well as all the
other programs and data so that's a very low
level concern.
And then we have this concept of virtual memory
or even we can call it memory management,
which we'll talk about in a later module that
has to be managed.
So, we're going to need some, some fundamental
control over what's in main memory.
So, those three components are absolutely
necessary in order to have an operating system.
Now in the old days and I'm not talking about
back in the mainframe days, but really only
a couple decades ago.
What we can say is the rest of it would have
been included in what we call a macro kernel
or a large kernel, so the micro kernel has
only the smallest and most essential elements.
The macro kernel has everything: communication
systems communication, subsystems for getting
information into and out of the computer,
the file systems, Windows even has some components
that are built into the kernel, that are purely
for the file system.
But file systems concerns in an operating
systems like Linux and most Unixes, those
are an upper level concern outside of the
kernel, devices that we might connect to,
directories that are on the file system, any
user processes, and the shell, the shell being
really what you're interacting with.
In Windows, this is called explored dot EXE.
So, the shell is a component that the user
interacts with everything below that is down
to Level five, is a concern of the operating
system and everything below that is a concern
of system hardware.
But I just wanted you to get an idea of what
we what we look at, what we use, because each
of these levels use services of the levels
below them.
Virtual memory, for example, stores components
of processes on the secondary storage device
so the virtual memory system uses components
of the secondary storage uses services of
secondary storage.
And because virtual memory is higher, that
means we can use the services they exist already.
So, what we do is we provide services to the
layers above, to the levels above and then
we use the services of the levels below.
So, that's the way that this whole interaction
works but I want to you have an idea of the
core levels, if you will, of the operating
system.