I want to show you now, and I hope you don't
get too concerned by this image that you're
going to see, of what the inside of Microsoft
Windows looks like or at least what Microsoft
will tell us the Windows model looks like.
And I really want you to concentrate on a
few items that are below the line, below the
solid line.
What we're seeing here is the components of
the kernel, and in fact you can see that indication
that shows you kernel mode versus user mode;
user mode being above and kernel mode being
below.
Now the lowest level of here that we want
to consider is the HAL, the hardware abstraction
layer.
We're going to talk about that in just a minute.
But I also want you to see that there are
some other components for device drivers as
well as video drivers, a few things that have
to be built in.
There's a virtual memory manager; those components
that are the fundamental components of the
operating system are down there in kernel
mode.
Now if you remember back from the computer
architecture discussion.
There is kernel mode as well as user mode,
and we're going to talk about this a lot more
in later modules.
But kernel mode has complete access to the
entire system, whereas user mode has a much
more limited access.
So, what I want you to get away and take away
from this is that Windows is of course a very
complex model, it's been around it's been
being developed now for over thirty years,
so it's a very complex model.
But what I want you to see is that at the
very bottom there's only a few layers that
directly communicate even inside the operating
system with system hardware, and there's good
reason for that.
Inside the kernel mode, we just keep track
of processes and other things, most of the
work of the Windows kernel is actually done
outside of kernel mode.
And the reason for that is one of security
as well as organization and it's much easier
to update things that are outside of the kernel,
than things that are inside of the kernel.
So, take a look at this image just don't,
don’t memorize it don't, don't study it
too hard.
Just take away some of the major components
of it that you can at least keep track of.
And understand that modular operating system
design is really what we absolutely have to
do today, because there are so many things
that the operating system has to do just even
to run the first program.