The harder obstruction layer is a magic little
layer that Microsoft built in, and to understand
why Microsoft even needed the HAL in the first
place you have to look back again in history.
Sorry, but we're going to dial the clock back
again.
And go back to the mid, maybe the early 1990’s.
In the early 1990’s, Microsoft was not the
big player in the market that they are today.
If you look today, most computers and I say
most I mean almost all computers run Windows,
run Microsoft, some version of Microsoft Windows.
The latest indications that I have here in
2016 are that Microsoft Windows runs on between
91 and 92 percent of the hardware that's out
there.
So as far as computers are concerned, Apple's
market share is around seven to eight percent,
at least those among the numbers that I have
today; seventy to eight percent, whereas Microsoft
is ninety-one to ninety-two percent.
And there's that one-percent/two-percent other
which includes Linux and some Unix's.
In any case, back in the day, back in the
1990’s, early 1990's, that wasn't the case
at all.
The operating systems were broken down much
more towards about thirty percent was windows,
about thirty percent was Mac, and by Mac I
mean a completely different hardware architecture,
and then there was also thirty percent other
things like Unix's in these sorts of hardware.
And Microsoft wanted an operating system which
they could market literally to everybody,
and so what they did was they designed the
architecture in a modular fashion so that
the lowest level, the level that actually
communicates with the hardware.
Not manages things like running processes
and scheduling and dividing up memory and
allocating it, not that thing but the code
that actually communicates directly with the
DMA controller, the interrupt controller,
the hard drive, things like this that are
very, very, very low level.
Microsoft designed them into a component they
called the hardware abstraction layer.
And the hardware abstraction layer was a set
of functions that the kernel could call on
to perform tasks on different, on the various
hardware.
So, rather than directly programming the timer
in the system to say: let this process run
for twenty milliseconds.
The hardware abstraction, the operating system
would call a function inside the hardware
abstraction layer to say program the timer
to let this process run for twenty milliseconds.
And the reason that that's essential is because
Microsoft can change out the HAL and produce
an operating system that can now run on a
completely different hardware.
Without making any other changes to the operating
system, it can change just the functions inside
the HAL and those functions will, those features
will take effect on the new hardware.
And Microsoft did this in the early 90’s
and produced five different operating systems,
now they were all Windows NT 4 0 but they
were five different versions of Windows NT
4 0.
One for the Intel architecture, one for the
Power PC architecture, and there were various
other architectures that Microsoft could support.
Now over the course of the next five/ten years,
all of the other architectures disappeared.
Even Apple; now if you go and buy an Apple
Macintosh, you're going to buy a MacBook let's
call it, let's say a MacBook.
You're going to buy something that runs on
the Intel architecture, and that means that
it could run Windows just as well as it could
run MacOS.
And that's to our benefit of course because
we want to do that we want to do exactly that.
But Windows has the support for the HAL which
has support for multiple hardware, and when
Microsoft, for example, released Windows RT.
When it came out, Microsoft said we can now
support ARM architecture and the way that
they did that was in part changing the HAL.
So, any changes that we make to hardware,
really only require changing the HAL and that
saves us from having to rewrite the whole
operating system; it's a very effective tool.