Unix was designed to be a multi-user, multi-tasking
operating system.
And what that means is that we are designing
an OS which is going to run on a centralized
machine and have lots of users; not one person
sitting at a keyboard a screen but in fact
lots of users accessing this all the same
time.
And in the era of the mainframe computer,
when you didn't ever access the mainframe
computer; I remember people telling me stories
of writing their programs on punch cards and
leaving punch cards in companies for the mainframe
operators to load into the mainframe.
They never directly interacted with the mainframe
the whole idea of Unix was actually very nice
because you could directly use the mainframe
or directly use the computer.
Unix was designed to allow users to manage
their own tasks and this was one of the first
time sharing systems that came about and that's
why it was so popular because it decentralized
responsibility.
Your users only got a very small portion of
the time allowed to run on the system and
nobody could take too much time on the system
or too much resources, I should say.
But it was allowed to access directly the
mainframe, and do your work directly on the
mainframe and have immediate feedback rather
than delayed feedback whenever the mainframe
operators cited for your program to run.
The other thing about Unix that was great
was that it was released into the public domain
with open source.
When you got UNIX you didn't just get the
operating system; you also got the source
code.
And it was released in the public domain with
public licensing, public domain licensing,
so that if you made any modifications to the
Unix operating system You could re-release
it as your own, except that you couldn't charge
for it.
So, you couldn't take the Unix operating system
and make one change and sell it for hundreds
of dollars; It wasn't allowed.
In fact, all they allow for is what's called
a media charge So a few dollars for the cost
of the media on which you would distribute
the source code, and you had to release the
source code as well for whatever changes.
Now Unix comes in a lot of different flavors
comes in AIX, Linux, Solaris, etcetera like
that.
And some of them are branches of the original
UNIX, so they're now public domain which means
if they made any if they used any of the original
source code of Unix, or any subsequent source
code of Unix, they have to be public domain.
There are some companies like IBM who designed
AIX from scratch to look like Unix, but include
none of the source code of Unix so that they
could license it and sell it and make money
off of it.
So, there are some versions like that.
And that's how Apple gets away with selling,
or what they used to, sell MacOS was because
they used BSD, which was a completely new
implementation of Unix; it didn't use any
of the original Unix.
So, Unix has been modified many, many, many,
many times over the years, but what we have
is this basic idea of a multi-user multi-tasking
operating system.