It's time to start talking about operating
systems and in this module we're going to
cover a few things about operating systems
and get you prepared for the future modules
which cover the rest of operating systems
concerns or at least some of the basics of
operating systems.
What we want to take away from this is a fundamental
understanding of how computer operating systems
first work and what they're expected to do,
and then how we can understand them and utilize
them either as programmers or if you want
operating systems designers.
So, in this module we're going to cover what
is an operating system.
We're going to cover a little bit history
of operating systems, so you can understand
how we got to this point today.
We're going to talk about preemption and how
we do scheduling of different programs that
are running on the system.
And then I'm going to talk about a basic architecture
of an operating system.