I want you to consider that when you go to
the Comp USA, or I guess Comp USA doesn't
exist anymore.
If you go to Best Buy or even if you go to
the Microsoft store and you buy Windows, what
you're buying is not an operating system;
you're buying a lot of other stuff in that
operating system.
In that box comes a CD that is filled with
ninety nine percent stuff that has nothing
to do with your operating system.
The operating system as we're concerned is
the kernel, and the kernel in Microsoft Windows
for example is about twenty five megabytes.
Now you say what comes on a CD for four gigs
when the operating system itself is only twenty
five or thirty megabytes, well all the other
stuff.
The extra stuff that you get are web browsers,
like Edge (I don't know who's using Edge yet)
but let's say Edge, Internet Explorer, text
editors, device drivers, really any other
application that comes on that CD, calculator,
minesweeper, solitaire.
those will come with the CD but they have
nothing to do with the operating system.
Linux on the other hand, for example, you
can just download the kernel.
If you go to www.kernel.org; you can see that
what you can download is just the kernel.
It comes with no text editors, it comes with
no web browsers, it comes with some device
drivers for stuff that supported directly
in Linux.
But fundamentally the thing that we want to
concern ourselves with is this kernel.
And the kernel is really only the very small
components that, we'll talk about this and
in a later slide, but really the just the
very small components that are necessary to
bring the system up online and start running
other programs.
And really that's not very much but what you
buy in the store is a lot more stuff.