Today we have a lot of processing power and
we have a lot of memory: eight gigs, sixteen
gigs, thirty-two gigs.
I've worked on machines that have one-hundred
and ninety-two gigs of memory, not hard drive
but memory.
and we have enough to run multiple programs
at the same time what we really want to do
is what's called multitasking.
We want to have the ability to open up a web
browser, as well as open up Microsoft Word,
as well as open up Microsoft Excel, as well
as open up anything else that we want to open
up at the given time.
So, in order to do that the operating system
has to become a resource manager, and what
we do is allocate resources to the various
programs that want to run them.
And then the operating system decides which
programs can run and which programs, and when
they can run.
The operating system will be responsible for
stopping and restarting running programs and
this is what we call preemption.
Now when we restart a running program, we
don't start over from the beginning we start
from where we left off.
So, you may not have realized this in your
‘hello world’ programs but your hello
world programs didn't start and run straight
through to the end; they were stopped and
restarted many, many, many times.
Not from the beginning just from where we
left off.
So, it's sort of like the operating system
lets the program do a couple of instructions,
in reality it's going to be a lot of instructions
but let's say a couple of instructions, and
then it stops and it saves everything in the
registers and saves all the information in
the CPU and it goes on to doing something
else entirely.
And when it comes back to decide that your
program is going to run again, all it has
to do is restore those values to the CPU and
let it run.
The instruction pointer, sorry… the instruction
register, the program counter, all the AX,
BX: all those registers that are in the CPU
are going to be saved and restored.
So, your program picks up from where you left
off; you don't actually have to restart the
whole process over from scratch it will just
stop and restart.
And this is what we call a timesharing system.
Now the reason that your program stops might
be because it wants to stop; it might want
to do something that takes a very, very long
time.
So the operating system says, let's say opening
up a file which takes a fairly significant
amount of time on the order of let's say fifteen
or twenty milliseconds.
The operating system will say okay, if you're
going to open up that file, there's no reason
that you're going to run anymore until I have
that file open.
So, we'll save your settings your registers
in the CPU, we’ll call your state and then
we'll run something else.
We'll do some other code; we’ll run another
program, we'll do anything else.
And when your file is loaded and ready to
go.
We'll bring you back and reload those registers
into the CPU and let you run again because
now we have your file available.
So the operating system does this very, very
quickly and it really does this hundreds or
even sometimes thousands of times per second
inside the system, and in doing so it creates
an environment that we call a time sharing
system.
And it allows us to run very many applications.
So, if you're on a Windows PC right now, you
can hit control shift escape and you bring
up the Task Manager; you go over to performance
and you can see how many programs, how many
processes are actually running, and that's
probably in the order of between seventy and
one-hundred, maybe even more processes that
are running.
If you're on a Mac, you can go to the activity
monitor in the Applications Utilities folder
and you can see that same information.
So, what we're saying is that in today's environment,
going back to the batch multiprogramming days,
is something that we absolutely could not
do; we don't even think that way anymore.
If you were restricted to only running Microsoft
Word and you could never get out of Microsoft
Word and go into a web browser and go into
absolutely anything else or any other program,
would you even be able to write a paper and
I doubt it very much.
But that's the way we worked in old environments;
today we don't expect to work that way.
So today we're doing multitasking and we're
doing time sharing.