In the modern operating system, we load a
lot of programs and they’re load all of
the same time all in main memory.
And if we take that into a bigger account,
you may even run chrome multiple times on
the same system.
So, now we've got two copies of Chrome loaded
into loaded into the operating system; how
do we keep track of which version of Chrome
is running and really which instance, if you
will, of Chrome is running?
And the way we do that is called a process
and we're going to talk about this extensively;
in fact, we have an entire module on processes
that's coming up next.
But what I need to know understand is that
when we load a program into main memory, we
create an object (if you will) called a process
to keep track of that program to see how long
it's been running to record when it's ready
to record when it's busy to record when a
file opened for this for this process.
We keep track of it by creating a process
and then we have struck the idea that this
is a program and instead it becomes a process.
The code for the program can be loaded multiple
times or not depending on how we how we implement
the operating system, but we can consider
that this process is a unique object all to
itself and doesn't interact with any other
process in the system.